<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The confirming worke of religion ..., or, The true and infallible way for attaining a confirmed state in religion ... with a short and confirming prospect of the work of the Lord about his church in these last times / by R. Fleming ...</title>
            <author>Fleming, Robert, 1630-1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 263 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 85 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B23015</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1263A</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19373280</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19373280</idno>
            <idno type="VID">205486</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B23015)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 205486)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1669:41)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The confirming worke of religion ..., or, The true and infallible way for attaining a confirmed state in religion ... with a short and confirming prospect of the work of the Lord about his church in these last times / by R. Fleming ...</title>
                  <author>Fleming, Robert, 1630-1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 105, [3], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Reinier Leers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Rotterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXV [1685]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Popular works.</term>
               <term>Providence and government of God.</term>
               <term>Faith.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:205486:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CONFIRMING WORKE OF RELIGION, In its neceſſity and uſe briefly held forth; that each Chriſtian may have a proper <hi>ballast</hi> of his own, of the grounds and reaſons of his faith, and thus ſee the greatneſſe of that <hi>ſecurity,</hi> on which he adventures his eternal ſtate.</p>
            <p>OR The true and infallible way, for attaining a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed ſtate</hi> in Religion, from theſe primary evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences and demonſtrations of our faith; which the Lord hath himſelf given, ſo as it may be eaſy for the meaneſt in the Church to know the ſame, and be ready to render an account thereof to all that ask.</p>
            <p>With a short and confirming proſpect of the work of the Lord about his Church, in theſe laſt times.</p>
            <p>BY R. FLEMING, <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At ROTTERDAM, Printed by REINIER LEERS. M.DC.LXXXV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:205486:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205486:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ſmall Eſſay, here offered, is on the greateſt ſubject, can fall under the conſideration of mankind; and is a ſtudy, was never more preſſingly called for, then in theſe dayes, for men to be making peace with God, and to have ſuch an aſſurance of his truth, as can fully quiet and ſupport the ſoul, though all ſenſible props should be brocken, and fail. Great changes doe ſurely haſten on this generation, and the <hi>life of faith,</hi> is in an other manner like to be put to tryal, then ſince the Churches riſe and recovery from <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian</hi> bondage. The ſtorme now viſibly grows upon the Churches of Chriſt, though nothing is thus to faint or shake, the ſpirits of any, who know their anchor is ſure and caſt within the vail; but the ſtrongest difficulties, in following the Lord, when overcome, yeelds the greateſt vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and will be not only matter of joy here, but to all eternity, in having with patience and hope indured, and got well through a throng of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and aſſaults in a reſolute adherence to the truth. If men think it their wisdome to ſecure their private intereſt, by dividing it in ſuch a time from the publick cauſe of the Reformed Church, and make light of the greateſt truths of God now aſſaulted, of the blood of the Martyrs, yea of their own eternal ſtate, by any coolneſſe or shrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="tcp:205486:3"/>from the ſame; they will find no temporal motives, can ever compenſe that loſſe and ruine which inevitably will meet ſuch in the iſsue, yea that theſe words of <hi>Mordecai to Eſther, Eſth. 4: 13, 14.</hi> have the ſame voice, and weight in this day. What is held forth in the following worke, I may with humble confidence ſay, was under ſome preſſure to have ſuch clear evidence and quieting perſuaſion of divine truth, as made it leſſe eaſy to have my own ſpirit ſatisfyed herein, then poſſibly it may be to others; for if it were not from that bleſſed aſſurance of the Lords being God, of the revelation of Chriſt, and of the glory to come, I should not know what could be confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or make a rational being deſireable. Some ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulare ingadgments I judge my ſelf alſo to ſtand under, for putting to my ſeal to the truth and faithfulneſſe of God in his word, from many ſignal confirmations hereof in the courſe of my pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, if ſuch a poor teſtimony might be of any weight. Let the bleſſed Lord, gratiouſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this ſmall offering to him, and for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of his truth, by ſo mean an inſtrument, and give ſome fruit hereof, that may abide, and be found in the day of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I hope the Reader may find by a peruſal of the I. Chap. of what ſerious uſe and intent the II. is; yea that in this day it was not unſeaſonable or incongruous to the forgoing ſubject what is held forth in the III. Chapter. But oh it is ſad and amazing to think how few are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that weight of Religion, as once to have a ſerious inquiry on the grounds and reaſons thereof, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt the moſt ſpecial aſſiſtances to their faith to be the greateſt helpers of their joy within time.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:205486:3"/>
                  <head>THE True and infallible WAY For attaining a confirmed ſtate in RELIGION, &amp;c.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAPTER I. <hi>The Primitive Confirmation in the truth of Chriſtianity, held forth and cleared, in its continued neceſſity and uſe to this day, in a few Poſitions.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat nothing can have a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſad and threatning aſpect on the preſent ſtate of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in all the churches of Chriſt, <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>I</label> then that utter eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trangment, moſt are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to the true grounds of faith, and to thoſe foundamental differences betwixt Chriſtianity, &amp; every falſe way, which no pretended religion can lay claim to. The reaſons of the <hi>Poſition,</hi> are theſe. I. That it is too viſibly manifeſt, how no men in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:205486:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>world know ſo little of their own profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, were it of any human art or ſcience, as ſuch who bear the name of Chriſtians, or are ſo generally ſtrangers to the truth and firmneſſe of the principles therof, for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining either a due valuation, or powerful ſenſe of the ſame on their ſoul; ſo that an implicit and <hi>traditional profeſſion</hi> is the only part and propriety which moſt can claim in the truth, and doctrine they profeſſe. II. That ſo rare alſo is any ſuch ſerious worke amonghſt men, as a perſonal inquiry and tryal, if there be indeed ſuch a thing as an <hi>experimental and ſoul quickning religion</hi> in the earth, that can bear the expenſe of the moſt diſmal and afflicting times, and hath ſo great a temporal revenue lying therto, as peace with God, an immediate communion with him, the joy and comforts of the <hi>H. Ghost,</hi> when under ſuch preſſours of trouble as are above the ſupport of nature. III. That the furtheſt account, why moſt goe under the name of Chriſtians, rather then of any other forme, can riſe no higher then cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and education, that it did beſpeak them from their birth, and was the religion of their anceſtours, yea become in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner naturall to them, as the cuſtomes and language of their country; which are grounds that should determine to the very
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:205486:4"/>oppoſite profeſſion, if they were ſtated un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame circumſtances, and had the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me motives to be <hi>Mahumetans;</hi> ſince it is ſure theſe can found no other aſſent, then is ſuitable to the nature and ſtrenth therof IV. That thus it cannot be under debate, how the moſt numerous part of viſible pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours, are ſo deſtitute of any defenſe from internal motives, and ſolid conviction of the truth they profeſſe, upon its own evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; as there was never more cauſe to fear, ſome unuſual apoſtacy from the very viſible profeſſion of Chriſt, upon any violent try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and aſſault this way, when ſuch finds it more eaſy to render up their religion, then to adhere to the ſame, under ſtrongh temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, who yet never knew that ſubſtance, advantage, or certainty herein, as could preponderate with the want of all external motives for ſuch a profeſſion.</p>
                     <p>That thus one of the higheſt ſervices of theſe times, <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>II</label> for the publik good of the Church, does convincingly lye here; to have <hi>the faith of aſſent</hi> to the truth and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Chriſt, in a clear and firme certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the judgment, on its own evidence, more vigorouſly promot, and the proper means and aſſiſtances, which the Lord hath given for this end, in ſome other manner yet improven, then ſeems to be this day,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:205486:5"/>for a more univerſal uſe. The grounds to inforce the neceſſity hereof, are theſe; I. that its ſure wherever the Goſpel is revealed to men, it comes with ſo full an aſſurance of underſtanding, and ſufficiency of objec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive evidence, as can admit no poſſible doubtfulneſſe herein, which is the credit and glory of our religion, that in no other way it doth require acceptance, but with the furtheſt conviction of evidence. II. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the expreſſe deſigne and tendency of this bleſſed revelation, is no leſſe to found ſuch a <hi>rational aſſurance</hi> in the judgment, of its truth, then to ingadge their will and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, for imbracing therof; and though ſuch great demonſtrations for this end can only, <hi>in ſuo genere,</hi> have a convincing influence to perſwade the underſtanding, yet are they of ſuch weight here, as next to the demonſtration of the Spirit of God, they are the greateſt means to bring up mens aſſent to a full and quieting reſt on that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity to which they muſt concredite them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for ever, and to let them ſee, that this even here by the way, is aſſuredly full, though not yet their injoyment. III. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this faith of aſſent, should be firſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in the order of nature, as being the very firſt principle of converſion, to know and be ſure, that God hath ſent his ſon into
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:205486:5"/>the world to ſave ſinners; wherin as the <hi>H. Ghoſt</hi> is not the objective, but the efficient cauſe here of our faith, ſo is not the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal worke and teſtimony he gives on the ſoul the firſt teſtimony, but muſt ſtill have reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to the revelation of the word without, and ſuch demonſtrative evidences therof, wherwith it is revealed to the world, nor may ever be ſeparate, that which God hath himſelf ſo indiſſolubly joyned. IV. That ſo convincing a neceſſity and uſe is hereof to the Church, and in a ſpecial way with reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to the youth, for a more firme laying of the groundwork of their Chriſtian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and to be as the ſeed-plot of a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and deſirable grouth amonghſt ſuch in this day; that they might thus know early, ſomething of theſe primary grounds and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of their faith; ſo alſo is it a ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of that high importance, as I humbly jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, should be of notable uſe for a Manuduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the firſt place to ſtudents of <hi>Divinity,</hi> before they launch forth in that vaſt and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe ocean of the ſpeculative part therof; and for being at ſome greater advantage thus for carying on ſuch a confirming worke in the Church in their future ſervice. V. Yea of what uſe might this be with reſpect to many, who may be ſore haunted, with hid and dreadful temptations to infidelity, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:205486:6"/>to weaken them on the very foundations of their faith; who are wholly unfurnished of any ſuch grounds and arguments in their judgment to repel the ſame: and it is ſure, to believe firmly the hiſtory of the Goſpel, <hi>that God was manifeſted in our nature,</hi> to ſave man, is with reſpect to the object a much higher act of faith, then to believe, that he will ſave us; ſince as the one doth unſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kably more tranſcend all human reaſon then the other, ſo doth the Apoſtle thus argue from the greater to the leſſe, Rom. 8: 32. <hi>That he who gave his own ſon to the death; will he not alſo with him give us all things.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That ſuch a confirming worke, <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>III</label> was moſt ſpecially followed in the practize of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times, and one of the great ends of the miniſtry of the <hi>Apoſtles and Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts,</hi> to have this faith of aſſent and doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal certainty therof, on its proper grounds and evidences, deeply founded in mens judgment; is ſo clear, as cannot come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der debate. I. That this way did the great author of our profeſſion himſelf take, not only by the authority of his word, and the power and energy of grace, but with that convincing evidence and demonſtration of his truth to mens underſtanding, as might found alſo a firme and rational aſſurance he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof. II. That for this end, he did pray
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:205486:6"/>the Father, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17:21. and was ſo much preſſed herein, that ſo great an external de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the truth of the Goſpel, in the concord and unity of his people, might be kept clear, that the world might thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that he was ſent of God, and have a dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per conviction hereof ſerved on them, by ſuch an evidence. III. That one ſpecial intent of the Evangel of Luke, was for this end, <hi>Luke</hi> 1:4. that men might know not only the things themſelves by a naked relata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but the certainty of theſe things, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they had been formerly inſtructed. IV. That herein did the miniſtry of <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los</hi> ſo brightly shine forth, <hi>Act.</hi> 18: 28. and was then of moſt ſingulare uſe to the Church, by that clearneſſe of rational con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction and demonſtrative arguments for the truth of Chriſt, as the greateſt gain ſayers could not withſtand. V. That its ſure it was then without exception, expreſſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of the meaneſt within the Church, to be allways ready to render the reaſons of their hope to all who ask; and not only to know what they did believe, but why they did ſo, as is clear 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3:15. yea that this could not be by bringing forth of internal evidences, for conviction of others, but to give them an account of the moſt cogent grounds and demonſtrations of the Goſpel,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:205486:7"/>as might be moſt prevalent, and confirming to the weak, and leave others inexcuſable; and ſeems to have been then ſpecially preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in theſe primitive times, as a proper teſt of their Chriſtian profeſſion. VI. And we ſee herein alſo, how much theſe excellent <hi>Bereans</hi> were taken up, and were ſo highly commended of the <hi>H. Ghoſt, Act.</hi> 17:11. to know the <hi>demonſtrative</hi> part of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and by its own evidence, with that intire harmony and conſent of the Scripture therin, and their being thus diligently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in that comparing-worke of religion, to ſee the truth therof not ſingly and apart by themſelves alone, but in that joynt union and coherence, wherin they ſtand, each in their own room, for confirming and giving light to other. VII. That this was the way alſo, wherin the Goſpel did come to the Gentil church is cleerly shewed 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1:5. <hi>Not in word only, but as in power, and in the H. Ghoſt, ſo alſo in much aſſurance of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, upon its own evidence;</hi> which was that way, it did ſo wonderfully prevail over the world againſt nature, and ſtream of flesh and blood, that ſtood in the furtheſt oppoſition therto. VIII. That one of the greateſt ſervices of the Apoſtles in their viſiting the Churches, did expreſly ly here <hi>Acts</hi> 14:22. to confirme the ſouls of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:205486:7"/>the Diſciples in the firſt place on the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of their faith, and then in exhorting them to continue in the ſame, ſo as they might follow the Lord, with the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt light and aſſurance of mind, amidſt the great tryalls of ſuch a time. IX. That its this way alſo the world is rendred inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable for their misbeliefe of the Goſpel, when under ſuch ſufficiency of means given for this end, by ſo great a diſcovery of the confirming evidences of its truth, ſo as they can have no pretence herein, but an obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy and reſolution not to be convinced; on which ground doth our bleſſed Lord teſtify, that it was no want of light, upon the certainty of his truth, why men did not receive it, but that they loved darkneſſe better then light, becauſe their deeds were evil; &amp; when ſuch clear, rational, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing evidences are laid open to their view, how moſt poſſibly can get theſe put by or rejected, is not eaſy to comprehend, but that a real irritation and torment of ſpirit, from ſuch clearneſſe of evidence, doth thus more tend to harden then convince.</p>
                     <p>That there is a continued neceſſity of ſuch <hi>a confirmation in the faith</hi> to this day, <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>IV</label> what ever can be objected of ſo long a conſent and preſcription of time in the profeſſion therof, is fully demonſtrable on theſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:205486:8"/>grounds. I. Becauſe it is ſure, the Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian faith doth ſtill need theſe aſſiſtances; and is a ſtrang miſtake, that only for <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, and Atheiſts,</hi> ſuch confirming evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of the ſame should be adduced, but not for any under a viſible profeſſion, when the whole of <hi>divinity,</hi> and <hi>doctrine</hi> of <hi>our faith,</hi> is ſo full of demonſtrative arguments, for the dayly uſe of the moſt eſtablished Chriſtians in their paſſage through time. II. That as the higheſt motives to all ſerious godlineſſe and the moral duties of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity muſt needs be from its known certainty to us, ſo is the continued uſe therof to be ſtill the ſame. III. That theſe numerous tryalls and conflicts of Chriſtians now, doe no leſſe call for ſome higher eſtablishment in the truth on which they muſt alone reſt, when all viſible props fail in their judgments, then of ſupporting grace; nor is it concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable how men can this day walk in the light of any true joy and comfort, without a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſollid aſſurance of their being on ſafe grounds herein then moſt ſeem to reckon. IV. Becauſe the revelation of the Goſpel and of an eternal ſtate in an other world, is ſo great and wonderfull as its ſtrang how this is not the higheſt intereſt of mens life, to have their faith more deeply confirmed on the furtheſt tryal of their ſecurity now
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:205486:8"/>by the way herein, who muſt shortly make ſo great a tryal therof at death; for if we we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re but once this length to ask our own ſoul, what the <hi>Chriſtian faith</hi> indeed is, and are thus called to believe, it could not poſſibly but beget ſome extaſy of wondering at the greatneſſe therof, and to reckon any light and implicit aſſent to the ſame as a degree both of Atheiſm &amp; indifferency in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. V. Though there be no conflict with <hi>Heathens</hi> as in the <hi>firſt times,</hi> yet was ſuch a ſpirit never more aloft then it is now to take of all firm aſſent to the greateſt principles of truth, when <hi>Atheiſme</hi> ſeems to be at its <hi>ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timus conatus</hi> in the world, and we are fallen in ſo amazing an hower of the power of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as makes theſe latter times more remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kably perillous and trying then the firſt. VI. Yea if ſuch a confirming worke, be one of the greateſt means to advance the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute and honour of religion, when its won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted awe and veneration is ſo far loſt, and to awake men to deeper impreſſions of its truth, when ſo few ſeeme now under any ſuch weight; then it is ſure there was never more need of the ſame then in this day.</p>
                     <p>That ſuch a ſervice to the <hi>Church,</hi> 
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>V</label> doth not only reſpect the more knowing, inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive, and judicious part therof, but the meaneſt profeſſours of religion alſo, of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:205486:9"/>whom this is neceſſarly required, is evident on theſe <hi>grounds.</hi> I. Becauſe each Chriſtian should have undoubtedly ſuch a <hi>ballaſt</hi> on their own ſoul, of the ſolid and rational grounds of their faith, as well as theſe of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter parts and induments: the promotting of which were it more deeply conſidered, I da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re humbly adventure to ſay, should be found one of the choiceſt meanes to promot Chriſtianity this day. II. Becauſe this is not to drive any to doubt or queſtion the leaſt ſincere degree of <hi>aſſent,</hi> though it be not with ſuch ſtrenght of evidence as in others, nor can by that formal argumenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion give the ſame accompt therof; ſince a few grounds this way may ſpecially help to ſome ſolid conviction and confirming of their mind, when they may be ignorant of many other cogent arguments for this end; but its ſure alſo the greater clearneſſe of evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence doth ſtill in the appointed way of means lead in to a more firme and ſtrong aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the judgment, to the truth of our religion. III. Becaus the ſtrenth of the foundation in it ſelf cannot be enough if it be not with ſuch a known evidence, as men may build firmly and with aſſurance theron; nor hath the Lord thus only deſigned to gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve his people an infaillible and ſure teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to adventure on, but that it should be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:205486:9"/>made ſure alſo to them. IV. Becauſe none can in truth ſay that <hi>Jeſus is the Lord but by the H. Ghoſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 22:3. by which is not to be underſtood ſo much there, the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of ſupernatural grace, for a ſaving faith, but that none can give a true aſſent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the ſame, but from theſe grounds and arguments which are revealed by the <hi>H. Ghoſt</hi> unto men for this end; and as its ſure that theſe <hi>characters and evidences of divinity,</hi> which are imprinted on the whole revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Goſpel, may be clear &amp; demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrative to our judgment, ſo are they as tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>divine,</hi> as the doctrine which is confirmed therby. V. Becauſe there can be no poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible cauſe for credulity of the truth from any intricate obſcureneſſe of the ſame, when the Lord hath given ſuch great aſſiſtances to our faith to be <hi>as milk for babes</hi> as wel as <hi>meat to ſtrong men.</hi> And though it be objected that the furtheſt objective evidence of the Goſpel, with ſo clear and ſtrong a convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance therof, is yet ſo little operative on moſt; the ſame might be ſaid alſo of the whole let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Scripture; but as this tends not in the leaſt to reſolve our religion into any meer exerciſe of reaſon, and leaves the who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le worke of the Spirit, in its energy and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration therwith on mens ſouls, intire; yet doth it fully evince ſuch a ſufficiency of evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:205486:10"/>with the Chriſtian faith, as makes any doubtfulneſſe herein ſimply impoſſible, through want of the greateſt advantage of means; yea ſuch as are of another kind then to induce only a <hi>probable perſwaſion</hi> of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. VI. Becauſe it is one of the ſaddeſt ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes of the preſent ſtate of religion, that ſo few almoſt in whole congregations can give any clear aſſent to the truth and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thereof, but to amazement both live and dye ſtrangers to the ſame, yea how many of theſe who are otherwiſe ſerious in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, yet have their <hi>faith ſtarved</hi> this way, and are deſtitute of any ſuch ſupport; but as it is not the <hi>numberouſneſſe of profeſſours,</hi> but the <hi>ſtrength and ſolidity of their faith,</hi> wherein the Churches ſtrength moſt lyes, and hath more ſlowrished in a few ſuch to beget a greater awe and veneration of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion amongſt men, then at other times in the greateſt multitude; ſo is it the glory of divine truth, that it can ſubſiſt by its own proper evidence, and preſerve its ſtation in the worſt of times, when all external argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments does moſt viſibly ceaſe.</p>
                     <p>That its thus fully demonſtrable and clear, <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>VI</label> how no ſimple inſtructing of men in the <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral principles of religion,</hi> can be the proper and adequate mean for ſuch a faith of aſſent to the truth thereof, on its own evidence,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:205486:10"/>or anſwer that <hi>Apoſtolick pattern of laying the foundation, Hebr.</hi> 6:2. but that ſome ſpecial duties elſe are called for to ſo high an end; ſuch wherein not only that true primitive confirmation in the Chriſtian faith might have ſome practical uſe, but we might alſo hope therewith, for a more remarkable out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letting of confirming influences of the Spirit of God. What is to be underſtood herein I shall humbly offer in a few <hi>particulars.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">I. That it is one of the greateſt concerns of the <hi>miniſterial worke,</hi> and of the <hi>key of doctrine,</hi> to have all who heare the Goſpel, in the <hi>Firſt</hi> place preſſed to take religion ſo far to heart as to have a ſerious inquiry on the grounds and reaſons hereof, and thus to know their being on ſure ground herein, not becauſe they know not another way, but becauſe they know this is the alone way of truth, to which they dar truſt their immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſoul. II. That for this end the ſupreme truths of religion be repreſented with that certainty of <hi>evidence, and demonſtration,</hi> as both ſuch great and marvelous things does require, and the temper of ſuch a gainſaying age now calls for; and to have this preſſed more on mens judgment and conſcience, that the <hi>things of God,</hi> which are of the <hi>higheſt conſequence, reality, and ſubſtance,</hi> can have no poſſible reception by any implicit or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:205486:11"/>belief thereof, nor can admit any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for the ſame, when the Lord hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſuch kind of proofes and evidence, as leaves mens darkneſſe herein, without any shaddow of excuſe.</p>
                     <p n="2">II. That it peculiarly belongs to the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techetical work of religion</hi> to take ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of the meaneſt profeſſours thereof, and with a ſpecial reſpect to the <hi>youth;</hi> of their <hi>faith of aſſent</hi> to the doctrine of Chriſt, on what <hi>grounds</hi> and certainty of evidence this is founded, and for their inſtructing therein, as well as in the <hi>general principles</hi> of religion; when one of the moſt ruining things to the Church lyes here, that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of moſt is layed in ſo deep an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, as they have almoſt nothing to ſay for the ſame, but a naked affirmation. I know the difficulty hereof for the weak may be objected, but without juſt cauſe; ſince as the prime truths of religion are few, eaſy and plaine for the meaneſt capacity, ſo alſo are the <hi>primary evidences and demonſtrations of our faith,</hi> if ſuch once with that deſire did ſearch after the ſame as for a hid and invalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble treaſure; wherein this reſpect should be ſtill had, to difference betwixt what is ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial and of a more fundamental concern for the weak, and what may tend to an higher grouth and increaſe of others.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:205486:11"/>III. It should be of greateſt uſe and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage alſo for the ſame end, that the <hi>young grouth</hi> now coming up in the Church were put to give ſome <hi>explicit evidence</hi> of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and choice of the profeſſion of Chriſt, ſo far as may witneſſe a ratification of the <hi>baptiſmal covenant,</hi> now as their own proper dead, wherein they were implicitly ingad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in their infancy. Some ſpecial grounds and reaſons for this are; I. Becauſe God will have his ſervice freely entered in and upon <hi>choiſe,</hi> as that way which is moſt agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his honour; for as the <hi>covenant</hi> binds mutually, ſo doe the <hi>ſeals</hi> therof alſo, and therfor, upon our part is <hi>baptiſme a ſacre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental oath of aledgence to God.</hi> II. Becauſe it tends to a more reſolute and firme adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the ſervice of God, that this buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe should be perſonally brought home to mens conſcience, eſpecially before their firſt admittance to the Sacrament of the Lords ſupper, and thus to ingadg them as <hi>Joshua</hi> did <hi>Chap.</hi> 24: 22. <hi>Ye are witneſſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt yourſelves herein, and they ſaid we are witneſſes.</hi> III. Becauſe this is expreſly held forth 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3:21. where <hi>baptiſme is called the anſwer of a good conſcience toward God,</hi> upon this ground, that ſuch then who were come to years of knowledge, were perſonally ſiſted to confirme by their own conſent that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:205486:12"/>ſolemne ingadgment and dedication by Baptiſme to be the Lords, and therefor it is called <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, which is <hi>vox juris,</hi> and ſignifies, <hi>ſponſio, &amp; ſtipulatio publica inter Chriſtianum, &amp; Dominum Chriſtum,</hi> as the moſt judicious Commentators on that ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture does clearly render; and ſo this was a ſpecial part of the primitive practize, not only with reſpect to ſuch, who were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from <hi>Heatheniſme,</hi> but were born within the Church and partakers of that <hi>ſeal of Baptiſme in their infancy,</hi> to ſiſte them upon anſwer to that great demand of the Covenant, doe yow now conſent upon <hi>evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and choiſe</hi> to be the Lords and to be a ſubject of his Kingdom, and embrace the laws therof, and doe yow thus in ſincerity and truth declare the ſame wherein you have a good conſcience before God. And of what bleſſed fruit and advantage should this be both for the increaſe and honour of the Goſpel, if this were more deeply taken to heart for ſome practical uſe, according to the <hi>rule,</hi> and <hi>primitive pattern</hi> in the Churches of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="4">IV. It were ſpecially deſirable alſo, that there be ſome <hi>clear view and ſummary</hi> by it ſelf, of the moſt <hi>cogent grounds and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of the Chriſtian faith,</hi> with reſpect both to the <hi>Doctrinal, Hiſtorical, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical</hi>
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:205486:12"/>part therof, and in that manner ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate, as the meaneſt within the Church might have ſuch a help ſtill at their hand, and thus with the leaſt expenſe of time, be provided of ſuch arguments and reaſons, as should tend (through the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God) not only to the furtheſt ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal aſſent, and certainty of the truth of their profeſſion, but to give a moſt ſpecial ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of mind againſt that inward tryal of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans temptations and fiery darts this way; yea is ſuch a mean, that in the ſerious im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provment herof by having ſuch evidences once brought in on mens judgment and conſcience, ſo as to ſee with their own eyes the truth of the ſame, I muſt humbly judge, there is nothing, next to the internal work of the Spirit, of this kind might tend more to promote the Kingdom of Chriſt in this day.</p>
                     <p>I shal but add this further on the preſent ſubject, <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>VII</label> that as there are ſome more <hi>ſignal periods of time,</hi> to which a greater brightneſſe and increaſe of light hath reſpect under the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> ſo doth there now ſeem to be ſome remarkable call and excitment, to ſuch a <hi>confirming work,</hi> in this day about the Chriſtian faith; when we may hope that a more <hi>ſolemne and reſtoring time of religion</hi> in the world, is on a near approach, (though
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:205486:13"/>all ſenſible evidence would ſeem to control this) and may be now more looked after, then prepared for, under any ſuitable im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of theſe <hi>grounds</hi> for the ſame. I. That the promiſed time of the <hi>converſion of the Jewes</hi> doth aſſuredly draw near; and whatever be judged by ſome of the Lords immediate appearence herein by a <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle,</hi> yet is it unqueſtionable that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the way of means could be more promiſing and hopeful to promot this great end, then in promoting ſo great a ſervice as this for the Chriſtian Church. II. That a greater extent alſo of the profeſſion of Chriſt amonghſt the Gentils, and renting of the vaile that is now over many dark nations, ſeemeth clearly inſured therwith; and what a hopeful evidence should this be if ſuch a <hi>publick and catholick ſpirit</hi> were more ſeen, how to advance the higheſt ends of religion on ſuch an accompt without reſpect to any partial or divided intereſt; yea that this bleſt zeal of God might in that manner appear to have the dark world get a more clear and convincing proſpect of the <hi>higheſt rational demonſtrations of Chriſtianity,</hi> as might through the Lords gracious concurrence bring men once to an <hi>inquiſitive and ſerious ſpirit</hi> about the ſame. Oh that ſuch may be thus raiſed up in this diſmal hower with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:205486:13"/>ſomething of that ancient ſpirit, to travel with deſire for the <hi>ſalvation of mankind,</hi> and of whom it may be ſaid, as of bleſt <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah, theſe are indeed come to ſeek the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of their people,</hi> in their greateſt intereſt. III. And this farther excitment we are now under for this end, in a time when Popery ſeems to be upon one of its laſt and greateſt aſſaults againſt the Church; ſince its ſo clear what ever tends to confirm men in Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity from their own tryal and inquiry upon the confirming evidences therof, muſt have the ſame native reſult, to make ſuch confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Proteſtants; yea nothing is more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrable then that the method and grounds that are taken both to ingadge and fix men in the Popish profeſſion, have the ſame rational tendency to promot Atheiſm, and to give infidels the greateſt advantage to reject the profeſſion of Chriſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:205486:14"/>
                     <head>CHAPTER II. <hi>The confirming worke of Religion, reduced to practical uſe; in ſome clear view of theſe primary grounds, and demonſtrations of our faith; which none should pretend ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of, who enters the profeſſion of Chriſt upon choiſe, and certainty of evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div n="1" type="section">
                        <head>SECTION I.</head>
                        <p>QU. I. WHat <hi>reaſons,</hi> and <hi>demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> can yow give for ſo great a faith of the <hi>glorious being of God,</hi> when he is inviſible to humane ſenſe, ſince this is the fundation of all religion?</p>
                        <p>ANSW. Though on the ſacred truth and authority of his own word, this is principally founded, yet I am with the furtheſt infallible <hi>evidence</hi> herein confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; I. That it can be no more ſure, this marvellous frame of the heavens and earth hath a being, and is the object of our ſenſe, then that a ſupreme infinite wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and power muſt be the firſt cauſe hereof, and it were ſimply impoſſible it could ever otherwiſe have been. II. That he hath thus made himſelf <hi>viſible</hi> to our eyes by ſuch a <hi>viſible world,</hi> and in ſo exquiſite
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:205486:14"/>an order and correſpondence there to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the ſame, as nothing ſtands alone by it ſelf, but in a line of mutual reſpect, which runs through the whole creation, whom we may as clearly thus ſee, as that there is an inviſible ſoul in a living body. III. That this harmony is amongſt thinghs, in their own nature ſo contrare and deſtructive to other, for to hold this wonderful frame, as all muſt abandon reaſon, or ſee an infinitly wiſe conduct herein; and no need of extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary <hi>miracles,</hi> to confirme what the whole conſtitutions of nature do witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. IV. That this rare frame of man could never have come in being, but by him who could unite ſuch different ſubſtances as a <hi>material body,</hi> and an <hi>immaterial ſoul,</hi> in ſo near and marvelous an union. V. That ſuch an univerſal conſent of mankind is in all ages therto, as shews religion to be founded in the very nature of man, and as eſſential to his being, as his reaſon is, yea how the ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate difference of man from the beaſt, and moſt eſſential property of human nature lyes here. VI. That though every one be an enemy to what torments him; yet was it never poſſible for an Atheiſt to free himſelf from that unavoidable ſenſe and fear of a <hi>Deity;</hi> nor, in a world ſo much loſt in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, could ever extinguish the awe of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:205486:15"/>religion, or make any rational oppoſition to this greateſt article of the common faith of mankind. VII. That the reaſon of the whole conſtitution of nature, and viciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of things here, is ſo great, as, without shutting out the uſe of reaſon, we cannot but ſee, how nothing poſſibly could have been better; and that any want hereof in the whole frame of the univerſe, would be as the diſlocation of a joynt of the body, and were not conceivable to be otherwiſe then it is by infinite wiſdome appointed. VIII. That its ſimply impoſſible that God bleſſed for ever should not exiſt, or that this uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, (which is a worke ſo highly becoming the greatneſſe of its maker) could poſſibly ſubſiſt for one hour or minute of time, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſupreme independent power and being, on which all viſible beings have their dependance, ſince they cannot depend upon nothing. IX. That ſuch is the abſolute neceſſity of the <hi>faith alſo of a God-head,</hi> as without this the ſtate of mankind could not <hi>morally</hi> ſubſiſt, or any poſſible order, ſubjection, piety, and juſtice, be to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port human ſociety, but as <hi>Bradwardine</hi> ſaith, <hi>O quam neceſſe eſt hunc eſſe, quem im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibile eſt non eſſe!</hi> O that men cannot but ſee theſe effects of his power on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, in the certainty of a profetick light
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:205486:15"/>and diſcovery, as hath been oft given of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture things, and in the undenyable truth of miracles, ſo as ſuch a <hi>prodigy</hi> as a profeſt <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> can have no claime to human race, as a rational being, more then the greateſt <hi>monſter</hi> in nature to be a true man.</p>
                        <p>QU. II. What doth witneſſe the <hi>worlds</hi> not being <hi>eternal,</hi> and its firſt origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and beginning from God, to confirme your faith herein, by the further rational de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration.</p>
                        <p>ANS. I. That as an eternity is only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable to the firſt cauſe, ſo that which is made up of corruptible &amp; perishing things, as this viſible world, cannot poſſibly be in it ſelf <hi>eternal;</hi> nor could ever produce it ſelf, ſince thus it muſt both exiſt and not exiſt at the ſame time, which is the greateſt contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. II. That if there be ſuch a thing now <hi>as time,</hi> there can be no judging of dayes, yeares and ages to be infinite, or how one thing in a continued order, should thus goe before another, without coming to ſome firſt beginning. III. If there be a gradual advance of human learning on the earth, and a further diſcovery of arts and ſciences; and that the greateſt experiments and inventions there have been but of a late riſe and date; then can there not poſſibly be an eternal ſucceſſion of mankind, with a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:205486:16"/>continued progreſſe and experiency this way; nor that but of late one part of the world is known and diſcovered to another. IV. That ſo short an hiſtory as we have in the moſt ancient records of time, were wholly inconſiſtent with ſuch an eternal du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, or that infinite ages preceeding, should leave no rememberance to poſterity, when ſo ſmall a meaſure of time, as a few <hi>thouſand years,</hi> have left ſo much. V. Nor could men beget other eternally without going back to ſome firſt man, who could not beget himſelf. VI. That if eternity be preferable to time, then should not the excellenteſt being in the earth, <hi>man,</hi> be thus corruptible, and only this inanimate maſſe of the earth eternal. VII. That infinite ages paſt, though they should have but mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed the race of man in an age, to two or three more, should have come at laſt, that the whole precinct of the earth could not poſſibly bear the product of ſuch an infinite increaſe; and no wears or extraordinary judgments were ever yet known to be ſuch, as to reſtrain ſuch an unavoidable grouth.</p>
                        <p>QU. III. What infaillible evidence to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is there of a <hi>ſupream Providence,</hi> both in the <hi>conſervation, and government of the world;</hi> for confirming your faith of the Scripture herein?</p>
                        <pb n="27" facs="tcp:205486:16"/>
                        <p>ANS. I. That it is ſo clear the ſupport of this great frame of the Univerſe, with that continued &amp; regular coure of nature herein, are as ſimply impoſſible without an infinite divine power, as its firſt being and creation. II. That ſuch an extent of providence as reſpects ſo innumberable objects, with ſuch a contrariety both of qualities and paſſions in the ſame, muſt needs be from an infinite and intelligent cauſe. III. That all things to this day, continue in that eſtablished or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ſecond cauſes, wherein God hath pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them by a law ſo viſibly imprinted on the nature of things without reaſon, that they doe as exactly anſwer the ſame in their proper courſe and ſtation, as if they had a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional knowledge of their duty. IV. That univerſal reſpect, the <hi>ſun in the firmament</hi> hath to things here below, though at ſo great a diſtance, yet doth neither ceaſe, nor weary to emit its beams and hid influences to the meaneſt creatures, may let us clearly ſee, how it hath the ſame viſible uſe and end to confirme an incomprehenſible and infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te providence about the meaneſt things, as wel as the greateſt. V. That immediate precedency of the ſoul in that leſſer world of man, bears the ſame evidence therwith; which though we never ſaw with our eyes, yet doth undenyably actuate the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:205486:17"/>in its functions, as the proper ſpring of every act and motion there. VI. It is thus further confirmed, by theſe continued vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſitudes of <hi>Summer and Winter,</hi> and <hi>of day and night,</hi> that man might have, both light for his labour, and darkneſſe as a covering for his reſt. VII. By ſuch viſible diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>divine judgment and execution</hi> of his laws on men here, as all may ſee his hand therin, who yet will not hear his voice in the word. VIII. By theſe extraordinare and wonderfull works of providence, which have been in all ages. IX. By ſo evident a reſtrainct both over <hi>Devils, and wicked men,</hi> without which they would quickly diſturbe the whole frame of this earth, and make it uninhabitable for human ſociety; if their being thus bounded and chained, were not as viſible, as the certainty of their being. X. By ſuch a <hi>natural obligation</hi> to moral du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, with the ſenſe of a difference betwixt good and evil, as is founded in the very ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional nature of man, that none can poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly root out, even where the Scripture is not known. XI. By that natural confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence alſo in God, and in a recourſe to him on any preſent extreme hazard, to witneſſe, not only the moſt high beares rule in the kingdomes of men, but that the ſenſe and evidence hereof is unavoidable.</p>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:205486:17"/>
                        <p>QU. IV. But doth this great <hi>admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of providence,</hi> about human affaires as uncheangably appear, in a <hi>differencing</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the righteous and the wicked, by ſome recompence to the one, and punishment to the other, as in the eſtablished courſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
                        <p>ANS. It is ſure ſuch as deſire a confirming of their faith herein, wants it not, with the furtheſt evidence, but may ever ſee that exact conformity in the whole diſpenſation of providence, to the rectitude and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the divine nature, and how a firm beliefe <hi>that God is,</hi> and <hi>that he is a revarder of them that diligently ſeek him,</hi> is one and the ſame faith; when we cannot but ſee, I. That natural ſenſe of good and evil, and eſſentiall difference betwixt the ſame, which is ſo fimly founded in the reaſon of all mankind, as no human laws or cuſtome could ever ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke this off their conſcience, or make an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference her in, without extinguishing the very nature of man; to shew that eternal and uncheangable difference, which the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nature of God hath put betwixt them. II. That we ſee ſuch conſtraint ſerved on the worſt of men, to an awful ſenſe and regard of <hi>truth and weal doing,</hi> and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the loveleneſſe and excellency hereof, as does make them ſeek their own
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:205486:18"/>repute by a falſe shew and counterfite of the ſame; and gives ſuch a being and riſe to that dreadful impoſture of <hi>hypocriſy.</hi> III. That its the <hi>truths</hi> priviledge ever to outlive <hi>fals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> and prevail over the ſame, yea to have the greater triumph after its ſoreſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts; and how this is of as foundamental a conſtitution in the courſe of providence, as the moſt firm eſtablishment of nature. IV. That in no time ſince man was formed in the earth, doth true <hi>joy and ſerenity of mind,</hi> ceaſe to be the native reſult of <hi>weal-doing,</hi> or the <hi>fruit of righteouſneſſe, to be peace and aſſurence of mind,</hi> nor hath ever wanted a witneſſe even before the world of the Lords taking pleaſure herein. V. That its ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, in the moſt diſmal times, what a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick <hi>bleſſing,</hi> ſuch are, who by more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinare tryals have been put to the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gheſt exerciſe of their grace and patience; yea how viſibly ſuch have been promot to the moſt honourable ſervice for God, and to advance the credite of religion before men, who on the firſt ſight and view have been accounted the moſt miſerable of any. VI. Whilſt, <hi>on the other hand,</hi> it may be ever ſeen, how with the greateſt <hi>proſperity</hi> of the wicked here, there are <hi>punishments of another kind</hi> diſpenſed, and more dreadful then any outward affliction, ſuch as <hi>judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:205486:18"/>obſtinacy, and blindneſſe of mind in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to God,</hi> even when their own ruine is made viſible to them herein. VII. How oft men are thus evidently condemned to be happy in this world by ſome ſtrang meaſure of <hi>temporall ſucceſſe and proſperity,</hi> before ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me great fall and ruine, as the iſſue hereof in the laſt shene of providence doth fully at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. VIII. That its ſeen alſo, how ſin doth ever bring its own <hi>punishment</hi> therewith, in ſome begun degree both of shame and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and, as <hi>Seneca,</hi> an heathen could ſay, <hi>that wickedneſſe was the moſt exquiſite contriver of human miſery,</hi> ſo the world like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe may ſee how a preſent immunity from judgment is no releaſe, but when its ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce is not <hi>ſpeadily execute,</hi> yet is it at laſt ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly execute. IX. And how evident is it, that the greateſt haters of godlineſſe are yet inforced to juſtify the ſame and the Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians choiſe herein, as the greateſt wiſdome, upon any ſurpriſing ſtate and extremity; yea how ſuch would be glad to joyne intereſts then with ſuch in their death, whom they moſt contemned in their life.</p>
                        <p>QU. V. How is it convincing and demonſtrable, that God hath given any clear and expres revelation of his will and councel unto men, and that ſuch a <hi>wonderfull record</hi> is undoubtedly extant in the world.</p>
                        <pb n="32" facs="tcp:205486:19"/>
                        <p>ANSW. That, I. it is not poſſible to believe the <hi>being of God,</hi> and not alſo the truth of an eſtablished <hi>law,</hi> and rule of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce betwixt him and man here, ſo as to know both what we should doe, and what to expect and hope from him. II. That this alſo muſt be known and diſplay its po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and efficacy to the world, in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and by ſuch infallible evidence of its truth, as may render all inexcuſable, who give not intire credite therto. III. I can be no more clear and aſſured there is but one <hi>ſun in the firmament;</hi> then that there is but one <hi>fountain,</hi> and <hi>repoſitory of ſacred light</hi> about religion, which is the <hi>Scripture,</hi> and its being the alone publick ſtandard of truth to the whole world. IV. That no way was ever made known to recover mankind from a ſtate of bondage, darkneſſe, and miſery, compatible with the very uſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but by this bleſſed light which shineth there. V. Yea that there is as viſible a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, betwixt the ſame and any preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded religion which ever was beſides in the world, as there is <hi>betwixt day and night,</hi> which is founded in the immutable nature of theſe things in themſelves. VI. That the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re is one proper <hi>sphere,</hi> where this glorious light of divine truth is fixed, and wherein it shines forth from one age to another; which is the Chriſtian Church.</p>
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:205486:19"/>
                        <p>QU. VI. But what more peculiare eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces can yow shew of the <hi>divinity of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> that all may ſee to be of infallible truth.</p>
                        <p>ANSW. I. That its ſure ſuch a <hi>book</hi> is this day in the earth, which no created wisdome could ever have done, and contains ſuch things of higheſt conceirn to mankind, as doe infinitly exceed the bounds of human ability and invention, or could ever have been diſcovered but by God himſelf. II. That it gives forth ſuch exquiſite <hi>laws</hi> and conſtitutions of our religion, as men muſt needs ſee the <hi>holy nature, purity, and perfection of God,</hi> moſt brightly shining forth therin. III. Which doth diſcover ſo great and proper a relief for all theſe evils and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries that doe attend this fallen eſtate of man, as none but an allſufficient God could only doe. IV. That he alone muſt be the author of this bleſſed record, who rules the world, and hath determined the changes and revolutions therof, when it is not more evident how theſe viſible heavens are ſtretched forth over the earth, then that this <hi>line of the Scripture is</hi> ſtretched over the whole worke and <hi>frame of providence,</hi> and doth moſt clearly illuminate the ſame. V. That ſurely this was the product of infinite wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, whence ſo great a variety of matter, doth meet with ſo viſible a concent and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:205486:20"/>in one perfect and intire frame; yea knit in ſo cloſſe a bond of union together, as makes the whole Bible to be intirly <hi>one piece;</hi> though in the writing of each diſtinct part therof it could never have poſſibly been contrived or forſeen by humane wiſdome, what we ſee here of ſo admirable an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; correſpondence, as is in all the parts therof. VI. That none els could have ſpoke to the world, in ſo majeſtick a way, &amp; becoming the greatneſſe and ſoveraignity of God, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume ſuch a ſupremacy, &amp; give forth laws for abſolute obedience from all mankind therto, &amp; on ſuch a penalty of eternal deſtruction; or that any impoſtures, either poſſibly could, or durſt have, in ſuch a manner, perſonate the ſame. VII. That it muſt needs be his word who perfectly knows what is in man, and hath an abſolute authority over the ſoul, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts therof, who thus not only gives law to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and our inward parts, but doth eſtablish an internal religion there, no leſſe abſolutly, then what reſpects our external worke and actions. VIII. Yea where all may ſee the whole penmen therof under ſo intire a ſubjection to the doctrine which they tought, and to be no contrivance of their own, as they did record their own failings, and imperfections in behalf of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:205486:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>truth; and did thus alſo require all juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and obedience to the Magiſtrates, when through the whole earth they were then greateſt enemies to the truth of the Goſpel. IX. That this muſt be his word, who alone can derive principles of life to his own inſtitutions, and animate the ſame with a quickning Spirit; and is a worke above the contrivance of Angels or men, when directed to each new tryal of the Church, and perſonal caſe of Chriſtians, as though it had been alone writt for that time; ſo that I can be no more perſwaded in reaſon there is ſuch a book as the <hi>Bible</hi> in the earth, then that it came from heaven, and is the alone rule of religion, and of divine revelation, for the governing of mankind.</p>
                        <p>QU. VII. How is the ſecure <hi>conveyance of the Scripture</hi> demonſtrable amidſt all the changes of times paſt, and that no poſſible acceſſe could be for its corruption.</p>
                        <p>ANSW. I. That its ſo undenyably the firſt rule which ever was given to mankind of religion, and the alone <hi>publick ſtandard of truth,</hi> that hath endured the tryal and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry of all times paſt, ſo as no pretences in the matter of antiquity could yet ever be to the contrare. II. That ſo exact an <hi>harmony</hi> is betwixt <hi>the Old and New Teſtament,</hi> as the one is a viſible tranſcript of the other, in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:205486:21"/>its accomplishment; that I can be no more ſure of ſuch a venerable record as the Old Teſtament, and its unalterable conveyance to the Church, to which the whole race of the Jewes is yet a ſtanding witneſſe, then how it is continued and perfected in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of the Goſpel, and but one intire frame. III. That its deliverance was no private deed, but by a publick truſt to the whole univerſal Church; ſo as it were more eaſy in the way of reaſon to queſtion the moſt fundamental ſtatutes and lawes of any nation, by which mens private right and property is ſecured, then the truth hereof. IV. That under the Goſpel it hath been ſo fully diſperſed over the world, and in ſuch various languages; as an innumerable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Chriſtians theſe 1600 years paſt, hath been as a common library of the ſame. V. That theſe numerous verſions and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries tranſmit theron in diverſe langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, doe fully evidence they had the ſame Scripture, and no other then what we have this day. VI. That this was delivered to the Church not only in write, but in that forme of ſound words, for keeping cloſſe therby, as could admit no poſſible acceſſe to corrupt or alter the ſame; beſides the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued and publick reference hath been ſince the firſt ages of the Goſpel to its deciſion,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:205486:21"/>which all theſe sharpe controverſies, that have been in the Church on all ſides, doe inevitably require.</p>
                        <p>QU. VIII. What doth confirme the fall of man, and entry thus of ſin into the world, this way, from clear and unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble evidences of reaſon.</p>
                        <p>ANSW. I. That there is ſuch a thing as ſin and evil in the world, with the ſenſe and conſcience of guilt ariſing hereon, amonghſt all mankind, can need no proof or evidence. II. That it is ſimply impoſſible this should have been originally created with man, or eſſentially belonging to his firſt frame and conſtitution, ſince then there could be no conſcience of guilt or remorſe, for what was given to be a part of himſelf, in his firſt frame; or be any ſin, to act thus ſuitably to their own original ſtate. III. That it were not conceivable alſo how one part of <hi>man</hi> should be in ſuch oppoſition to another. IV. Nor that ſuch a thing as <hi>inherent shame</hi> could be in the nature of man, upon the ſence of <hi>guilt,</hi> and by ſo natural a reſult fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ſame, or that ſuch should be asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of any part of his <hi>own being,</hi> if this were not upon ane undoubted <hi>apoſtacy</hi> from what once he was, and that inevitable conviction of conſcience that he now is what he ought not to be, ſo as the certainty of <hi>mans fall</hi>
                           <pb n="38" facs="tcp:205486:22"/>though alone revealed in the Scripture, as to the true cauſe thereof, yet may be as evident to <hi>reaſon,</hi> as the truth of his being now is.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="section">
                        <head>SECTION II.</head>
                        <p>QU. I. ARe there ſuch <hi>aſſiſtances</hi> to the Chriſtian faith upon that great and aſtonishing myſtery of the revelation of Chriſt to the world as can fully anſwer the greatneſſe thereof from cleare and infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble evidence to mens judgement?</p>
                        <p>ANSW. It is ſure there could nothing poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be deſired more to ſatisfy the moſt doubtfull and ſuſpicious minde then is given for the furtheſt certainty hereof. I. That ſuch <hi>a glorious perſon</hi> as the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> was to come, and be <hi>anoynted</hi> to that great work of <hi>redeeming mankinde</hi> from ſin and miſery and bring man back again unto God; and how this <hi>promiſe</hi> is the alone foundation, whereon the <hi>church</hi> was founded ſince man fell. II. That all theſe numerous <hi>types and ſacrifices</hi> under the <hi>law,</hi> did ſo expreſly tend to confirm their faith of that one bleſſed <hi>propitiatory ſacrifice</hi> which was to be offered up. III. That longer the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> was writ, there was ſo cleare and exact a portraicture of the <hi>Meſſias</hi> drawen forth in the <hi>old,</hi> with ſuch peculiar marks whereby
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:205486:22"/>he should be knowen to the <hi>church,</hi> and have infallibly taken place in the event as men could not upon any <hi>Scripture evidence</hi> exſpect his comming in another way. IV. That his <hi>humiliation and ſufferings</hi> were ſo expreſly shewed forth and foretold, with the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar circumſtances thereof in the 53. <hi>chap. of Iſaiah, and</hi> 9. <hi>of Daniel,</hi> as if they had been eye wittneſſes of the accomplishment the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof. V. That even the ſpeciall <hi>ſeaſon</hi> and period of time for outmaking of this <hi>great promiſe</hi> was ſo far made knowen, as upon diligent ſearch and inquiry, its neare ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach might be diſcernable and cleare to <hi>what or what manner of time</hi> this did ſpecially relate; for which both the <hi>fall of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies</hi> and <hi>Daniels ſeventy weekes</hi> were ſet up as highway markes to guide mens faith herein. VI. That its ſimply impoſſible according to the Scripture, how the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Meſſias</hi> could be yet to come, except the <hi>Jewes</hi> were put in the ſame ſtate they were in at his coming, when now for theſe 1600. Jeares there hath been no <hi>Scepter,</hi> nor <hi>lawgiver,</hi> no <hi>temple,</hi> or <hi>daily Sacrifice.</hi> VII. That this great myſtery could never poſſibly have entered in our thoughts, or be deviſed by any created underſtanding.</p>
                        <p>QU. II. But are there as cleare and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible evidences of the truth of this great
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:205486:23"/>promiſe in the event, that ſurely the bleſſed <hi>Meſſias</hi> of the world is now come, as that it is ſure be was promiſed.</p>
                        <p>ANSW. Its beyond all poſſible debate. I. That ſo <hi>divine and wonderfull a perſon</hi> was in the dayes of <hi>Tiberius Caeſar</hi> manifeſted then to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> with no outward shew or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; who did ſo great and marvellous things, before all the people, as were above all created power, yea, was <hi>crucifyed at Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> under <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> and is a truth in the matter of fact, that both Jewes and heathens have been enforced to confeſſe. II. That this ſpecial ſeaſon of his comming into the world as the <hi>great Epocha</hi> and period of time from which the <hi>Chriſtian church,</hi> hath ſince to this day reckoned her ſtate and ſucceſſion, is undoubted and clear alſo. III. That the time of his appearance unto the world, did ſo exactly tryſt with that which was foretold by the <hi>Prophets,</hi> as then the <hi>Jewish church</hi> was with greateſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertance looking after the <hi>Meſſias;</hi> ſo as ſome remarkable <hi>impoſtors</hi> were thus excited to deceive the people herein. IV. That in him who was then revealed, and whom the Chriſtian church <hi>worships</hi> its ſure, was moſt exactly fulfilled, what ever was foretold, concerning the Meſſias in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and we do appeal herein to theſe <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords</hi>
                           <pb n="41" facs="tcp:205486:23"/>which all the <hi>Jewes</hi> even to this day do acknowledge to be divine. V. That this was not done in a corner, but in the publick view of men in theſe dayes, moſt noture and famous; yea by the ſpecial deſtination of God at ſo ſolemn a time of the <hi>paſſover in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> where <hi>Chriſt our paſsover was then ſacrificed.</hi> VI. That no humane intereſt or policy can poſſibly be in this diſcovery of the <hi>goſpell;</hi> when nothing more viſibly croſſe therto or obſtructive of its ſucceſſe, then ſuch a publishing of the <hi>death and ſufferings of our Lord,</hi> with all the ignominy and aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſement which attended the ſame, had there been any acceſſe here to conſult carnal rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or any other ground to beare it out then the evidence and certainty of its truth. VII. That herein have all divided partyes <hi>and ſects</hi> in the Chriſtian world been enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſtil to meet and conſent, in ane acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of the ſubſtance thereof. VIII. That in the ſame light which was held forth in the Old Teſtament about the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> did the whole <hi>gentile church</hi> enter; and made claime to their right for being adopted the ſeed and children of Abraham, on theſe cleare and expreſſe promiſes given for the ſame; which the Jewes could not but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe to be of divine authority.</p>
                        <p>QU. III. What confirmation is to the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:205486:24"/>Chriſtian faith, that for 4000. yeares the comming of the Meſſias should be deferred after the promiſe.</p>
                        <p>ANS. Though the ſoveraign pleaſure of <hi>God</hi> should ſilence and ſatisfy our minde herein; yet is there ſuch a ſight to be had hereof, and of inſinit divine wiſedome shining forth in the ſame as should be moſt <hi>confirming</hi> for theſe <hi>ends.</hi> I. That there might be a more diſtinct repreſenting of the <hi>glory of this myſtery</hi> to angels and men, in ſuch <hi>a graduall</hi> opening up of the ſame. II. To put that weight and high value on his own <hi>promiſe and teſtimony</hi> herein, when on the alone credit thereof, he would thus both try, and beare out the <hi>faith of his church,</hi> for ſo many <hi>ages,</hi> and draw forth their deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res and longings in all that long ſpace of time after the ſame. III. To teſtify the greatneſſe of his wrath againſt <hi>ſin</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtacy of mankinde,</hi> by ſuffering the generality there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to ly ſo long under its <hi>fatall</hi> effects. IV. To prepare the <hi>church</hi> for ſo <hi>great a reception,</hi> by all that long <hi>preparatory ſervice of legall inſtitutions,</hi> as ſo highly becoming the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this <hi>myſtery,</hi> to have ſo ſolemn and ſtupendious ane introduction thereto. V. That thus the world might have its full tryall of the inſufficiency of natural abilityes, and of any improvements of humane wiſedome
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:205486:24"/>and learning, for help; after this had firſt been at the furtheſt hight both in <hi>Greece and Rome,</hi> before the alone <hi>Redeemer</hi> of the church came.</p>
                        <p>QU. IV. What can offer furtheſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction to the world of the truth of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity from its nature and internall excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; and that it is no leſſe eſſentially good in its ſelfe, then evidently true.</p>
                        <p>ANS. I. That its ſo undeniable even to theſe that live at a diſtance, how ſuch is the <hi>truth of Chriſt</hi> that though all viſible and humane props should faill, it can ſubſiſt by its <hi>oun evidence, and authority</hi> over mens conſcience, and hath thus ever preſerved its ſtation in the worſt of times. II. That as it holds forth the moſt exquiſite <hi>rule of perfection</hi> to follow, ſo doth bring the greateſt releef to the diſtempers of the minde, and theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries which attend humane ſtate here; ſo as a higher glory doth thus reſult to the <hi>holy God,</hi> by this <hi>diſpenſation of Grace</hi> to fallen man then if he had ſtood in his <hi>primitive ſtate.</hi> III. That it is ſure the truth and doctrine of Chriſt doth natively tend to fix men in a <hi>ſtate of light and communton with God,</hi> and in a <hi>ſtate of ſeparation</hi> of ſuch in their <hi>principles, affection,</hi> and <hi>converſation</hi> from the world. IV. That it doth more brightly shine forth in <hi>ſimplicity, and truth and in its internall
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:205486:25"/>and vitallacts,</hi> then in any outward form or shew, yea in the way of <hi>ſelfe deniall, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and <hi>poverty of ſpirit,</hi> doth ſuch ane excellency appeare, as in <hi>its oun nature,</hi> hath as viſible a difference from the proud and vindictive ſpirit of this world, as the <hi>day</hi> hath from the <hi>night.</hi> V. How ſuch is <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> as by no naked <hi>doctrinall</hi> diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the ſame, to mens judgement, or ſuch rules as any humane ſcience is acquired by, can be knowen, without ane inward power and principles of a <hi>new life;</hi> nor can there ever be a right knowledge of <hi>divinity,</hi> untill it be firſt ingrafted in a <hi>divine heart;</hi> ſo far is this <hi>myſtery</hi> above all humane rule, and contrivance. VI. That it is ſtated in the greateſt oppoſition to any falſe shew or <hi>hypocriſy;</hi> yea, brings ſuch inforcements therewith of candor, and truth, and of <hi>love, tenderneſſe and ſympathy</hi> towards others, as all muſt ſee is not only the higheſt ornament and perfection of our nature, but the greateſt <hi>bleſſing to the world</hi> that ever was knowen. VII. That ſuch a native <hi>luſtre and fragrancy</hi> doth attend the truth, and ſimplicity of the goſpell, as its no more poſſible for humane <hi>art</hi> or cunning to repreſent this, then to make the dead image of a <hi>man</hi> to live, or to paint in a broad the <hi>vitall ſcent</hi> of a violet or roſe, to our <hi>ſenſes.</hi> VIII. That in this way
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:205486:25"/>of the <hi>goſpels</hi> ſubduing men to the obedience thereof, by the power of <hi>inward grace,</hi> the <hi>glory of Chriſt</hi> doth more eminently shine forth, then if he had appeared for this end with the greateſt outward majeſty and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Angels to our bodily eyes. IX. That it is ſo viſible how the whole world beſides, that is without the revelation of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is a place where horrour, falſehood, and impiety doth manifeſtly reign.</p>
                        <p>QU. V. But how do yow receive ſo wonderfull a truth, as that of the Goſpell is, when its now ſo great a diſtance of time from its firſt promulgation.</p>
                        <p>ANS. I. That we can be no more ſure and perſwaded of the moſt viſible and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent objects of ſenſe, then, that this is the ſame <hi>goſpell</hi> which is ſtill shining forth to the world, whereby ane innumerable company of all <hi>nations, tongues</hi> and <hi>languages,</hi> hath received the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and been <hi>ſealed;</hi> yea, hath made that change upon men, in turning them from <hi>ungodlyneſſe and idols to ſerve the living God,</hi> as hath been no leſſe marvellous then the turning of ſo many <hi>wolves,</hi> into <hi>lambs.</hi> II. That it is the ſame <hi>goſpell</hi> which not only through a ſeries of 16. <hi>centuries</hi> hath been atteſted, but by ſuch innumerable <hi>witneſſes</hi> who counted not their life deare unto the death for ſealing thereof, and found
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:205486:26"/>it ſweet to be offered up in the flames for <hi>Chriſt.</hi> III. Which in all ages paſt hath ſtood out the greateſt oppoſition that ever the world made to any intereſt, while the <hi>weapons of its warfare were ſpiritual, and not carnal;</hi> &amp; with that ſucceſſe as the time of the <hi>Churches hotteſt perſecution</hi> from heathens was that period of time alſo of a moſt remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpreading in the world. IV. That the ſame <hi>Goſpel</hi> is revealed this day, which hath had ſuch diſcernable <hi>triumphs</hi> and ſucceſſe when no external aſſiſtance could be ſeen herein; and no viſible power by which it gained the moſt ſavage and dark parts of the earth, to take on the <hi>yoak of Chriſt,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the objects of faith to the moſt deſireable <hi>objects of ſenſe.</hi> V. Yea, which hath not only had ſuch <hi>vital influence</hi> on mens heart, and practice to change it into the ſame <hi>image;</hi> but that herein the doctrine of the <hi>croſſe of Chriſt</hi> in the greateſt <hi>ſimplicity</hi> hath ſtill been the moſt effectual way of its conqueſt, and the greateſt attractive on mens ſouls to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſame.</p>
                        <p>QU. VI. How is it demonſtrable that ſuch remarkable ſufferings of times paſt for the truth of Chriſt, were both founded on the alone certainty thereof, and carryed out by a divine Spirit above any aſſiſtance of nature.</p>
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:205486:26"/>
                        <p>ANSW. That it is ſure, I. Here was no <hi>comedy,</hi> or perſonated ſufferings which the <hi>primitive Chriſtians,</hi> and in after times did endure for <hi>Chriſt;</hi> or that theſe unexpreſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble torments and paines were any <hi>dream,</hi> and <hi>deluſion</hi> either to themſelves or the world, and that their adverſaries did thus conflict and wreſtle with their own <hi>shadow</hi> in ſo continued and cruel ane oppoſition. II. That ſuch <hi>joy and exultation of Spirit</hi> theſe witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed amidſt their <hi>torments,</hi> who otherwiſe wanted no ſenſe or feeling of their paines and ſufferings, could have no riſe but what was ſupernatural. III. That this could be no poſſible diſſimulation or <hi>counterfit</hi> when they were ſtepping in on <hi>eternity,</hi> nor the product of a diſtempered judgment; whilſt all might ſee what ſeriouſneſſe of Spirit, <hi>tenderneſſe, and bowels of compaſſion</hi> to their adverſaries they did then evidence. IV. That theſe greateſt ſufferings were upon choiſe, and to endure rather then to be ſafe at the rate of receding in any thing from the truth. V. Yea no natural reaſon can comprehend how ſuch mean and feeble perſons as many of theſe were, should endure, what would have made the greateſt <hi>natural courage</hi> to faint, as if they had foregone humane paſſions which flesh and blood muſt needs have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſo as I am conſtraind to ſee ſomething
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:205486:27"/>no leſs marvellous and ſupernatural in the <hi>faith of martyres,</hi> then in the <hi>faith of miracles.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="section">
                        <head>SECTION III.</head>
                        <p>QU. I. IS it fully demonſtrable, that the <hi>faith of a deity,</hi> and of ſuch an eſtablishment as a religious worship, muſt neceſſarly determine men to be <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> on this ground that they cannot but ſee how <hi>religion</hi> hath not another being in the earth, but in the truth of <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>ANSW. It is ſimply impoſſible to make a rational tryal herin, and not ſee the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of this demonſtration, to be thus clear. I. That there needs no more for any of a ſerious ſpirit, but to come and ſee, what the whole frame of <hi>Heatheniſme</hi> was, and if it be poſſible to deny, even under any ſenſe of the law and dictates of nature, its being the higheſt reproach of mankind; and how the very <hi>myſteries</hi> of that <hi>Heathenish worship,</hi> was ſo horrid and impure, as they needed a vail then from the common view of the world. II. Nor can there be a ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal reflection this day, on that ſtrang mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of <hi>Mahumitaniſme,</hi> but of a viſible <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digy</hi> of the judgment of God, on theſe parts of the earth; upon their apoſtacy from the <hi>Chriſtian faith,</hi> by giving men up to ſuch an
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:205486:27"/>impoſture, as expoſeth the very name and form of religion, to deriſion; and can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver claime a reception either from the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of its rule or internal evidence of the truth therof, or of its having any poſſible conſiſtence with it ſelf. III. That its ſure alſo the <hi>Jewish religion</hi> had never another being but in the truth and faith of <hi>Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and where this fundation is divided from, it hath none at all; yea how that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple unto this day are ſuch a confirming wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the Chriſtian Religion, as its ſtrang this doth not beget deeper impreſſions on mens ſpirit. So that there is an abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, we muſt either forgoe the uſe of reaſon, or ſee, if there were not ſuch a rule given and revealed for commerce betwixt God and man, as the <hi>Scripture,</hi> where the laws and conſtitutions of the <hi>Chriſtian faith,</hi> are for this end held forth, that its then ſure there is no ſuch thing, as any religion in the earth, but what wer ſo highly irrational and abſurd, as should rather juſtify <hi>Atheiſm.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>QU. II. What ſpecial confirmation to <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> can this viſible ſtate of the <hi>Jews</hi> bear, who are in ſo expreſſe an oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the Goſpel of Chriſt?</p>
                        <p>ANSW. If this were brought near our thoughts we should find it one of the great aſſiſtances to our <hi>faith.</hi> I. That its ſure there
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:205486:28"/>is ſuch a people and race, as a living and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible evidence to our ſenſe, of the truth of that renowned <hi>nation, and church of Iſrael,</hi> to which the <hi>oracles of God</hi> were committed, and thus are ſtill, as ſome part of the evident ruines of that once flourishing ſtate. II. That the world may ſee, ſuch a people kept by themſelves and not mixed with the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whoſe fathers from one generation to another did ſtill own the <hi>divinity of the Old Teſtament;</hi> and doth atteſt that doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, in which the truth and ſubſtance of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> lyes, even whilſt with greateſt malice they oppoſe the Chriſtian faith, to witneſſe there can be no poſſible colluſion here. III. Their being under a ſtroak of that <hi>judicial</hi> induration and blindneſſe of mind, as no reaſon could poſſibly compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend ſuch a thing, how they ſee not the light in the very noon-day of the Goſpel, if it were not expreſly fortold their being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded under ſuch an arreſt of judgment, until the <hi>fulneſſe of the gentiles</hi> be brought in. IV. That ſo immediate an appearence of God, is in the <hi>judgment</hi> of that people, both in the manner and continuance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as no inſtance could ever be found to reſemble the ſame, ſince man was formed in the earth; and thus as a conſpicuous mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument of divin wrath, ſet up for every
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:205486:28"/>age and time of the Church, to turn aſide and conſider this great ſight, and inquire what means ſo ſtrang and amazing a thing, as the <hi>ſtate</hi> of the <hi>ſcattered Jews</hi> is, now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the times of the Goſpel. V. That this deſolation on them and ſtroak, had ſuch ſpecial concurring circumſtances for giving light therto; as being not above 48. <hi>years, after the death of Chriſt,</hi> with their hands, as it were, hot and reaking with that <hi>blood</hi> which they had wished on them, and their children; that it should be at that time of the <hi>Paſſover,</hi> which was the very ſame of the <hi>ſufferings of our bleſſed Lord</hi> there, and pointing as with the <hi>finger</hi> at the ſame; as alſo by the <hi>Romans,</hi> whoſe intereſt in their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to Chriſt they pretended to own.</p>
                        <p>QU. III. Is the <hi>way and manner</hi> of the <hi>Goſpels promulgation</hi> ſuch, as no other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion could ever pretend to, and where all may ſee there can be no human intereſt or contrivance in the ſame?</p>
                        <p>ANSW. It is undenyable, that no intereſt elſe was ever in ſuch a way promot and does exceed all natural underſtanding, how the truth of Chriſtianity could in this manner prevail. I. To perſwade men without any <hi>motives,</hi> or inducements from this preſent world, to imbrace a doctrine ſo wholly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to nature; yea to preferr an intereſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:205486:29"/>of things <hi>not ſeen,</hi> and which none ever in the earth ſaw, to the moſt deſirable <hi>objects of ſenſe.</hi> II. To admit no <hi>implicit reception</hi> from any, but on their exacteſt inquiry and tryal herein; or in an other way claime an intereſt in mens affections, but by a full aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of their light and judgment to the ſame. III. To admit no gratification to the moſt predominant deſires and inclinations of men upon any darling ſin, which according to human wiſdome would be judged of an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute neceſſity for gaining any acceptance with ſuch; yea to give no partial reſpect to the greateſt <hi>Princes</hi> more then to the meaneſt. IV. To purſue its intereſt, by ſo plain a diſcovery of the <hi>death, and ſufferings of our bleſſed Lord, with the whole ignominy thereof,</hi> when nothing could more evidently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trol ſuch an end by any rules of human wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and policy, if there had been a poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble acceſſe to conſult flesh and blood herein. V. And its ſure there could be no deſigne, without an immediate divine power, in ſuch a manner to plead the intereſt of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with men, by inſerting affliction, and the <hi>croſſe</hi> in the firſt entry, as <hi>eſſential to the profeſſion thereof,</hi> and holding forth the neceſſity of taking on the <hi>yoke of Chriſt,</hi> without which none can be his <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:205486:29"/>
                        <p>QU. IV. But wherein doth the evidence of that great demonſtration of the Goſpel moſt clearly appear, in the <hi>love and unity of Chriſtians</hi> amonghſt themſelves, which we find Chriſt doth ſo ſpecially preſſe, for this end, that the world might know, and have ſuch a viſible ſeal of his <hi>divine miſſion, Joh.</hi> 17:21.</p>
                        <p>ANSW. The greatneſſe of this demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration may be thus evident to all. I. That its ſo clearly demonſtrative of the <hi>purity of our Religion,</hi> which can admitt of no bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſtrife, recrimination, or ſuch inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencies of heat and paſſion, which are theſe fatal effects of diſcord in the Church; and thus lets us ſee the excellency of the <hi>ſpirit and rule</hi> of the Goſpel. II. That thus alſo we may know the power and efficacy of the truth thereof, <hi>which is according to godlineſſe,</hi> upon mens heart, in ſubduing theſe diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the mind and judgment. III. That this doth ſo ſpecially tend to make religion <hi>lovely,</hi> and to draw forth matter of praiſe and bleſſing to God from the world, when they ſee ſuch a native effect of Chriſtianity as this, to make thoſe who profeſſe the ſame in that manner shine forth in <hi>tenderneſſe, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility,</hi> and <hi>brotherly love,</hi> ſo that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as a publick good and bleſſing to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in the place they are in. IV. This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:205486:30"/>alſo from the nature of that <hi>union in the Church of Chriſt,</hi> and amongſt his followers, which only a divine power could both frame and make effectual; and its ſure no human ſociety or conſtitution could ever claim ſuch an <hi>unity</hi> therein as this is; where not only perſons of all nations and languages and of all conditions, both high and low, but of the moſt different intereſts, humours, and dividing circumſtances in other things, doe yet in ſo marvelous an <hi>harmony</hi> meet in the <hi>body of Chriſt which is his Church</hi> here in the earth. V. Becauſe herein alſo doth the glory and honour of our <hi>bleſſed head,</hi> more eminently appear in ſecuring this <hi>unity</hi> of his Church, under a <hi>diverſity of light</hi> and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment otherwayes, by a ſpirit of love, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and condeſcendence amongſt his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; then by impoſing the moſt ſevere and abſolute uniformity in all things, to be the alone condition of <hi>Chriſtian communion.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>QU. V. But what ſtrength and evidence doth this <hi>demonſtration</hi> of the Goſpel, now bear in ſo <hi>divided a ſtate</hi> of religion, and when the wounds and breaches of the Church this day are like to blood unto death?</p>
                        <p>ANSW. Whatever juſt cauſe be of griefe, yet is there none for darkening the truth of this <hi>demonſtration,</hi> on theſe grounds. I. That
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:205486:30"/>none can deny the perfection of the <hi>rule</hi> of the Goſpel, for the moſt firm and intire uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty amonghſt all the followers of Chriſt on the earth. II. That no oppoſition which is made therto, but what hath been <hi>fortold</hi> as one of the greateſt tryals of the Church un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> and the Spirit of God doth moſt expreſly point at in theſe <hi>latter times.</hi> III. Becauſe the furtheſt <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> thereto can be no more cauſe for any to ſtumble, or queſtion the truth of this <hi>demonſtration,</hi> then that there is a <hi>Devil,</hi> whoſe greateſt deſigne hath ever been to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide and break Chriſtians amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. IV. Becauſe this <hi>union,</hi> which is chiefly <hi>miſtical and inviſible,</hi> is much greater oft, then what this way may appear to the world, and of that kind as is not interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by diſtance of place, or any want of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal communion. V. That ſuch a <hi>guard</hi> is ſet by the Lord unto this piece of his glory, and to oppoſe any invaſion thereon; that there ſtands an <hi>Angel with a flaming ſword,</hi> upon every hand in the <hi>commands</hi> and <hi>threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings</hi> of the Goſpel, to ſecure this bleſſed <hi>unity</hi> of the Saints amonghſt themſelves, ſo as none can invade the ſame but on their hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gheſt peril, of oppoſing that which is as the <hi>apple of Chriſts eye.</hi> VI. That its ever found how this demonſtration hath ſome clear evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:205486:31"/>amonghſt ſuch who are indeed the <hi>Diſciples of Chriſt,</hi> and according to their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance in the life and power of Chriſtianity doth the more brightly shine forth; ſo that the nearer the <hi>lines</hi> are to the <hi>center,</hi> the nearer alſo are they amonghſt themſelves. VII. That in all times there hath been ſome tremenduous <hi>marke</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>f the judgment of God made viſible on ſuch who are <hi>contentious,</hi> and have made it their worke to <hi>cauſe diviſion</hi> in the Church and ſow diſcord among bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
                        <p>QU. VI. But what hath the Church now in theſe latter dayes to compenſe the want of that great demonſtration by <hi>mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> and ſuch extraordinare confirmations of the Chriſtian faith, as were in the firſt times?</p>
                        <p>ANSW. I. That we may ſee how far that <hi>ſeal of martyrdome,</hi> which came in the roome of <hi>miracles</hi> to the Church, hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded that which was in the firſt times of the Goſpel. II. That there hath been ſince ſuch innumberable <hi>shining examples of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> yea theſe continued to this day, whom the world might ſee did walk in the light and power of Chriſtianity, as ſure as men walks, under the power and vertue of a living ſoul. III. That we now ſee what a length the <hi>courſe</hi> of the Goſpel and of the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:205486:31"/>Church militant is come, and how far thus the <hi>times of the Gentiles are fulfilled,</hi> which once was ſo contrare to all human appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. IV. That ſo ſure and exact <hi>a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the Scripture,</hi> is now undenya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the event, and of ſuch great and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velous things which were fortold under the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> that in an ordinare way none could have believed, what we ſee with our eyes, and now have theſe things, which were in former ages the <hi>object of the Churches faith,</hi> made the <hi>object of our ſenſe;</hi> and its ſure this is ſuch <hi>a ſeal</hi> and confirmation to our faith in theſe laſt times as doth much exceed the greateſt <hi>miracles</hi> which were with the <hi>firſt planting of the Goſpel.</hi> V. Though we may not reſolve our faith on any <hi>extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinare providences,</hi> or lay the leaſt weight hereon to ſupport the authority of the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine we profeſſe, ſince this only is founded on that ſacred revelation of <hi>divine truth in the Scripture,</hi> which is that infallible rule to diſcerne true miracles, and what is Gods ſeal herein under the undoubted ſignature and ſtampe of his own power and working in the ſame; yet hath there been ſuch incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trollable evidence of extraordinare ſigns and confirmations to confirme the truth of the Reformed Religion, ſince the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, as in no ages paſt was ever known,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:205486:32"/>but with the firſt planting of the Goſpel among the Gentiles.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="section">
                        <head>SECTION IV.</head>
                        <p>QU. I. IS it cleare and demonſtrable that the <hi>doctrine of Chriſt,</hi> is a <hi>ſoull quickening</hi> and <hi>experimental religion,</hi> and the trial thereof, in its moſt ſupernatural truths, of ſuch rational certitude and evidence, as the world can no more deny or queſtion the ſame then theſe <hi>experiments of nature,</hi> that are of moſt univerſal uſe?</p>
                        <p>ANSW. Though men looked but at a diſtance here or were come from <hi>Heathniſm,</hi> ſo for as to make a ſerious trial of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> its ſure they could not but ſee, and be fully perſwaded in their judgement, hereof on theſe grounds. I. That ſuch a diſcovery is undoubted and cleare in the <hi>Scripture</hi> of ſo great things, as, that there is <hi>a holy Ghoſt,</hi> and his workings on mens ſouls, of <hi>peace with God,</hi> and the <hi>joy of his preſence,</hi> which all who receive the goſpel are called to know and prove on their oun trial. II. That this wittneſſe of Chriſtian <hi>experience,</hi> hath as diſcernable a conſent and harmony there with as face anſwereth to face in the glaſſe, and is cleare to be no <hi>caſual thing,</hi> but where every ſtep in this way of <hi>trial,</hi> is by <hi>Scripture
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:205486:32"/>light,</hi> and what they did before read there, ere they knew it on their oun ſoul. III. That this in all ages of the <hi>church</hi> and wherever ſuch as ſerved God in the ſpirit were found in the moſt <hi>remote parts</hi> from others, hath ſtill been the ſame; and like a <hi>great roll</hi> is tranſmit from one generation to another, with their <hi>confirmatory ſeal, that God is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and true,</hi> in theſe truths of his word which ſeem moſt incredible to the world, &amp; now comes to our hand to require the ſame atteſtation and wittneſſe. IV. That theſe who know and teſtify theſe things once found it not eaſy to beleeve the ſame and did no leſſe judge of ſuch <hi>great experiments of religion</hi> as a dream or imaginary thing then moſt now doe, until they knew them on their ſoul. V. That ſuch alſo have been the moſt <hi>burning and shining lights</hi> that ever were in the church and theſe innumerable in all ages who declare the ſame, yea this in the mouth of the grave and entrance to ane eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſtate when no outward intreſt could ſway them here. VI. That it muſt be a matter of greateſt aſſurance which hath then preſſed the moſt tender <hi>parents</hi> with their laſt and dying breath to commend the ſame <hi>trial to their children,</hi> and to obteſt their making earneſt herein as the greateſt intereſt they could leave them. VII. That what ever
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:205486:33"/>
                           <hi>differences</hi> be oft among theſe in ſome matters of truth: yet, in the certainty of this great trial of the life, power and comforts of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, is ane <hi>harmonious onenes</hi> in the ſame teſtimony in all times of the church. VIII. That if any queſtion this becauſe ſo remote from mens <hi>ſenſes,</hi> and the judgement of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal reaſon; the reality of its <hi>effects,</hi> doth unanſwerably prove both the <hi>reality</hi> and <hi>excellency of the cauſe.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>QU. II. What cleare and rational con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction can yow offer, of ſo great a thing as <hi>converſion</hi> of men from a ſtate of nature, to a <hi>new ſtate by grace,</hi> which doth raiſe them as far above the reſidue of mankinde, as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon doth above the ſtate of the beaſtes?</p>
                        <p>ANSW. Though I should ſtrive againſt the conviction of ſuch a <hi>miracle,</hi> and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Goſpel, as <hi>converſion</hi> is, yet were it not poſſible to deny ſuch demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive evidences as the world cannot but ſee hereof. I. That it is ſure ſuch a <hi>change</hi> is made eſſentially requiſite to the <hi>being,</hi> and conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of a Chriſtian, by the whole conſent of the Scripture. II. That there was never yet ane <hi>argument in nature,</hi> for ones being a Chriſtian in the life and power thereof what ever may be for a naked form or shew. III. That they are not a <hi>few,</hi> but innumerable inſtances in all times and of all rancks &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:205486:33"/>of men on whom ſo great a <hi>change</hi> and difference hath been made thus evident, both from themſelves what once they were, and from the reſidue of the world. IV. That this hath been not only upon ſuch as have been <hi>ſignally impious</hi> in their practiſe, but who in their judgment were wont to deread holyneſſe as a fancy, ſo as <hi>Atheiſts</hi> muſt grant that there have been as profeſt <hi>Atheiſts</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times as themſelves, who have been made ſuch conſpicuous monuments of the power of the goſpel. V. That none can object here, as once the <hi>Jewes</hi> did, doe any of the <hi>rulers,</hi> or ſuch as the world counts moſt <hi>wiſe,</hi> and knowing ſtand wittneſſes to the ſame; when it is ſo knowen there have not been more <hi>wiſe, learned,</hi> and <hi>judicious</hi> in the things of reaſon upon the earth, then ſuch as have been eminent examples of the power of converſion. VI. That its mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous <hi>effects</hi> in ſubduing men, to what once was there predominant intereſt and idol, and to part from what had been as their <hi>right eye, or hand</hi> could only be from ane immediat di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine power. VII. That ſuch as were grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt adverſaryes to the truth, have been made no leſſe eminent <hi>inſtruments</hi> in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of Chriſt, and choiſe veſſels of honour, then once they were in their enmity and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. VIII. That this change hath
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:205486:34"/>been ſo diſcernable in times of moſt viſible perſecutions and hazard, when no outward advantage or gaine could have the leaſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence thereon. Now as theſe are demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrably cleare, ſo can there be no poſſible ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to queſtion this. I. That the <hi>Scripture</hi> is faithfull and true in ſo great a diſcovery. II. That there is a <hi>divine ſpirit</hi> and a power above nature, which accompanyes the ſame in ſuch a change. III. That there are ſurely, <hi>contrary ſtates in ane other world,</hi> when they are ſo undeniably manifeſt here.</p>
                        <p>QU. III. But can ſo great ane experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of religion as that of <hi>communion betwixt God and men,</hi> here upon earth be made ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally convinceing to ſuch as are themſelves ſtrangers thereto; and for a further confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Chriſtian faith?</p>
                        <p>ANSW. Though this be ane <hi>experiment</hi> of divine truth of a more tranſcendent intereſt and value then all that ever were in nature, yet is it no leſſe <hi>evident,</hi> there can be no poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible deluſion herein; if I. to which ſo <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable a company</hi> beares teſtimony and hath tranſmit the ſame, as that which not once or twice they have proven but in the continued trial of their life. II. That its knowen to the world, how ſuch as teſtify what they doe, and have ſo oft found in the retirement of their ſouls with God, are of as
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:205486:34"/>
                           <hi>diſcerning ſpirits</hi> to know the true value of things, as any elſe; yea ſuch whoſe teſtimony in other things the worſt of men could not refuſe nor deny. III. How its undeniably evident, ſuch muſt know ane other acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and <hi>ſociety then that of men;</hi> that not only makes theſe hid exerciſes of godlines ſo deſireable, where all may ſee they more flee then follow any humane wittneſſe, but thus makes ſo viſible a change oft both in their caſe and countenance after moſt ſad anguish and dounecaſtings of ſpirit. IV. That it is ſo evident alſo how ſuch as are moſt ſerious this way, have been viſibly oft rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed above their ordinary caſe, and frame in prayer, and other dutyes of religion; yea, in that manner, as they who never knew, there is a <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> but by report, could not withſtand ſo cleare conviction of the reality hereof, that can beget ſuch <hi>liberty, humble tenderneſſe</hi> and melting of heart, yea ſuch diſcernable joy and confidence. V. That no deluſion or falſe shew can be here, when its ever ſeen, how ſuch as are moſt ſerious and frequent in <hi>prayer</hi> and theſe hid retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with God, are the moſt flourishing alſo in the <hi>vitals</hi> of Chriſtianity, and have the moſt honorable luſtre, and appearance of any in their profeſſion. VI. That its ſuch only whoſe joy and comfort is moſt ſpecially
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:205486:35"/>diſcernable beyond others when theſe lower ſprings of outward help and encouragement are moſt viſibly shut up.</p>
                        <p>QU. IV. Is that great, and experimental part of religion in the <hi>power of the conſcience</hi> over man, ſuch as may be as demonſtrable to the world, as the truth of a rational being?</p>
                        <p>ANSW. It may be matter of wonder how men are not ſtruck with deeper convictions hereon, when they cannot but ſee. I. That though this be the greateſt <hi>tormentor,</hi> and troubler of the world, yet is there no poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble retreat from its power tho they should flee to the uttermoſt parts of the earth, but doth thus enforce the ſoul to a <hi>reflexion on its ſelfe</hi> even when it trembleth at that ſight. II. Which cauſeth ſuch feare and horrour upon the commitment of <hi>ſecret ſins,</hi> when no dread of humane wittneſſe, or of viſible hazard this way could ever occaſion this. III. Which admits no violence in any to outdare the ſame, but is a power that the <hi>greateſt monarches</hi> finde to be ſtronger then they; and is ſuch, as theſe oft are enforced for a preſent eaſe, and releefe either to divert, or bribe the ſame by ſome falſe grounds of peace. IV. That it conſtraines men to <hi>juſtify God,</hi> and <hi>judge themſelves</hi> when his hand doth purſue them, and to finde out
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:205486:35"/>their ſin, and guilt, which was before hid. V. Which makes men alſo afrayed to be <hi>alo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> with themſelves; and to tremble at the word of truth, becauſe its <hi>light doth torment them,</hi> by that unavoidable application the conſcience makes hereof. VI. Yea makes mens guilt ſo legible oft in their countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, even when they ſtudy moſt to conceale it, as all may ſee, there is ane accuſer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in whoſe authority and power cannot poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be declined. VII. Which with ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable a <hi>conſidence,</hi> and <hi>ſecurity</hi> doth ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port mens ſpirit and makes it eaſy to ſuſtain its greateſt infirmityes from without, when it is a friend; yea, thus upholds the oppreſt with unſpeakable peace and comfort, when it doth oft cauſe the oppreſſours to tremble.</p>
                        <p>QU. V. But what doth moſt neceſſarly reſult from ſo cleare a demonſtration as the <hi>conſcience</hi> is for confirming of our faith?</p>
                        <p>ANSW. I. That its infallibly thus cleare, how there is a <hi>higher power</hi> and <hi>judgment,</hi> to which all mankinde is ſubjected, &amp; gives the world an unavoidable demonſtration, both of the being of <hi>God,</hi> &amp; the <hi>truth of his word,</hi> in the great &amp; ſupernatural diſcovery which it makes hereof. II. That there is a ſupream &amp; infallible law alſo &amp; inviſible judge above us, under whoſe power and authority this <hi>court of juſtice</hi> doth without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:205486:36"/>both <hi>ſummond, arrest,</hi> bring in <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> and <hi>ſentence</hi> great and ſmall. III. That the <hi>internal government</hi> of our <hi>bleſſed Lord,</hi> this way both in the ſeverity of his rebukes and moſt ſenſible enlargements of peace and comfort is unavoydably demonſtrat. IV. That it beares ſo clear evidence to that unknowen and undoubted <hi>releef;</hi> and how none elſe could be ever found, to theſe wounds and ſtings of the conſcience, but in the <hi>light and power of Chriſtianity.</hi> V. That it is ſimply impoſſible for men to delight freely in a courſe of ſin, when no humane power can diſarm the conſcience of that ſo intollerable <hi>a ſting,</hi> by which it begins ſo early a hell within the ſoul. VI. That ſuch is the power and peace of a good conſcience as can make it ſtand unbroken amidſt the greateſt ruines and terrours of the world when under ſuch a guard, as it is wrapped up in its own <hi>innocency.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="section">
                        <head>SECTION V.</head>
                        <p>QU. I. IS the evidence of a <hi>Kingdome of darknes,</hi> in a direct oppoſition and contrariety, to that Kingdome of light, which Chriſt hath ſet up by the Goſpel, ſuch as the certainty thereof may be a matter of ſenſe, as well as of faith?</p>
                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:205486:36"/>
                        <p>ANSW. Since this is of ſuch ſpecial uſe, both to confirm the chriſtian faith and awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ſuch to deeper reflexion on the ſame, with whom there ſeemes no acceſſe to deall, but by <hi>proofes</hi> from <hi>palpable experience;</hi> it is not poſſible to deny. I. That there is ſuch a power, as the <hi>devil</hi> and theſe <hi>wicked ſpirits</hi> incompaſſing the earth, yea that have ane ordinar and familiar converſe with many therein. II. That theſe ſpirits though once originally excellent, have fallen into ſuch ane apoſtacy, as all may ſee their aim and only pleaſure, is to <hi>dishonour God,</hi> and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troy his <hi>image</hi> in man. III. That it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to deny the <hi>marks</hi> of that power and conqueſt, which the <hi>Prince of this world,</hi> hath every where amongſt men; yea how vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly many are transformed into his image into ſuch prodigious and deſperat acts of wickedneſſe; as we should think humane nature could not but tremble at. IV. That none can control the certainty both of <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>reaſon</hi> which is in the truth of <hi>apparitions</hi> and <hi>bodily poſſeſſions</hi> of men in all ages, and in all places of the earth; and can need no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration for this, that in many places of the earth, the <hi>devil</hi> is both viſibly and audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly knowen. V. That he is ſo manifeſt in his appearence as a <hi>ſpirit of blaſphemy,</hi> which impetuouſly acts men to war againſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:205486:37"/>with their <hi>tongue</hi> in ſuch oathes and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing as hath no caſual pleaſure, or gain here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; yea, as a <hi>ſpirit of deluſion</hi> in ſo viſible ane excitement of others to theſe extravagancies under a shew of religion, as are incompati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with any uſe of judgement or reaſon. VI. That ſo innumerable a company of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane race, hath in all ages been in a <hi>formal,</hi> and <hi>expreſſe covenant</hi> with theſe powers of darkneſſe is undenyable upon the moſt ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re and impartial inquiry herein.</p>
                        <p>Qu. II. What ſpecial <hi>aſſiſtence</hi> to your faith doth the certainty of theſe <hi>powers</hi> of <hi>darkneſſe</hi> bring therewith?</p>
                        <p>ANSW. I. That ſuch a party both in their nature and continued actings, are in a ſtated oppoſition to the Kingdome of Chriſt. II. That it is ſo viſible the <hi>prey</hi> which theſe mighty hunters do follow is not our <hi>body,</hi> or the things of this life, but is with reſpect to ane <hi>immortal ſoul,</hi> and ane <hi>after ſtate,</hi> and that thus man might be made sharer of the ſame miſery under which they are conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. III. That all may ſee their being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der reſtraint of a ſupream power above them &amp; under ſuch <hi>chaines</hi> as do irreſiſtibly bound their <hi>rage,</hi> and <hi>enmity</hi> againſt man by ane <hi>inviſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>le guard</hi> and <hi>hedge</hi> which they cannot breake over. IV. How their greateſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, and ſtrugling is againſt the <hi>converſion,</hi>
                           <pb n="69" facs="tcp:205486:37"/>of ſinners to God, and to hold faſt his poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion in ſuch, as the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> doth not, more clearely move for their reſcue, then theſe doe to croſſe that bleſſed deſign of the Goſpel. V. That there are none ſerious in the truth and life of religion but finde themſelves purſued by ſuch ane <hi>adverſary;</hi> and to have as diſcernably another party then themſelves, or the world to conflict with as if they ſaw them in <hi>a viſible shape.</hi> VI. That by the <hi>Goſpel</hi> and within the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct of the church, is ſo diſcernably a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>reſtraint of Satans dominion</hi> and power then in all the earth beſides; yea that the advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of being within the <hi>external covenant of Baptiſme,</hi> is ſo demonſtrable as the leaſt yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or tendency to a renouncing of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, or any acts of <hi>homage,</hi> for making uſe of his help, hath ever made way for ſome more extraordinary power of the <hi>devil</hi> over ſuch then others. VII. Thus alſo is a moſt undeniable confirmation given of ane <hi>inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble world,</hi> and of ſuch <hi>intellectual beings</hi> the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, as are far above man; yea that there is ſo undoubted ane intercourſe betwixt men and ſpirits, as may clearely shew that intereſt mens ſoul hath in another ſtate and world then this.</p>
                        <p>QU. III. Is that great truth of the <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality of the ſoull,</hi> and its never dying ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:205486:38"/>after death, as fully demonſtrable to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as it is by the furtheſt certainty of faith?</p>
                        <p>ANSW. Though it be ſo amazing a thing to beleeve ane <hi>immortal ſoull,</hi> and <hi>eternal ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te,</hi> wherein it muſt shortly enter, as by few ſeemes to be apprehended, yet are its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrative evidences, ſuch that except men loſe all ſence and uſe of reaſon, it is not poſſible to deny. I. That there is ſuch ane <hi>immaterial and active ſubſtance</hi> as the <hi>ſoull,</hi> which can admit no cauſe, either of its decay or diſſolution, from the body, yea that the greateſt excellency of this viſible creation, is here, that ſuch a vital <hi>beam of life, light,</hi> and <hi>immortality,</hi> as the <hi>ſoull</hi> of man is therein. II. Though we cannot ſee this rare and wonderful being, yet it is here we both <hi>ſee,</hi> and <hi>feel</hi> it to be ſomething <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the body,</hi> and to have a diſtinct in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, both in its griefs and comforts. III. How it can have no dependance on the body in its being, which doth no way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend thereon in its actings and exerciſe; but is oft moſt vigorous and cleare, in its exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, not only when moſt <hi>ſeparat</hi> and abſtract from ſenſible things, but when the <hi>flesh</hi> is under the greateſt decay, and neare its <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution;</hi> to shew the <hi>ſoull</hi> lyeth not a dying with the body, but hath its <hi>diſtinct ſubſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,</hi>
                           <pb n="71" facs="tcp:205486:38"/>to live in a ſeparat ſtate, when it dyes. IV. Its being peculiarly framed for conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, and intercourſe with ſpiritual beings, yea is only of the viſible creation admit to fellowship with the inviſible God, and to have reflex acts upon it ſelf. V. How it is a <hi>being</hi> of a higher nature and value, then the ſun, moon and ſtarrs; which not only can know, and conceive of things above the evidence and impreſſions of <hi>ſenſe,</hi> but to make a rational choiſe of good, though croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe to any ſenſual pleaſure; yea to rejoyce, and have its proper delights, when the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is afflicted and in pain; nor can be defiled from the moſt loathſome ſores and defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the flesh, ſo as I muſt needs ſee both its dominion and preheminence over the body, and to have aſſuredlie a ſubſiſtence without the ſame. VI. That it is ſuch a being, as is capable of a happineſſe beyond the who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le extent of the world, &amp; hath theſe intellec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual facultyes, which cannot poſſibly want, both objects ſuitable thereto, and injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, above the ſenſes. VII. That the moſt choiſe and excellent, are uſually moſt afflicted, and crushed under the feet of their oppreſſours, whilſt theſe flourish in the earth and have no bands in their death, ſo as ſuch were of all men the moſt miſerable, if in this life, both their being and bleſſedneſſe
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:205486:39"/>were founded. VIII. That there is ſo <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal a ſenſe</hi> of <hi>immortality,</hi> as theſe who both feare and hate the evidences hereof, yet under ſome conſtraint of reaſon hath the ſame for a continued terrour. IX. That it is ſure the <hi>certainty of death,</hi> makes it ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply impoſſible, for things only ſuited to this life of ſenſe, to be the ultimate good, or fruition of man; ſince elſe the <hi>beaſts</hi> should have a greater happineſſe then ſuch, if it were not from reſpect to ane after and <hi>immortal ſtate.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>QU. IV. What confirmation to your faith does that great and amazing change by <hi>death</hi> offer, when it would ſeem to be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing meerly <hi>natural?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>ANSW. Though the only wife God moves herein according to the nature of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſes, and that it hath various wayes of approach unto men, yet may all ſee with the furtheſt conviction of rational evidence, as well as certainty of faith, I. How <hi>death in its firſt conſtitution is penal;</hi> and comes by a divine appointment unto all, not meerly as men but as ſinners, and to be thus no <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral accident</hi> and reſult of our primitive and original frames. II. That its <hi>death,</hi> as a <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty</hi> which keepes the feare and dread there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſo much on all living, as that laſt period, when the eternal ſtate of men is then caſt.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:205486:39"/>III. That the <hi>ſting</hi> and bitterneſſe of ſin, is ſo manifeſt in innumerable diſeaſes and ſtroakes of death, which many feel an 100. times ere they <hi>dye</hi> once, beyond other of the creatures. IV. Though the ſentence of <hi>dying</hi> is on all, yet ſo great a difference is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the ſaints and reſidue of men here, that its <hi>penal</hi> execution on the ungodly, is ſuch as nature can give no ſupport herein. V. That <hi>ſupernatural preſages</hi> and warnings hereof ere it come, are in all times ſo known and ſure; yea ſuch extraordinare evidences ſometimes of the preciſe time, as could have no poſſible riſe from any <hi>natural cauſe.</hi> VI. That its immediat <hi>commiſſion</hi> from a ſupream and <hi>inviſible power,</hi> is ſo evident in ſuch exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions oft, of this ſentence, by <hi>ſword, famine</hi> and <hi>peſtilence,</hi> as the viſible <hi>finger of God,</hi> in a juſt retribution unto men for ſin, may be no leſſe ſeen, and a ſupernatural <hi>cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality,</hi> then the effects have been undoubted and cleare; to shew ſuch is the ſtate of man, as this great revolution by <hi>death,</hi> doth each moment depend on a call from heaven. VII. That the certainty of ſomething <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural</hi> herein, as the King of terrours, is ſo known as no releefe can poſſibly be found, but in the <hi>truth and power of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> to ſet men both above the feare of death and ane after ſtate, when once it comes
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:205486:40"/>neere. VIII. Yea that it is ſurely above the poſſibility of nature, which can beare out in this great adventure and <hi>trial</hi> of mens <hi>faith,</hi> both in the truth and ſtrength thereof, at <hi>death,</hi> for which end the Lord hath thus choiſed that by ſo ſtrange ane <hi>entry,</hi> and at ſo dark a port they should firſt paſſe to the full enjoyment of that glorious ſtate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove.</p>
                        <p>QU. V. What <hi>evidence</hi> and <hi>demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> can yow shew, to confirm ſo great a faith of an <hi>eternal glory</hi> abiding the Saints in heaven, and of its <hi>earnest</hi> and <hi>firſt fruits</hi> here, as may ſtrike ane undeniable convic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hereof on the world?</p>
                        <p>ANSW. I. By that viſible <hi>ripening</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance to ſuch a ſtate in all the degrees of a Chriſtians grouth, to a more <hi>full ſtature of the man in Christ,</hi> as may be no leſſe evident then the natural grouth of our body. II. That though the opening of theſe <hi>gates</hi> of the <hi>ſecond world</hi> be hid, as no humane ſenſe can diſcern the <hi>ſpirit</hi> in its <hi>aſcent</hi> through theſe higher regions, to that unconceivea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>paradiſe and glory</hi> in the <hi>third heaven,</hi> yet is the <hi>triumphant entry</hi> and paſſage of innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Chriſtians at death, ſuch as hath oft been, a matter of ſenſe and cleareſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to the world. III. That ſuch alſo were both <hi>humble, tender,</hi> and <hi>ſincere</hi> in
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:205486:40"/>their life, and then in ſo great a compoſure of judgement, as all might ſee they knew what made them glade and could ſwallow up both the feares and bitterneſſe of death; yea that this was not given for their own ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port only, but for a more <hi>publick uſe,</hi> to the conviction and confirming of others. IV. That the ſtate of glory is demonſtrable and hath been oft brought downe to mens ſenſe, by theſe <hi>ravishing joyes of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres of Chriſt,</hi> and exultation of ſpirit even in the <hi>flames.</hi> V. By ſuch ſupernatural comforts as attend the life of Chriſtianity, and can have no poſſible riſe from the flesh and outward cauſes, with that <hi>joy and peace,</hi> which by ſo natural a reſult followes <hi>well-doing;</hi> and any ſervice of love for Chriſt as all may ſee to be the <hi>firſt fruits</hi> of that har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt which is above. VI. By ſo rare and marvellous a frame of the <hi>new man,</hi> ſet up in this lower region of grace, in ſo diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable a conformity to the bleſſed God, and reſemblence to another ſtate then here, to which the world is but as a place of pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, trial and a <hi>preparatory ſtate</hi> only. VII. By ſuch viſible returns of joy and comfort of Chriſtians after ſaddeſt conflicts and downecaſtings, and day-break of theſe <hi>vital quickning beames of divine light,</hi> that have been no leſſe evident oft, then that of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:205486:41"/>the <hi>martyrs</hi> at the ſtake, who cryed out, <hi>Now he is come, he is come.</hi> VIII. By theſe <hi>breathings of love</hi> after ane unſeen Chriſt and viſible effects of its power on men, as might shew ſome begun <hi>tranſlation</hi> of the ſoull ſo far herein, as to be more where it loves then it lives. IX. Though we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee here, that <hi>ineffable glory,</hi> which is above, but should have our <hi>faith</hi> inſteed of <hi>eyes;</hi> yet ſuch is the truth of <hi>holineſſe,</hi> as doth not only evidence, but in its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture partake of a <hi>future glory;</hi> ſo as every degree and act thereof doth enter in a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun ſtate of <hi>fruition</hi> and bleſſedneſſe, and makes it ſimply impoſſible for a <hi>good man</hi> in any true exerciſe of godlineſs, <hi>not to be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py alſo,</hi> and thus in a more near capacity to know that <hi>joy unſpeakable,</hi> and <hi>full of glory,</hi> which is above. X. By ſo ſure, known, and tryed a paſſage betwixt heaven and mens ſouls in <hi>prayer,</hi> with ſo ſetled a trade of <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce</hi> this way, and certain returns, as with aſſurance ſuch can ſay, though they muſt <hi>change their place,</hi> yet not their <hi>company.</hi> XI. That the whole diſpenſations of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in <hi>Iſra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ls paſſage</hi> through the <hi>wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and to ſo excellent a country as <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> is no leſſe ſure in it ſelf, then that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> was given for an embleme and <hi>type</hi> of the jurt nying and militant ſtate of the faints here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:205486:41"/>to be a ſolemne pledge of that <hi>Canaan a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove.</hi> XII. That ſuch is the magnificence, harmony, and order of theſe viſible <hi>heavens,</hi> and <hi>celeſtial bodies</hi> there, with their different <hi>degrees</hi> of <hi>glory,</hi> (though all illuminated from the ſame fountain of light the ſun) as we may judge by a <hi>divine ordination</hi> have ſome peculiar reſpect to that end, to awake &amp; raiſe our thoughts thus, to theſe <hi>higher regions of glory,</hi> which are above all theſe, by what is thus viſible to our eyes; where the redeemed of the Lord shall be ever fixed, &amp; <hi>shine forth as the Sun in the kingdome of their Father.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>QU. VI. What viſible and awakning <hi>evidences</hi> are there of the truth of an <hi>Hell,</hi> and that ſtate of <hi>horrour</hi> and <hi>torment</hi> in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world, which even to mens <hi>ſenſes</hi> here, might preſent the certainty thereof?</p>
                        <p>ANSW. I. That it can be no more ſure, there is ſuch a power and party as that of the <hi>Devils,</hi> then the reality of ſome ſuch <hi>horrid region</hi> and place alſo, to which they belong, and are adjudged to. II. From ſo innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a company of <hi>human race,</hi> as are not only in the viſible ſervice of theſe <hi>infernal ſpirits,</hi> but partakers of the ſame nature and <hi>enmity</hi> againſt the <hi>H. God</hi> and his <hi>image,</hi> as doth clearly witneſſe their reſpect and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency to the ſame <hi>ſtate</hi> and <hi>place,</hi> and to be conſederate in their <hi>judgement,</hi> as they were
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:205486:42"/>here in their <hi>ſin.</hi> III. From ſuch viſible impreſſions of <hi>vindictive juſtice</hi> on mens ſouls, with ſuch <hi>horrour of conſcience</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable torments this way, as in all ages have been known by moſt remarkable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, when not in the leaſt diſtemper of their natural reaſon, that may preſent to mens <hi>ſenſes</hi> ſomething of a <hi>viſible Hell,</hi> as convincingly, as if one had <hi>riſen from the dead,</hi> for the ſame. IV. From ſuch a trembling <hi>ſenſe,</hi> and <hi>terror of divine ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance,</hi> as oft follows upon <hi>horrid acts of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe</hi> and moſt eminently then breaks forth upon a ſurpriſing ſight of <hi>death,</hi> as all may ſee ſomething more dreadful herein then the diſſolution of nature and the power and preſent arreſt of a <hi>future judgment</hi> made viſible in the ſame. V. From ſuch begun degrees, as that of <hi>blaſpheming and rage</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, becauſe of his <hi>plagues,</hi> with theſe <hi>prodigies of cruelty</hi> exerced by men here in the earth, as might be evident to all to be more then human, and rather the effects of infernal ſpirits acting in a human shape. VI. From ſo clear a <hi>prelude</hi> of the ſame in that judicial <hi>obduration,</hi> and blindneſſe, ſo many are given up to under the greateſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries of light, ſo as all may ſee their being thus bound over in <hi>chains,</hi> and shut up in <hi>priſon,</hi> until <hi>death</hi> bring them forth to the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:205486:42"/>
                           <hi>execution;</hi> and how no relief or application of the means of grace hath then any more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. VII. From ſuch a mape &amp; shaddow of <hi>eternal vengeance,</hi> in theſe terrible acts of divine judgment inflicted here on <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> and <hi>perſecuters</hi> of the <hi>truth,</hi> and other flagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious perſons which with the very firſt view might preſent an awful and immediat appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of God in the ſame, and that ſome <hi>ſtrang</hi> and ſupernatural <hi>punishment</hi> is oft vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible on the <hi>workers of iniquity.</hi> VIII. And what ever be of natural cauſes in ſuch viſible repreſentations here in the earth, as that <hi>ſulphureous lake</hi> where once <hi>Sodom</hi> was, and theſe burning mountains ſuch as <hi>Haecla, Et<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> and <hi>Veſuvius,</hi> yet we may truely judge their being thus ſet before the world as ſome viſible memorials of theſe <hi>infernal flames;</hi> and as it were ſo many <hi>lumeheads</hi> thereof, for ſuch who will not believe the ſame, becauſe they doe not yet ſee or feal ſuch a thing.</p>
                        <p>QU. VII. What <hi>aſſiſtances</hi> hath our <hi>faith,</hi> of that great and wonderful truth of the <hi>reſurrection of the body,</hi> after its diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the <hi>grave unto duſt?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>ANSW. I. From that viſible and ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious frame of the <hi>heavens</hi> and the <hi>earth,</hi> when its ſure that the ſame <hi>infinite power,</hi> that hath not only made man, but the whole creation, can as eaſily collect and recount
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:205486:43"/>the diſperſed <hi>ashes</hi> of the <hi>body,</hi> as <hi>form the ſame.</hi> II. From that greateſt pledge hereof, in the <hi>reſurrection of the body of Chriſt.</hi> III. From that tribulation and ſore pain, that the ſaints here in their outward man are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to, ſince it is ſure that in the holy juſtice of God, he did not give ſuch <hi>bodies</hi> for <hi>labour,</hi> and for toyl, and to his <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,</hi> to endure unexpreſſible torments for Chriſt, to perish for ever. IV. From theſe viſible <hi>reſemblances</hi> and <hi>prefigurations</hi> of the <hi>reſurrection</hi> which the Lord hath given to confirme our faith herein, in the ordinare courſe and <hi>productions of nature;</hi> ſo as all may ſee how every <hi>night</hi> is as the <hi>grave</hi> of the <hi>day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light,</hi> and each morning a new reſurrection of the ſame; and how viſible an image of <hi>death</hi> is in each ſeaſon of the <hi>winter,</hi> with ſo marvelous and beatiful a <hi>reſurrection</hi> of the earth, on every return of the ſpring, in the <hi>herbs, flowers and plants,</hi> taking life and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing again, in the <hi>leaves, bloſſomes and fruites;</hi> yea this in ſuch a variety, as may no leſſe convincingly evidence an infinite divine power herein, then that the ſame body of man should be raiſed at the <hi>laſt day.</hi> V. From that continued <hi>miracle</hi> of the <hi>harvest,</hi> after the <hi>ſeed-time,</hi> with ſo amazing a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of the <hi>grain ſowen</hi> in the earth, and its firſt dying there before it be quickned,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:205486:43"/>ſo as to be at laſt brought to 30, 60, yea ſometimes an <hi>hundred fold,</hi> out of the very ſame grain; which to theſe who had never before known the ſame would ſeem incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp; above all reaſon to conceave, or bear credite therto.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>
                           <hi>The</hi> confirming worke of Religion, <hi>impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven wich reſpect to the</hi> times, <hi>to</hi> clear the way of the Lord <hi>herein, before this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and let us ſee how nothing is ſo ſtrang in the</hi> events <hi>of this day, which should not more ſtrenthen, then shake, and that the</hi> God of the Reformed Church <hi>doth ſtill own the ſame intereſt, according to his</hi> faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: <hi>which is here briefly pointed at, upon ſome ſpecial</hi> inquiry, <hi>propoſed about the ſame.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </argument>
                     <div n="1" type="section">
                        <head>SECTION I.</head>
                        <p>QU. WHat can afford both <hi>light,</hi> and <hi>confirmation to our faith,</hi> in ſuch a time, when we ſee the <hi>worke of the Lord,</hi> about his Church, to be moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markably now a <hi>worke of judgement,</hi> with ſuch dark and ſearching tryals therwith, as former times have not known.</p>
                        <pb n="82" facs="tcp:205486:44"/>
                        <p>ANSW. It is ſure, we have ſeen nothing, but what might have been too evidently looked for, and that we can pretend no want of <hi>light</hi> herein, upon theſe grounds. I. That the <hi>Trialls</hi> of a Church, should be ſuited to the meaſure of their <hi>talent of light,</hi> &amp; when this hath been in ſome more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare way diſpenſed, that ſome remarkably <hi>ſearching times</hi> might be expected to follow; nor can it be now ſtrang to us, that ſuch things fall in with this <hi>day,</hi> which did not meet the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> at the <hi>firſt entry of the Reformation,</hi> who then had not ſo clear diſcoveries of the truth, and that meaſure of <hi>confirmation</hi> therein, which hath been ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce. II. That ſome unuſual <hi>tryals,</hi> and <hi>conflicts,</hi> in the Lords uſuall method of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, should be ſuited alſo, to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that <hi>worke,</hi> which he is bringing forth, may be no ſtrang thing; and to ſee a time of ſuch ſore wreſtlings as this, when all things ſeem to cry, <hi>be in pain</hi> as <hi>Micah</hi> 4:20. Yea when ſome great <hi>event</hi> of the Scripture is to be revealed to the world, and near to its <hi>full hight,</hi> and <hi>period of accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as we have ſafe ground for aſſurance of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ay. III. Nor hath this ſad and diſmal hower on the Church, been more obvious then the <hi>provoking cauſe</hi> hereof, in which the <hi>holy righteouſneſſe of God,</hi> may be
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:205486:44"/>no leſſe clear then the <hi>cloud</hi> now is dark; when ſuch a viſible falling of hath been from that <hi>love, tendernes,</hi> and <hi>power of religion</hi> that did formerly attend its profeſſion; as for theſe many years paſt we might have ſeen that ſome ſore and remarkable judgment was coming, and that if we had not been in ſuch a maner undone, we were, under ſome ſadder ſtrock of ſpiritual judgment, ready to be undone. IV. Yea it hath been too viſible, that ſuch <hi>evils</hi> followed the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches,</hi> as in no time it was ever known, that the holy God, did paſſe ſuch by, without ſome ſignal evidence of his <hi>wrath</hi> againſt the ſame before the world. V. We know that <hi>carnal confidence</hi> hath a <hi>cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe</hi> ever waiting upon it in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> which none can take of, or make that thrive which God hath himſelf curſed; and it is too viſible how far we have gone thus out of the way of our ſtrenth, by ſuch eager ſeeking <hi>human props,</hi> &amp; ſupport, as we have for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ot the <hi>guide of our youth,</hi> and <hi>convenant of our God,</hi> and what great things he hath formerly done in the greateſt ſtraits of his Church, when the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re was much humble <hi>truſting,</hi> with little ſence; as though the <hi>ſpirit of the Lord,</hi> had not done more to recover his truth, then all human might or power, ever could doe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="section">
                        <pb n="84" facs="tcp:205486:45"/>
                        <head>SECTION II.</head>
                        <p>QU. WHat talent, are we ſtill accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for to ſupport our faith againſt the greateſt <hi>fears</hi> of this time, from theſe <hi>immediate appearances of God,</hi> and of the <hi>glory of his power,</hi> for the ſame <hi>truth and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe</hi> of the <hi>Reformed Church,</hi> we are now cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to contend for, which hath been ſince the reformation when ſo ſtrong &amp; unuſual a tyde, now is againſt the ſame?</p>
                        <p>ANSW. If men shut not their eyes, and <hi>hide</hi> this great <hi>talent</hi> of the <hi>workes of God, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ground,</hi> its ſure none can queſtion ſuch a <hi>ſeal,</hi> which before the ſun, to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazment and conviction of the world, hath been put to the truth of the <hi>Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;</hi> that we are now ſiſted under ſuch a <hi>call,</hi> as the Church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4:34. to <hi>ask of the times, that are past,</hi> ſince <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raels</hi> coming out of Egypt, and ſince the firſt planting of the <hi>Gentil Church,</hi> by the <hi>Goſpel, whither there hath been ſo great a thing as this in the earth, that God hath eſſayed to ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke to himſelf a people from the midſt of other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> by <hi>temptations, by ſigns, and by won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> and <hi>by war,</hi> and by <hi>a mighty hand,</hi> and by <hi>an ouſtretched arm,</hi> and <hi>by great terrours,</hi> according to all that the <hi>Lord our God</hi> hath
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:205486:45"/>done for the reſcue of his people, in theſe <hi>laſt times,</hi> from <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> bondage and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and ſettling them in a church ſtate; but <hi>unto us was this shewed, that we might know, that the Lord he is God, and there is noncelſe beſide him:</hi> yea are ſtill called to ſee, and be as <hi>eye witneſſes</hi> to theſe things; I. How <hi>bright a day</hi> of the Goſpel of Chriſt, did goe before this great <hi>darkneſſe</hi> on the Church, and what a ſolemne <hi>triumph</hi> in theſe late ages the <hi>truth</hi> hath had over <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> ſo as the <hi>full ſtrock</hi> and ruine of his kingdome, which is ſure and eſtablished in the <hi>promiſe of God,</hi> ſeems not now more marvelous and above human appearence, then what <hi>we have ſeen,</hi> in the begun degrees of its accomplishment. II. In how few years alſo, there was, as a <hi>new Chriſtian world</hi> brought forth, in that ſwift courſe and progreſſe which the inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of the Reformed Churches had, ſo as between the year 1621, and 1560. ſuch fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>plantations</hi> of the Goſpel, were ſetled in a Church ſtate; which all may ſee was the immediate worke and power of God; to shew that none should fear, or <hi>ſtagger at his promiſe,</hi> though the waters yet ſwell, and come to the <hi>flowings of Jordan,</hi> and difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties appear unſuperable to human ſenſe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this great things which the Lord hath do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. III. How extraordinare a <hi>calling,</hi> and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:205486:46"/>excitment of <hi>inſtruments,</hi> was then evident, for the ſervice of that time, and <hi>reapers</hi> thus eminently prepared for ſo great an <hi>harveſt</hi> of the Goſpel, as might put the world to inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re whence theſe were, in ſo numerous a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence, when a few of ſuch a ſpirit, we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſo rarely to be found in many ages before. IV. Yea ſuch an acceſſion alſo, of <hi>ſpiritual gifts,</hi> and induments then for <hi>building</hi> of the Church, as had not been formerly known, ſince the firſt coming of the Goſpel to the <hi>Gentils;</hi> wherein it may be ſaid, the <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of theſe <hi>laſt times</hi> hath even in ſome degree exceeded that of the <hi>firſt.</hi> V. And can the moſt diſmal things of this time, countervail the <hi>confirmations of our faith,</hi> who have ſo clearly ſeen, with the firſt breaking up of the <hi>pur doctrine of Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>power and life of Chriſtianity</hi> came therwith to the world, as a <hi>ſeal,</hi> and atteſtation therto, beyond any <hi>miracles;</hi> yea how innumberable a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, in theſe laſt ages of different tongues and languages, and theſe ſo remot from one another, did not only receive the ſame truth, but with ſuch reſolution adventure their ſouls theron, as might fully witneſſe, they had another proſpect of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and to be in ſome other manner ravished with the <hi>glory</hi> &amp; <hi>beuty</hi> of the ſame, then is now in theſe times. VI. That ſuch high <hi>ſpring ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi>
                           <pb n="87" facs="tcp:205486:46"/>of the <hi>power,</hi> and <hi>efficacy</hi> of the Goſpel, might be evident to all, after ſo ſad a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint had been for ſo many ages before, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> darkneſſe; for whatever was then as a <hi>private ſeall,</hi> on the ſpirit of Chriſtians whilſt the witneſſes did <hi>propheſy in ſack-cloth,</hi> yet was there no ſuch evidence and <hi>demonſtration of the H. Ghoſt,</hi> or a <hi>publick confirmatory ſeal</hi> to the truth, as was after the <hi>Reformation.</hi> VII. Yea was it not the moſt ſober, ſerious, and inquiſitive part of men, upon a ſure tryal of the grounds of their faith, who did moſt firmly imbrace the ſame; and how many of theſe alſo were of the greateſt parts and abilities, whom none could judge to adventure ſo far herein, without the higheſt aſſurances, that this was their undoubted intereſt and upmaking. VIII. We have ſeen not only theſe of mean and low eſtate, but ſuch of the <hi>higheſt</hi> place and <hi>quality,</hi> moſt chearfully adventuring whatever intereſt could be deareſt to them, in the earth for the truths ſake; yea was ever found, how ſuch as were moſt acquaint, with the reformed religion in its power, and living up in their practiſe, to what they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt thereof, were theſe who with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt aſſurance, have moſt reſoluty ſtill adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thereto. IX. We have ſeen alſo, its moſt remarkable ſpreading in the world,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:205486:47"/>when there could be no poſſible pretence of a <hi>lucrative intereſt,</hi> or external motives for the ſame. X. We have ſeen ſomething not only extraordinare, but even <hi>miraculous</hi> in the <hi>joy,</hi> and <hi>reſolution</hi> of innumberable <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi> ſince the <hi>Reformation</hi> who did bear out with a more then human ſtrenth, againſt a cruelty ſo viſibly <hi>inhuman,</hi> and ſavage; yea which did in ſome degrees exceed that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the <hi>Heathens,</hi> in the <hi>Primitive times,</hi> as being againſt a greater light then theirs. II. And have we not ſeen of what ſpirit, ſuch ſtill have been ſince the <hi>Reformation,</hi> who were the moſt notour inſtruments in the Churches perſecution, and how viſibly ſuch did act herein, under ſo impetuous an incitment of the <hi>Devil,</hi> that as <hi>Tertullien,</hi> in his <hi>Apollogy</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>Nero,</hi> the truth might boaſt in having ſuch adverſaries. XII. It is ſure we have ſeen, how no human power, could yet ever undoe this bleſſed intereſt of the <hi>Reformed religion,</hi> tho no way, or chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of weapons, hath been left untryed; but we have thus ſeen, whither ſo ſtrong, and unite a confederacy, as the <hi>Catholick league</hi> in <hi>France</hi> did at laſt reſolve, and, not only in the ruine of the greateſt acters and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers therein, but to a further eſtablishing of the <hi>Reformed Church</hi> there, as though ſuch had intentionally acted for the ſame; when
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:205486:47"/>if <hi>ſecond cauſes</hi> had brought forth their ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare effects, it might have been judged im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to fail. XIII. We have ſeen that iſſue of the whole councels, expenſe and cruelty of <hi>Philip the II. of Spain,</hi> to bear down the truth of the Goſpel in the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> which was to the furtheſt ſetling of this <hi>illuſtrious ſtate</hi> and the <hi>Church of Christ</hi> there; yea how their conſpicuous riſe and flowrishing even in the externals, and their reſolute adherence to the truth of Chriſt did moſt viſibly keep together. XIV. We know that <hi>deludge of blood,</hi> which ſo quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly followed the <hi>French maſſacre;</hi> and the moſt diſmal time which ever that <hi>nation</hi> know, did then viſibly contemporate, with ſuch a time of their greateſt rage and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution againſt the truth, and that event of the <hi>third vial</hi> moſt clearly fulfilled herein, <hi>Revel.</hi> 16: 5, 6. <hi>Thou art righteous, o Lord, which art, and was, and shall be, becauſe thou hast judged t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>us, for they have shed the blood of thy ſaints and prophets, and thou haſt given them blood to drink in great meaſure.</hi> XV. Yea have we not ſeen how <hi>four Kings of France</hi> ſucceſſively were in leſſe then 30. years, taken away, in the ſame continued purſuit, how to deſtroy the Church there, in whom that whole race of the <hi>Valois</hi> was thus extinct; yea in the manner of their
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:205486:48"/>death, were moſt remarkable monuments of divine judgement, as the moſt famous writers of that time does atteſt. XVI. We have ſeen what marvelous effects did follow theſe bloody years of <hi>Queen Mary's reign</hi> in England, to promot and commend the Proteſtant doctrine to mens conſciences there, with ſo great a triumph it had in the ſufferings of ſuch choiſe and excellent wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes for Chriſt, as hath brought in more rent to the praiſe and glory of their bleſſed head, then may to the furtheſt compenſe all that blood of the Saints there, though high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>precious in the eyes of the Lord.</hi> XVII. We have ſeen likewayes the blood and cruelty, of late againſt the Proteſtants <hi>in Bohemia,</hi> in a short time moſt obſervably returned on the authors thereof, and how the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate finger of God might be ſeen in cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling forth the <hi>Swedes</hi> to avenge the ſame, and in that deſolating ſtrock which followed on <hi>Germany.</hi> XVIII. We have ſeen in theſe late times the iſſue of that horrid <hi>maſſacre</hi> on the <hi>Proteſtants in Ireland,</hi> to the utter ruine in a very few years after, of that barbarous party, who had thus acted herein. XIX. We have ſeen what wonderful providences did attend the actings of that poor handful of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in the <hi>Valleys of Piemont</hi> ſince the <hi>Reformation,</hi> upon the account of that
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:205486:48"/>bloody <hi>maſſacre</hi> which was ſet on foot there againſt them, which was ſo aſtonishing as all might ſee an extraordinare appearence of the Lord herein, as is clearly atteſted by the moſt faithful Hiſtories of that time. XX. And can it be forgot unto this day, how viſibly a divine hand did appear in brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that great <hi>Spanish Armado,</hi> in the year 1588. which had been for ſome years in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving againſt <hi>England.</hi> XXI. As it was aſtonishing, and ſpecially demonſtrative of the immediate power and preſence of God, it should be matter of wonder and praiſe alſo for after ages, that ſolemne time of the <hi>Reformation</hi> of the <hi>Church in Scotland,</hi> for planting the <hi>reformed Religion</hi> there; with that zeal and onneſſe of ſpirit, as did then appear in all ranks to imbrace and adhere to the profeſſion thereof, amidſt the greateſt threatnings of their adverſaries; ſo as a <hi>few years</hi> did bring forth that, which would have ſeemed ſtrang for an <hi>age</hi> to accomplish; yea that we find betwixt the laſt <hi>Martyr</hi> for the truth there, who was <hi>burnt</hi> at <hi>St. Andrews</hi> 1558. and the eſtablishment of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and full abolishment of <hi>Popery,</hi> with the full concurrence of <hi>civil authority</hi> herein, in <hi>July</hi> 1560. was but little above two years; to shew what great things the Lord can doe, above all human councel or
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:205486:49"/>confidence. XXII. Its ſure we have ſeen in what remarkable degrees theſe <hi>laſt vials</hi> of the holy judgment of God, hath taken place on the Kingdome of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and how conſpicuous the <hi>event</hi> hath been of that <hi>prophecy,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſal.</hi> 2: 8. in theſe great ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and conſumption thereof by the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of the Goſpel, as an aſſured pledge of the full accomplishment of what remains herein. XXIII. And as every ſtep of the Churches riſe, hath been ſtill advanced in a continued conflict betwixt the <hi>truth and Antichriſt,</hi> ſo have we ſtill ſeen, when the aſſault and oppoſition hath been greateſt, its moſt remarkable tendancy to a greater vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory; which were it rightly conſidered upon clear and ſolid grounds from the Scripture, the moſt formidable appearences of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble from this adverſary should with more comfort then fear this day be looked on; ſo that whatever be the neareſt and moſt imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate events, yet is it ſure, as <hi>the Lord is true,</hi> whoſe word is paſſed hereon, that whoſoever gives their power and ſtrength to ſupport that intereſt of <hi>Antichrist</hi> shall loſe the day and find their cauſe deſperate, for the party with whom they contend here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is the Son of God, againſt whom no hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man power shall ever be able to ſtand. Theſe are but a <hi>few,</hi> which are here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:205486:49"/>of the great <hi>acts of our God,</hi> in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of his Truth, to be ſtill as preſent in our ſight, in a time when the ſpirits of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are ready to ſtagger and faint; and here mentioned, to lay no ſtreſſe or weight of the <hi>authority</hi> of the truth and doctrine of our profeſſion thereon, but on the alone <hi>reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Scripture;</hi> but that they are ſuch an undenyable ſeal for confirming our faith, and of ſo known, <hi>publick</hi> and <hi>famous evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> as should be no leſſe conſidered and taken to heart now, then in the time when the Lord thus appeared herein.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="section">
                        <head>SECTION III.</head>
                        <p>QU. WHat <hi>preſent judgment</hi> are we called to have of this <hi>time,</hi> upon clear and aſſured grounds from the <hi>Scripture;</hi> that we may know under what <hi>aſpect</hi> therof, the preſent <hi>ſtate of Religion</hi> and of the <hi>refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches</hi> is under, when ſo great a <hi>cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> is this day, as would ſeem to be in the very <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> of its conflict, whither as to life or death?</p>
                        <p>ANSW. It is no preſent appearences of the time muſt direct our faith, nor should we either ſtreath our fears or expectations of things and <hi>events,</hi> beyond what the God of truth doth warrand in his word, but its
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:205486:50"/>clear, if we credite the ſame, and admitt the <hi>divinity of the New Teſtament,</hi> there is no juſt cauſe of heſitation or darkneſſe as to what the Lord is bringing forth for his Church now in theſe latter dayes; nor can there be any pretence, to ſeek an other <hi>light,</hi> either from the <hi>ſtars</hi> above, or the <hi>diviners</hi> of this time, when ſo woful a trade hath got up in the world, that men will thus goe <hi>to the God of Ekron,</hi> as though there were not <hi>a God in Iſrael,</hi> or ſuch a thing, as his <hi>written Oracles</hi> to inquire at, when its ſure theſe ly open, and with a clear and diſtinct ſound ſpeaks to all who have a ſerious and unprejudged ſpirit. I. That the <hi>Church</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> hath now paſſed and gone through that moſt diſmal and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued <hi>tryal</hi> herein, which was to goe over her head under <hi>Antichriſts reigne</hi> and <hi>hight;</hi> and whatever appearence he now hath in great wrath, yet is it ſure and evident that the <hi>winter is paſt</hi> and the <hi>Churches ſpring</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun; and a few ſteps further of that judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is now haſtning on, will at lenth end the quarrel; ſo that by a near converſe with the word, we may clearly ſee from what <hi>point</hi> the <hi>Churches courſe</hi> and motion this day lyes, and how exactly it keeps, in the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thereof, by that clear <hi>conduct</hi> of the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of truth,</hi> where a full <hi>map</hi> of her whole
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:205486:50"/>
                           <hi>courſe</hi> and paſſage through time is clearly shewed. II. That we may now with ſome clear evidence judge, and have our faith perſwaded hereof, that the <hi>Churches</hi> intereſt is upon the <hi>riſing hand,</hi> and on a preſent ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, though nothing would ſeem more contradictory then all viſible grounds now are; ſince this cannot ſail, <hi>John.</hi> 3:30. that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in his kingdom in the earth <hi>muſt increaſe;</hi> yea that the Scripture ſo clearly points forth <hi>Antichriſts</hi> ruine and progreſſe of his fall and douncaſting, with reſemblan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to that great judgment on <hi>Pharaoh</hi> as an evident <hi>type</hi> hereof; in the ſame judicial ſtrocks of <hi>induration,</hi> on both, and <hi>gradual</hi> progreſſe herein by one <hi>plague</hi> after another, until the laſt and greateſt aſſault, as was then at the <hi>Red-ſea,</hi> hath the ſame effect for a more glorious appearence of God, in the greateſt ſtep of judgment, and victory over this adverſary, when not only the <hi>ſong of Moſes</hi> but of the <hi>Lamb</hi> alſo shall be then <hi>ſung, Rev.</hi> 15: 3. as importing ſomething more glorious and a greater brightneſſe to be put on this <hi>illuſtrious act of divine judgment,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to theſe laſt times, when a more <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate appearence of the Lord</hi> will be ſeen, then in any ſormer deliveries of his Church. III. It is no conjectural thing, but what by a clear Scripture conduct we may ſee, that this
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:205486:51"/>time of the <hi>Church</hi> now under ſo notable a <hi>Criſis</hi> in her caſe, is evidently falling under that <hi>remarkable aſſault and conflict,</hi> with that adverſary, before the accomplishing of that <hi>vial</hi> on <hi>his ſeat and throne,</hi> as we may ſee <hi>Revel.</hi> 17:13, 14. that when ſo conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous a ſtep of the <hi>Churches victory</hi> is near; the oppoſition thereto alſo will be in ſome higher degree proportionable to the ſame, when the great men of the earth, and ſuch <hi>who shall receive power as Kings, one hower with the beaſt,</hi> shall have one mind and give <hi>their power and ſtrength thereto,</hi> and <hi>shall make war with the Lamb, but the Lamb shall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them, for he is King of Kings and Lord of Lords,</hi> &amp;c. Nor is it found through the <hi>Scripture</hi> where any <hi>great thing,</hi> the Lord hath done for his Church, but ſome unu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> and <hi>ſore wreſtlings</hi> hath ſtill gone before, and should be no matter of ſtaggering to our faith, whatever be of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent fears, to ſee ſo diſmal a <hi>time of tryal</hi> as now is, and amazing hight of trouble beyond what former times have known, when one of the <hi>greateſt events</hi> of providence in behalf of the Church, ſince the revealing of <hi>Christ</hi> to the world, until his <hi>ſecond coming,</hi> is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly near in the fall and overthrow of the <hi>man of ſin.</hi> IV. We have clear ground alſo to judge, that ſo great an <hi>eclipſe</hi> as ſeems
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:205486:51"/>allmoſt univerſally over the ſtate of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed <hi>Churches,</hi> is no goeing <hi>down of the ſun</hi> theron, whatever did befall the moſt famous <hi>eaſtern Churches</hi> to an utter diſſipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof; if theſe different <hi>periodes</hi> of time be juſtly conſidered, how their <hi>ſun-ſet</hi> did then fall in with the <hi>entry</hi> of that <hi>great Apoſtacy</hi> of the Chriſtian Church and with that long and diſmall night of <hi>Antichriſts reign;</hi> whilſt now this hower of tryal on the Churches, doth meet in that bleſſed <hi>period of Antichriſts begun fall,</hi> and of a growing light of the Goſpel, and when the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſo clearly warrands our faith herein, that the worke of providence is to <hi>plant,</hi> and not <hi>cutt of,</hi> but to bring forward that intereſt of the <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> in the founding of which the <hi>Mediator</hi> hath ſo eminently appeared in the glory of his power in theſe <hi>last times.</hi> V. It is ſure me now live in the evening, and extremity of time, when the motions of providence may be expected to be more quick and ſpeady, as being ſo near the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and to the laſt <hi>Epocha,</hi> and period of all <hi>prophetick Chronology;</hi> wherein the glory of God in his truth and faithfulneſſe shall moſt eminently shine forth, and theſe Scripture truths which were formerly dark &amp; abſtruſe, with that evidence shine forth in the event, as shall cauſe men to wonder at their former
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:205486:52"/>thoughts and ſtumblings thereat. And here I muſt ſay, that there is ſuch a ſight now in the earth, as the <hi>Romish Church,</hi> in its complex frame and ſtate, in ſo different a mould caſt from any power or juriſdiction elſe, and ſuch a compound of a <hi>civil, and Spiritual Monarchy</hi> in one and the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, is ſo ſolemn and undenyable a <hi>ſeal</hi> to the <hi>Chriſtian faith,</hi> and <hi>divinity of the New Teſtament;</hi> that its ſtrang why this is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proven more, againſt the <hi>Atheiſm</hi> of this ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, that ſuch a viſible event of the Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re is now in being, which was ſo clearly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> 1500. years ago, with its proper circumſtances, as to the manner of that <hi>Antichriſtian ſtate,</hi> with its <hi>riſe, grouth,</hi> &amp; <hi>duration,</hi> as is to admiration ſtil evident to the world, when not the leaſt shaddow or appearence of ſo ſtrang future emergencies was to be ſeen or could have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in mens thoughts; to shew it only could be revealed to the Church by him, to whom all his works are known from the beginning. This I have looked on, as ſuch a <hi>confirmation</hi> to the truth of Chriſtianity, that no mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles in the firſt times of the Church could have more evidence for the ſame; yea if ſuch a party were not in being, both what it now is and in former ages hath been, it might in another manner ſtagger the faith of the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:205486:52"/>Saints, to a queſtioning the truth of the Scripture, then its moſt formidable appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence this day can doe. VI. I shall but add here, that we know and are ſure the Lord hath reſerved his greateſt works to theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dayes, wherein his judgments shall be manifeſt; and that one of the moſt eminent manifeſtations of his glory before the cloſe of time shal be conſpicuous in the <hi>fall of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt,</hi> on whoſe ruines that <hi>glorious hous</hi> which Chriſt is yet to have for himſelf both of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> shall be prepared and built up; and though this great <hi>eclipſe</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian darkneſſe,</hi> should yet more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, even over the viſible profeſſion of the truth in the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Britain,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> there is no cauſe to be ſtaggered in the faith of <hi>Romes fatal period,</hi> being near, but to look hereon according to the Scripture as the <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimus Conatus</hi> of that wounded adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, which will be found in the iſſue to have the moſt immediate connexion with his greateſt downfall, and the <hi>reviving glory</hi> of the <hi>Church; for ſtrong is the Lord God who judgeth her.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="section">
                        <head>SECTION IV.</head>
                        <p>QU. WHat is <hi>ſpecially called for,</hi> in this day, of ſuch as are accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:205486:53"/>for ſo great a talent of light, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations to our faith?</p>
                        <p>ANSW. If this were ſuitably taken to heart, we could not but reckon our ſelves under the greateſt excitment and <hi>call,</hi> to ſuch an improvment hereof.</p>
                        <p n="1">I. That we account it not enough to have a <hi>faith,</hi> for quieting our own ſpirits, but how to <hi>confirme</hi> others, by <hi>putting to our ſeal that God is true,</hi> in the great aſſurances of his word, and to <hi>ſanctify him before the world,</hi> which is ſo important a duty, as the Lord was wroth even with a <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> for one short-coming, when he called for the ſame, <hi>Numb.</hi> 20:12. and its ſure in no time was ſuch a ſpecial truſt more repoſed the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reon, then in this age, both as a publick debt on the Church, &amp; perſonal on each Chriſtian, how to witneſſe for the Lord, upon that great intereſt of his faithfulneſſe and for tranſmitting the ſame, to the ages to come, by a confirmatory ſeal, and teſtimony ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</p>
                        <p n="2">II. To reckon our ſelves alſo under ſome more then ordinare <hi>call</hi> this day, each in their preſent capacity and ſtation, how to appear for the <hi>credite</hi> of the truth, and <hi>ſtemm</hi> ſo viſible and impetuous a <hi>tyde,</hi> as is now run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>diſtruct,</hi> and of a diſcreditable <hi>faint;</hi> for it may be ſaid, never was the <hi>Church</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:205486:53"/>the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> ſo remarkably ſiſted under ſuch a trial, as that wherein the Lord did <hi>prove</hi> the <hi>Church of Iſrael, Numb.</hi> 14. or had a more evident reſemblance therto, in the ſame circumſtances as in this day, if they were ſeriouſly pondered; as I how in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me manner, ſuch a falſe &amp; <hi>evil report</hi> is too viſibly raiſed upon the bleſt ways of the Lord, to diſcourage and faint the ſpirits of his people, as was then by the <hi>ſpyes,</hi> that there were inſuperable difficulties in the way of the promiſe, by reaſon of the <hi>Anakims,</hi> and of their <hi>walled cities,</hi> and did thus op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the credite of <hi>ſenſe,</hi> to all theſe <hi>aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which God had given to their faith.</hi> II. That this highly dishonourable faint and <hi>diſtruſt</hi> did ſo ſeaſe on that people, as was like to reſolve in a viſible revolt, and to <hi>cry for</hi> a <hi>lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> to <hi>goe back to Egypt</hi> again; which amongſt too many in this time may be juſtly feared. III. That this was after ſuch extraordinare <hi>confirmations</hi> which the Lord had given to the faith of his <hi>Church</hi> then, who had by his own immediate and outſtretched hand ſo latly brought them out of the <hi>houſe of bonda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge,</hi> and from <hi>the iron furnace in Egypt,</hi> as ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred their misbeliefe to be a guilt under ſuch aggravations, as the holy God did in that manner plead, <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. <hi>Theſe ten times have they tempted me, who have ſeen my glory, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:205486:54"/>my miracles, which I did in the wilderneſſe,</hi> &amp;c. IV. But herein we hope, and are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently ſure of a bleſſed <hi>diſparity</hi> in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance, as to the <hi>numberouſneſſe</hi> of ſuch, who shall be found of the <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> to act ſomething of that part, which theſe <hi>heroick witneſſes</hi> a <hi>Caleb</hi> &amp; <hi>Joshua</hi> did &amp; were then put to ſtand alone therein, who through grat shall yet appear with ſome meaſure of that ſpirit, and withſtand ſo high a tyde of fears, diſcouragment and misbeliefe as is this day, and thus to plead againſt the ſame as theſe did, <hi>Num.</hi> 14:9. if the Lord delight in us, then let us not rebel againſt him, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fear the greateſt difficulties can be in the way &amp;c. V. And is not the ſame precedent of providence, of ſo ſingular a reſpect as the Lord did then teſtify to his <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joshua</hi> (who were of <hi>another ſpirit</hi> in <hi>following him fully,</hi> in that day) a continued aſſurance, for all who shall be helped to any honourable appearence of this kind, by making them ſee, and inherit the truth of his promiſe; yea that ſuch a reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due who outlives this great and amazing ſtorme shal have ſomething of that teſtimony to bear alſo which <hi>Caleb</hi> gave <hi>Josh.</hi> 14:8, 10. <hi>My brethren which went up with me made the heart of the people faint, but I fully followed the Lord my God, and now behold the Lord hath keeped me alive,</hi> &amp;c. o bleſſed they whoſe
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:205486:54"/>ſouls are raiſed with that holy zeal for the truth to ſtand up in this great breach, by a reſolute profeſſion of their faith, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the faithfulneſſe of God, as ſuch great and extraordinar confirmations, given thertho, now calls for.</p>
                        <p n="3">III. It is one of the ſpecial duties of this day we ſtand alſo accomptable for, how to ſtemm this high and growing <hi>tyde of preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, and reproach</hi> againſt the <hi>Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> which in ſome unuſual way is now aloft; and by manifeſtation of the truth to gain ſome more awfull regard herof on mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that they may ſee ſomthing of the <hi>glory of our profeſſion,</hi> and in what maner it maintains its conqueſt as no way elſe can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly claim; I. Which reckons none elſe to be the true and genuine profeſſours hereof, who imbrace not the ſame upon <hi>evidence,</hi> and with reſpect to its <hi>intrinſick excellency</hi> and worth; nor does judge the intereſt of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to goe by <hi>number, and poll,</hi> where this is wanting; but to purſue that end to have men ingadged <hi>firſt to be Chriſtians,</hi> that they may be true and ſincere <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> and therfor can admitt no ſuch methods of any baſe compliance with the humour and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of men, which its principles will not bear. II. Which in its courſe is ever <hi>regulare</hi> and certain, according to that rule
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:205486:55"/>of an <hi>uncheangable and eternal truth,</hi> without dependance on the will of man herein, or any mutable revolutions of the time. III. Which doth with the greateſt luſtre shine forth in the brighteſt <hi>light,</hi> and is maintained by the <hi>cleareſt knowledge;</hi> yea by the furtheſt plaineſſe, and openneſſe of heart, towards all, commends it ſelf; ſo that the world may ſee, it eſpouſeth not mens <hi>affection,</hi> before it gain on their <hi>conſcience;</hi> and to have their judgment fixed on a judicious tryal, before their reſolution; nor accounts the truth of religion, can ever ſubſiſt by an <hi>external shew</hi> and profeſſion, without is known <hi>evidence</hi> and the <hi>efficacy</hi> therof on mens ſoul. IV. Which ſincerly follows the <hi>Catholick intereſt of Chriſtianitie</hi> and publick good of mankind, in promotting the great <hi>ends of the Goſpel,</hi> ſo as the world may ſee its higheſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent is to exalt all <hi>divine inſtitutions,</hi> and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the <hi>ſimplicity,</hi> and ſpirituality of <hi>Goſpel adminiſtrations,</hi> (according to the revealed <hi>rule</hi>) amonghſt men, as that which doth moſt nearly conceirn the <hi>vitals of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> and ane <hi>inward life</hi> of communion with God. V. Which pleads an impartial tryal of al its adverſaries, whither the principles of our <hi>profeſſion</hi> or of <hi>Popery,</hi> gives the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſecurity to <hi>Civil Government,</hi> &amp; founds the ſtrongeſt obligations to <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:205486:55"/>to all <hi>Civil,</hi> and <hi>Moral duties,</hi> by which the awe and venerable eſteem of religion is kept up in a nation. It is high time that men should ceaſe to be implicit upon this greateſt intereſt they have within time, which is the truth of their profeſſion in the matter of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, when a deceit or miſtake here is of an eternal conceirn: upon which account without reſpect to intereſt, party, or edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, I have this day ſought to know the truth, and what adverſaries could poſſibly pretend, to <hi>reproach,</hi> or prejudge any at the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> which can only amount, to charge mens corruption and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences in their practiſe, upon the <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>principles</hi> of their <hi>profeſſion,</hi> that can never give the leaſt <hi>latitude,</hi> or connivance therto, but is <hi>clear as the ſun;</hi> when on the other hand I could know no other way, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace ſuch a profeſſion, as <hi>Popery,</hi> but by turning <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> in the <hi>firſt place,</hi> and quite both <hi>religion</hi> and <hi>reaſon</hi> at once: but may ſay, in a reſolute adherence to the doctrine of the <hi>Reformed Church,</hi> I fear not to adventure my ſoul, and enter into an eternal ſtate.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:205486:56"/>
                  <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>CHAPTER I. <hi>The primitive confirmation, held forth and cleared in ſeven Poſitions.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <item>POSIT. I. That ſad aſpect, which the implicit and traditional profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this day hath upon the preſent ſtate of religion. Pag. 1</item>
                     <item>POSIT. II. The greatneſſe of that ſervice for the Church to have a clear founding of the faith of aſſent, upon known and ſolid grounds herein, more univerſally promott. Pag. 3</item>
                     <item>POSIT. III. The true primitive confirmation as it was in the times of the Apoſtles, hold forth and cleared from the Scripture. Pag. 6</item>
                     <item>POSIT. IV. The continued neceſſity therof, no leſſe convincing now, for the Churches uſe, then in theſe Primitive times. Pag. 9</item>
                     <item>POSIT. V. That ſuch a confirmatory worke reſpects not only the more knowing and inquiſitive part of men, but the meaneſt within the Church. Pag. 11</item>
                     <item>POSIT. VI. VVhat is ſpecially called for in the practicall uſe of this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive confirmation, held forth in ſome ſerious propoſals for this end. Pag. 14</item>
                     <item>POSIT. VII. VVhat ſpecial excitment we are under, for promotting the ſame in ſo remarkable a period of time as this, and from that hope of a greater reviving yet of ſuch a Catholick ſpirit, to advance the higheſt ends of religion amonghſt men. Pag. 19</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>CHAPTER II. <hi>For giving ſome clear view, of theſe primary evidences and demonſtrations of our faith, that the meaneſt Chriſtian should know, and vvith the leaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe of time may improve for their dayly uſe, on theſe greateſt principles.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <item>
                        <label>SECTION I.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>I. Of the glorious being of God, which is the firſt foundation of all religion. Pag. 22</item>
                           <item>II. Of the original of the world, and its not being eternal. Pag. 25</item>
                           <item>III. Of a ſupreme providence in the conſervation and goverment of the world. Pag. 26</item>
                           <item>IV. Of that ſpecial providence, which in its continued adminiſtration about human affaires, doth unchangably difference betwixt the righteus and the wicked. Pag. 29</item>
                           <item>V. How ſuch a wonderful record as that of an immediat revelation of God unto men, is ſo demonſtrably extant in the world. Pag. 31</item>
                           <item>VI. Of theſe ſpecial evidences of the Scriptures divinity, which men muſt needs ſee to be infallible. Pag. 33</item>
                           <item>VII. Of the ſecure convoyance of the Scripture through all the changes of times paſt. Pag. 35</item>
                           <pb facs="tcp:205486:56"/>
                           <item>VIII. Of the fall of man and entry of ſin into the world, as it is fully demonſtrable to reaſon, as well as by the certainty of faith. Pag. 37</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>SECTION II.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>I. Holding fort theſe great aſſiſtances to the Chriſtian faith, and of the Meſſias being ſurely promiſed to the Church before his coming. Pag. 38</item>
                           <item>II. Of the truth and accomplishment of this great promiſe of the Meſſias, and how it is now as ſure in the event as its clear he was promiſed. Pag. 39</item>
                           <item>III. Of that ſpecial advantage for confirmation of our faith herein, that for 4000. years the promiſed coming of the Meſſias was deferred. Pag. 41, 42</item>
                           <item>IV. Of the nature and internal excellency of Chriſtianity, to bear fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt evidence to the truth therof. Pag. 43</item>
                           <item>V. That this is the ſame Goſpel we now receive and injoy, which from the firſt promulgation therof hath had ſo great effects on the world. Pag. 45</item>
                           <item>VI. That the ſufferings of the ſaints in times paſt was ſo demonſtrably above the aſſiſtance of nature. Pag. 46</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>SECTION III.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>I. For holding forth on what grounds the faith of a deity muſt determine men to be Chriſtians. Pag. 48</item>
                           <item>II. What confirmations the Chriſtian Religion hath from that viſible ſtate of the Jews. Pag. 49</item>
                           <item>III. That way and manner of its prevailing on the world, as no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion elſe could ever pretend to. Pag. 51</item>
                           <item>IV. The nature of that great evidence, which Chriſt hath himſelf given to the world of his divine miſſion in the love and unity of his people, Joh. 17: 21. Pag. 53</item>
                           <item>V. How the ſtrenth of ſuch a demonſtration ſtands ſtill clear and evident in theſe dividing times of the Church. Pag. 54</item>
                           <item>VI. What in theſe laſt times is under our hand to compenſe ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation by miracles, which was in the firſt times of the Goſpel. Pag. 56</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>SECTION IV.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>I. For holding forth with the furtheſt rational certainty, and evidence the truth and doctrine of Chriſt, to be a ſoul-quicking and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental religion. Pag. 58</item>
                           <item>II. The truth alſo of converſion of men from a ſtate of nature to a new ſtate of grace. Pag. 60</item>
                           <item>III. Of ſo great an experiment of religion as Communion betwixt God and men here in the earth. Pag. 62</item>
                           <item>IV. Of ſo great a demonſtration of religion in the power and workings of the Conſcience. Pag. 64</item>
                           <item>V. Of that ſpecial confirmation to our faith, which doth reſult from ſuch a demonſtration of this power of the Conſcience over men. Pag. 65</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:205486:57"/>
                     <item>
                        <label>SECTION V.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>I. For holding forth the truth of a Kingdom of darkneſſe in the world, in oppoſition to the Kingdom of Chriſt. Pag. 66, 67</item>
                           <item>II. What confirmation to our faith, the certainty hereof, and of theſe powers of darkneſſe, doth clearly afford. Pag. 68</item>
                           <item>III. That great truth of the immortality of the ſoul, with the cleareſt evidence to reaſon, as well as by the certainty of faith. Pag. 69, 70</item>
                           <item>IV. How confirming a ſeal to the Scripture that great change which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth on all men by death is, and how its no natural accident. Pag. 72</item>
                           <item>V. Some ſpecial aſſiſtances to the Chriſtians faith of an eternal glory in heaven, and to ſerve an unavoidable conviction thus on the greateſt Atheiſts. Pag. 74</item>
                           <item>VI. Some thing of a viſible Hell, in ſome near approach hereof even to mens ſenſes, held forth to awake and convince the world of ſuch a ſtate of horrour and torment in another world. Pag. 77</item>
                           <item>VII. Some aſſiſtances to our faith of that great truth of the Reſurrection of the body. Pag. 79</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>CHAPTER III. <hi>The Confirming vvorke of religion further improven vvith reſpect to this diſmal and amazing time vve are novv fallen in.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <item>
                        <label>SECTION I.</label> To hold forth what may be both for light and confirmation upon this great diſtreſſe the Churches of Chriſt are now under. Pag. 81, 82</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>SECTION II.</label> How great a talent we ſtand accountable for in this day of ſuch imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate and extraordinare appearences of the Lord for confirming the ſame publick cauſe of the Reformed Church ſince the Reformation, which we are now called to adhere to. Pag. 84</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>SECTION III.</label> What manner of time is the preſent lot of the Church now fallen in, and what judgment we ought to have hereof from the Scripture, for our furtheſt confirming in ſuch a day. Pag. 93</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>SECTION IV.</label> Some ſpecial ſervice that we are now called to, and accountable for, in behalf of the truth, and for ſanctifying the Lord in the eyes of others, who are under ſo great a talent of light and confirmation in the ſame. Pag. 99</item>
                  </list>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:205486:57"/>
                  <head>AN IDEA, <hi>Of the confirm'd ſtate of a Chriſtian in diſmall and shaking times.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ho the ſame meaſure of <hi>Chriſtians eſtablishment</hi> in the truth be not alike to all, but muſt have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the different <hi>trialls, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,</hi> &amp; <hi>improvements</hi> of ſuch for this end; yet may it be cauſe of aſtoniſhment, how rare any ſtudy of this kinde is now to be ſound, when its not only one of the higheſt concerns of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> but in a more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary way called for, as the <hi>work of this day;</hi> yea, that this is a part of religion, which ſeemes leſt improven of any, for the <hi>more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſtate of profeſſours within the Church;</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſome conviction hereof, was this eſſay de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, where with humble confidence (I may ſay) the <hi>truth</hi> hath been ſought with that ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous enquiry into the <hi>nature of theſe things</hi> held forth, as I judged needfull for ſuch, who have ſo great ane intereſt &amp; venture not only through <hi>time,</hi> but for all <hi>eternity,</hi> to ſupport upon the alone certainty hereof, &amp; er theſe <hi>dayes of triall,</hi> which we now ſee, paſſe over this <hi>genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> it may be found this was not unſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or without cauſe directed to ſuch a time,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:205486:58"/>if the Lord graciouſly bleſſe the ſame; nor will it (I hope) be found incongruous &amp; without uſe to preſent yet further, in ſuch a method, &amp; way of example, ſome cleare proſpect of a <hi>confirmed ſtate in religion,</hi> &amp; what theſe ought to be, who with light &amp; aſſurance of minde would <hi>follow the Lord fully,</hi> in ſuch a day, as is here offered in a 7 <hi>fold Character,</hi> under which a <hi>truly confirmed Chriſtian in the truth of his profeſsion</hi> may be <hi>ſtated.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>CHARACTER. I. That he is one <hi>who hath ane other ſence,</hi> &amp; <hi>impreſſion of this great ſtudy for attaining to a confirmed ſtate in religion,</hi> &amp; is on <hi>higher grounds preſſed to follow the ſame,</hi> then <hi>what moſt of the viſible Church ſeemes to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend;</hi> &amp; ſhould be thus conſidred.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. As one to whom the <hi>glory of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an profeſſion</hi> is in the higheſt degree deare, &amp; to have the world ſee, that ſuch as embrace the ſame &amp; does moſt fully adventure on the teſtimony of God in his word, are theſe alſo who walks on the higheſt principles of true, &amp; <hi>enlightned reaſon;</hi> yea, who takes deeply to heart that obligation which is on all, who deſires to advance the <hi>repute,</hi> &amp; <hi>honor of the truth,</hi> to be in ſuch <hi>tearmes</hi> therewith upon its <hi>own evidence,</hi> as they may know how to ſerve a rationall conviction both on <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> &amp; <hi>inſidels,</hi> if called thereunto.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Who ſees alſo, how ſuch is the ſtate of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:205486:58"/>
                     <hi>fallen man,</hi> as ſtands in need of all the <hi>contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions</hi> that can be, not only to ſtrengthen the <hi>Chriſtians faith,</hi> and beare out againſt the ſtrong aſſaults of <hi>infidelity,</hi> but to gain alſo more cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and <hi>veneration</hi> to the truth with theſe who are not eaſily delt with, but by ſuch <hi>meanes,</hi> as beares ſome <hi>congruity to their naturall light, and reaſon;</hi> for which end the Lord hath af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorded theſe miniſteriall helpes, to render the misbeleefe of the world, or any pretenſe of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation about his truth more fully inexcuſable.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He thus ſees, how the moſt important, and <hi>fundamentall truths</hi> of Chriſtianity, needs the greateſt <hi>confirmation of his faith,</hi> &amp; for theſe who enter in ſo high &amp; diſcriminating a profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from the reſidue of the world, to know in what manner they embrace the ſame: yea that the <hi>naturall order of things</hi> does abſolutly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire to have the <hi>foundation</hi> ſure laid, on which ſo great a <hi>ſuperſtructure</hi> muſt reſt, ſo as he judgeth it a <hi>work by its ſelfe,</hi> and to need ſome peculiar retiring his ſoul in the moſt ſerious <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe,</hi> and compoſure thereof, to attain <hi>a stedfaſtnes of his own</hi> in the truth, and to know the ſtrong and <hi>firm convoyances</hi> of that greateſt <hi>myſtery</hi> of the goſpell, in ſuch a manner, as needes no <hi>paund of a miracle</hi> to confirm the ſame. But he knowes here that no ſharpneſs of mens <hi>naturall underſtanding</hi> about the truth can ever attain a true <hi>reſt, and ſettlement of minde</hi>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:205486:59"/>therein, without a <hi>humble,</hi> and <hi>ſerious ſpirit</hi> ſtooping doune before the wiſedome of God, and to enter as <hi>little Children</hi> into his Schoole; yea that by humble <hi>practice,</hi> and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the goſpell there is ane undoubted com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming up to the greateſt aſſurance and <hi>cleareſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of the ſame, as Joh.</hi> 7: 17.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. He knowes that as nothing tends more to ſhake mens ſpirits, and ſtagger them about the truth, then a <hi>light and tranſient view</hi> hereof, ſo does the greateſt <hi>eſtablishment,</hi> follow on the neareſt approach by a <hi>deep and ſerious enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> about the ſame, and thus clearely ſees that if ſuch who look but at <hi>a diſtance</hi> on the way of religion, did but once come that length of triall, as to have their ſpirits <hi>ſeparat,</hi> by a more ſerious reflection thereon, the <hi>firſt view</hi> they ſhould have, could not but be matter of wonder, and amazement, to think what can determine and ſupport in ſo marvellous a way as the life and <hi>practice of Chriſtianity,</hi> which is ſo viſibly above nature, and wherein they muſt do violence to the ſame, where they muſt part with the <hi>multitude,</hi> and oppoſe themſelves to the ſtrongeſt tyde <hi>of exemple,</hi> and muſt <hi>endure alſo in hope,</hi> and <hi>believe for things not ſeen,</hi> which were never the object of humane ſence, to any in this earth, and are oft called to part with the moſt deſireable things of <hi>ſence,</hi> upon the alone credit of their <hi>faith,</hi> yea, where
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:205486:59"/>they muſt enter in that profeſſion, on no other <hi>tearmes,</hi> then to be <hi>martyrs</hi> for the ſame, and <hi>ſeall it with their blood;</hi> ſo that he muſt needs ſee a Chriſtian according to the <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the goſpell,</hi> to be the greateſt <hi>riddle,</hi> and <hi>wonder</hi> of any ſight within time; but when ſuch come more cloſſe and neare upon this <hi>triall,</hi> and have once underſtood the <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse of that ſecurity</hi> which theſe have to adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on, yea what is the glory of their <hi>hope,</hi> and the ſure ſpring of their ſupplyes, for their work and trialls within time, then will this <hi>ſecond wonder</hi> unſpeakably exceed the <hi>firſt;</hi> how its poſſible that ſuch are not of a more <hi>raiſed,</hi> and <hi>enlarged ſpirit,</hi> in the ſervice of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, in that ſhort ſeaſon they have here for it on the earth, and how their <hi>triall</hi> ſhould not be more to <hi>beare the joy of ſo great a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and expectation,</hi> then any preſent griefes and troubles, yea how mens life who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed makes earneſt of the Chriſtian profeſſion, is not in ſome more continued tranſport of <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vishment and wondering,</hi> to know that they are ſurely made for an <hi>eternall ſtate</hi> in another world, and are among theſe on whom the <hi>glorious God</hi> hath choiſed to have the exceeding riches of his grace ſhewed forth in theſe <hi>regions of bleſsedneſs</hi> above for ever.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. He hath another ſight and proſpect of the <hi>Chriſtian Creed,</hi> then moſt who give ane eaſy
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:205486:60"/>aſſent thereunto; and hath his reaſon ſo dazeled with the <hi>revelation of the goſpell</hi> and of the <hi>won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> thereof as hath put him to ſuch ane exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe as that 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 6: 8. How to credit his eyes therewith, the more deep reflexion he hath upon the ſame, <hi>but will God in very deed dwell with men on the earth;</hi> and to judge their caſe, who after ſome fluctuating ſuſpence, are admitt to ſee the truth of Chriſtianity, with that <hi>certainty of its evidence,</hi> as the greatneſs of ſuch a diſcovery does require, may have ſome reſemblance to that tranſport which the <hi>Angells</hi> had at the <hi>firſt being of the creation, where the morning ſtarres ſung together,</hi> and <hi>the Sonnes of God shouted for joy,</hi> to ſee themſelves thus, who were brought out of pure nothing, entered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that ineſtable light of ſeeing God, and of their own bleſſedneſs in him, in ſo high a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree; ſo that he accounts it one of the higheſt attainements of religion, for a <hi>Chriſtian indeed to believe the articles of his own faith,</hi> and have his ſoul thus as fully perſuaded, as of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that ſuch a time aſſuredly was, &amp; now many ages ſince paſt, when the <hi>glorious Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of the Church,</hi> the <hi>ſecond perſon of the God head came doune from heaven</hi> and was revealed in our nature, that on him as <hi>ſurety</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> divine juſtice in the roome of the <hi>Elect</hi> Church, was the whole <hi>guilt,</hi> and <hi>ſin</hi> thereof transferred, and in this marvellous way did the holy God <hi>take
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:205486:60"/>ſatisfaction to himſelfe, by himſelfe;</hi> that thus our nature is <hi>exalted,</hi> by the <hi>incarnation of Chriſt</hi> above the <hi>nature of Angels;</hi> that the time is neare when the meaneſt afflicted Chriſtian, ſhall draw in no other <hi>aire,</hi> then the breathings of the <hi>higher Paradiſe</hi> above, and now hath ane eternity of joy, and bleſſedneſſe before him; that within a very little time he ſhall know this <hi>welcome of</hi> our bleſt Redeemer to his followers here on the earth, <hi>come ye bleſſed of my father inherite the Kingdome,</hi> &amp;c. when he ſhall take off the <hi>croſſe,</hi> and put on the <hi>crown,</hi> when it ſhall be then no more a <hi>matter of faith,</hi> but of <hi>ſence</hi> to be <hi>partakers of that inheritance</hi> with the ſaints in light, and know theſe <hi>proper manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> in that ſtate of glory and peculiar <hi>aſſignement</hi> thereunto which all the Redeemed ſhall then have, and be adjoyned in the ſame claſſe with the <hi>Elect Angels</hi> to be as <hi>pure flames</hi> of <hi>love,</hi> and <hi>joy,</hi> yea know what its to walk in theſe ſtreetes of the <hi>new Jeruſalem</hi> which are as <hi>gold tranſparent as Chriſtall,</hi> and what that mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting will be of his <hi>ſoul perfected,</hi> and in a <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant ſtate</hi> with his <hi>glorifyed body,</hi> raiſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible and never to part any more; and to have his proper ſhare of that bleſſed and <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſolemnity,</hi> that ſhall be celebrated in heaven of the <hi>marriage ſupper of the lamb,</hi> with the whole triumphant Church, and heare that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable account which the <hi>great judge</hi> will then
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:205486:61"/>make of theſe <hi>trials</hi> of his faith, and ſharp con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts which he had gone through within time, with that <hi>ſolemn teſtimony of approbation</hi> which will be given thereof, and ſince its ſure theſe <hi>great things</hi> muſt be a part of the <hi>Chriſtian faith,</hi> can it be ſtrange, that ſuch, as would in that manner converſe therewith (tho they be not yet ſeen) as no leſſe undoubted <hi>realities</hi> then any preſent <hi>objects of ſenſe,</hi> be not eaſily ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed with a low degree of evidence and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of their judgement, but that their joy who are ſure here ſhould be perfected ſo far as this ſtate of mortality can beare, and thus find it ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy to <hi>rejoyce,</hi> and <hi>glory in tribulation,</hi> and to weep now for a ſeaſon, who are to rejoyce for ever, yea to ſay in the words of <hi>Mephibosheth,</hi> let them take it all, &amp; enjoy the ſame, ſince he who is their <hi>life and exceeding joy, lives and reignes,</hi> who is infinitly better to them then all theſe things.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. He accounts the <hi>ſtrengthning of his faith,</hi> to be ſuch a concern, not only as it is his <hi>ſoules venture for all eternity,</hi> but as the <hi>higheſt way of gloryfying God here,</hi> that what ever tends to a more full <hi>confirmation</hi> of the ſame, he rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kons alſo one of the greateſt <hi>additions to his joy and</hi> comfort within time; and that theſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfold <hi>aſſiſtances</hi> with ſuch <hi>reduplication</hi> thereof which the Lord hath himſelfe given for this end, are ſuch as no <hi>fragments</hi> of ſuch a <hi>talent</hi> ſhould
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:205486:61"/>be loſt; &amp; tho he knowes the greateſt <hi>demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations</hi> of our faith can add nothing to the <hi>certainty of divine truth</hi> in it ſelfe; yet are they thus given in regard of the ſtrong <hi>trials</hi> of a Chriſtians life, and of what their <hi>weakneſſe</hi> ſtand in need of for ſupport.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Its in this ſtudy, he ſees and takes to heart, how not only the <hi>condition of man</hi> in the earth, but the <hi>profeſſion of Chriſt</hi> alſo calls for ſuch a reckoning, that he may have <hi>trialls</hi> in that manner diſpenſed, when no <hi>viſible refuge</hi> will be found in the leaſt to ſtand by, but all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane comfort and aſſiſtance wholly to ſuccumb; as needes his laying in ſuch ballaſt now in its ſeaſon, and to be founded thereon with that aſſurance of judgment, as is needfull for that day, when he muſt either get through in the alone way of <hi>beleeving,</hi> againſt <hi>ſence,</hi> or <hi>perish,</hi> and tho no ſuch attainments of light can beare out then without preſent and immediat <hi>influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> from above, and that it is ſure <hi>according to the day, ſo muſt the Chriſtian ſtrength be,</hi> yet does he ſee alſo, the want of ane eſtabliſhed judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of ſome <hi>proper ſtock</hi> laid up of <hi>aides,</hi> and <hi>aſſiſtances</hi> this way forgainſt a ſharpe ſtorm, is like to make <hi>ſad work among the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsours of this age,</hi> er the trialls of ſuch a time have done their work.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. He ſees alſo how the greateſt <hi>conteſt,</hi> which is this day in the world, is <hi>betwixt God, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:205486:62"/>man,</hi> upon the <hi>truth and aſſurance of his word;</hi> and that the higheſt <hi>triall,</hi> and <hi>probation of a Chriſtian,</hi> in which all the trialls of their life does ſtill meet, may be reſolved here, if they receive <hi>the teſtimony of God</hi> in his word as an <hi>abſolute ſecurity</hi> to rely on, yea or not, and tho this is the peculiar glory of the <hi>only true God,</hi> to have ane abſolute <hi>dependance</hi> of his whole work on himſelfe, and to be the <hi>alone center of his peoples reſt,</hi> yet may nothing be more evident, then that with moſt he bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res that name, of <hi>being their truſt,</hi> when the whole burden and weight thereof lyes alone upon viſible grounds, ſo that thoſe <hi>bonds, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes</hi> which he hath himſelfe given unto men does beate no more credit, then they have ſome <hi>externall ſurety in the earth,</hi> which they ſtill looke after, to ſtand as it were good and <hi>reſponſible</hi> for the ſame, which is the higheſt <hi>indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> can be offered to the glorious Majeſty of God.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. He does much take to heart this <hi>preſent period of time,</hi> wherein the fluctuating ſuſpence and <hi>halting</hi> of ſo many under a viſible profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the truth is now one of the moſt diſmall ſignes hereof; &amp; that it ſeemes to be the <hi>time,</hi> wherein the Lord will in ane unuſuall way take this generation off any <hi>implicit profeſſion</hi> of the ſame; and when that <hi>great roll of viſible profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours</hi> in all the <hi>reformed Churches</hi> may be er long in that manner <hi>called,</hi> as <hi>each muſt anſwer
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:205486:62"/>to his own name,</hi> and put to ſtand to the <hi>proofe</hi> before the world, when no temporall intereſt, but <hi>internall motives</hi> and certainty of the truth upon its own <hi>evidence,</hi> muſt beare out; yea that the moſt <hi>eſtablisht</hi> may er long finde it not eaſy to be keept from ſtaggering, and a few dayes come in the Churches way, more remarkable for <hi>triall</hi> then hath been in ſome <hi>ages</hi> before.</p>
                  <p>CHARACT. II. <hi>A truely confirmed Chriſtian,</hi> may be thus alſo ſtated as one who is in the <hi>firſt place</hi> moſt deeply taken up about that <hi>rare plot of mans redemption,</hi> and to ſee theſe <hi>great and wonderfull truths there, not ſingly,</hi> and <hi>apart,</hi> but in that <hi>harmony, order</hi> and <hi>conſent of all the parts thereof,</hi> as <hi>they are linkt together in this marvellous frame, ſo as to make the whole one entire peece,</hi> and where no part does in the leaſt interfere with an other, which he finds to be one of the moſt <hi>principall demonſtrations</hi> of this great myſtery of the Goſpell, that the Lord hath given for <hi>confirming</hi> his peoples faith; and thus in another manner then formerly can now entertain his ſoul herewith, and have his joy unſpeakably hightned, 1 to ſee at once the <hi>ruined ſtate of fallen man,</hi> and what a floodgate of all evill is let looſe on that <hi>race,</hi> not only <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in ſin,</hi> but what is <hi>penall</hi> in the <hi>woe</hi> and miſeryes thereof; yea ſuch a ſtate, where all hope of releefe is for ever cut off in the way of nature or by any created help; and where
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:205486:63"/>the execution of a <hi>righteous ſentence</hi> on ſuch for the voluntare violation of a <hi>law, juſt, holy</hi> and <hi>equall,</hi> can be no impeachment in the leaſt of the <hi>righteouſneſs of God;</hi> But then therewith he does ſee ſuch a releefe brought to light as can not only anſwer the whole extent of this ruin, but the <hi>glory of God</hi> more eminently diſplayed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, then if the <hi>law</hi> had been <hi>obeyed,</hi> or <hi>abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely execute</hi> in its <hi>penalty</hi> on the whole race of man, yea which makes this more wonderfull to ſee a higher <hi>diſpenſation of grace</hi> unto man now under the goſpell then was to <hi>Adam in his primitive ſtate;</hi> whereby innumerable Chriſtians are made to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure and prevail over <hi>ſtronger aſſaults</hi> then broke him even in his <hi>integrity,</hi> which is a conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo marvellous that the great and infinit God only could finde out and effectuat. 2. He does now ſee how cleare a conſiſtence and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is here, that he who had no ſin by <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heſion,</hi> but holy, harmles, and undefiled, ſhould be under the greateſt weight of ſin by <hi>imputation</hi> and by the exacteſt rule of divine juſtice made liable to anſwer both the whole <hi>duty, and full penalty of the Law,</hi> having as <hi>ſurety</hi> betwixt the <hi>creditor</hi> &amp; <hi>debter,</hi> put himſelfe in his peoples roome to anſwer the full demands thereof both for <hi>debt, and duty.</hi> 3. It is here he does ſee that bleſt conſent and harmony betwixt the ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les <hi>juſtice of God,</hi> and his marvellous <hi>grace,</hi> ſo as his <hi>love</hi> is to the higheſt glorifyed, in that mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:205486:63"/>way, as ſecures the full and compleat ſatisfaction of his <hi>Law,</hi> and all the rights of <hi>ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice</hi> inviolable. 4. Whilſt he is thus dazled with the greatnes of ſuch a light, and put to enquire what ſuch a myſtery can mean, he is then fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der led on to ſee that <hi>rare plot</hi> and contrivance of the <hi>covenant of reconciliation</hi> between God and man, here within time to be the very <hi>duplicat,</hi> and <hi>counterpart</hi> of that eternall tranſaction and <hi>ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation between the father and the ſon;</hi> and thus ſees what ever God hath declared and <hi>promiſed</hi> in the <hi>one</hi> to his Church, was firſt <hi>promiſed and ſecured to our bleſſed head in the covenant of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> wherein as with a reverend and aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſtance, ſo with the greateſt evidence of light he is made to ſee here theſe reciprocall <hi>obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations</hi> betwixt them, and <hi>mutuall truſt</hi> for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king good the whole tearmes thereof in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted time. 5. He does alſo clearly ſee that rare <hi>order</hi> &amp; <hi>harmony</hi> of time in theſe <hi>ſignall periods</hi> of the revelation of this great myſtery of Chriſt which from its more dark diſcovery and dawning did ſtill more gloriouſly open its ſelfe to the <hi>Church</hi> by a <hi>graduall light</hi> and unvailing of the ſame, as the <hi>Sun</hi> in its courſe unto the perfect day; yea hath his faith thus unſpeakeably confirmed to ſee herewith the <hi>goſpell Church</hi> being ſtill the ſame, whither of <hi>Jewes</hi> or <hi>Gentil's,</hi> and how that <hi>ſeries</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> hath yet never been broken off ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of <hi>one Church</hi> ſeparat from the reſidue
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:205486:64"/>of mankinde ſet apart as a peculiar people for the Lord, where none ever had right and priviledge to be members of the ſame, but by <hi>faith in the Meſſias,</hi> and profeſſion of their obedience to his Lawes. 6. It is in this <hi>union and harmony</hi> he ſees the whole branches and parts of goſpell obedience moſt exactly meet, and terminat, to advance both the greateſt excellency and <hi>bleſſedneſs of man,</hi> and <hi>aſſimulat</hi> him to the <hi>bleſſed image of God,</hi> yea how all the rules and precepts there does ſo entir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſpire for this end as may conſtrain the world to ſee, and admire the <hi>glorious nature,</hi> and <hi>perfections of him,</hi> whoſe lawes theſe are, wherein he does ſo brightly ſhine forth. 7. Nor can he looke ſeriouſly herein and not ſee that ſweet <hi>concord</hi> as a part of this <hi>harmony,</hi> which is betwixt the <hi>promiſſory, and mandatory part of the goſpell,</hi> ſo as the Chriſtians comfort is moſt fully eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and no duty aboliſhed; but the very path rod to the muſt full enjoyments of the promiſe and proper way to attain reſt and tranquillity of ſpirit muſt be ever here by taking on the yoke of Chriſt. 8. Yea to confirm this entire union and harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more fully he now ſees that exact and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous correſpondence which is betwixt that firſt <hi>fundamentall promiſe</hi> of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and the <hi>event;</hi> betwixt the whole ancient <hi>figures and types</hi> of the <hi>leviticall ſervice</hi> and the revelation of <hi>Chriſt himſelfe,</hi> in which all theſe did meet as their proper <hi>center,</hi> and now have their full end and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:205486:64"/>
                     <hi>accomplishment.</hi> 9. His confirmation thus grows to ſee that wonderful conſent of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and native reſult hereof to put fallen man in a due <hi>poſtour towards God,</hi> towards his <hi>neighbour,</hi> and <hi>himſelfe,</hi> ſo as he may know by <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> how to <hi>enjoy God,</hi> and his <hi>brother</hi> by <hi>love,</hi> and thus by <hi>patience, meeknes</hi> and <hi>humility</hi> to <hi>poſſeſſe his own ſoul,</hi> and enjoy himſelfe. 10. Yea it is in this rare and wonderfull frame he is made to ſee (and no ſight can be like this) that exact correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondence which is betwixt the <hi>foundation</hi> and <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtructure,</hi> how the whole <hi>tract of the goſpell</hi> is but one entire and compleat <hi>mean to glorify God,</hi> and <hi>reſtore fallen man</hi> to the higheſt bleſſednes, how that excellent ſtream of <hi>ſanctification</hi> does flow from that fountain head of ane eternall decree herein, which does ſtill run under the ground, until it <hi>break up</hi> at laſt in the heart of each Chriſtian, by the <hi>effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall call of the goſpell;</hi> and thus runs doune through time untill it loſe its ſelfe in that unconceiveable deep of <hi>perfection</hi> and <hi>glory.</hi> Thus is it that each Chriſtian might attain ſome higher degrees of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation</hi> in <hi>his faith,</hi> then moſt ſeemes either to know or looke after if he underſtood more how to improve this rare <hi>comparing work of Religion</hi> by ſetting the great truths and principles thereof in their order &amp; dependance ſo as each may be ſeen, in its neceſſare <hi>coherence</hi> with other and under its <hi>proper aſpect.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the more deep reflexion and enquiry he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:205486:65"/>hath herein, he is the more made to wonder and finds this one of the great aſſaults to his faith, that the <hi>revelation of the Chriſt, and redemption by his blood should have no greater effects this day</hi> amongſt men, and that the <hi>Chriſtian world</hi> is not in ſome other manner awaked with the <hi>glory</hi> of this light, and preſt after a larger ſpreading and <hi>diffuſion</hi> of this <hi>higheſt</hi> and <hi>univerſall good</hi> to poore man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde; yea the more he conſiders this it doth highten his amazement to think how mens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns in the matter of duty and ſervice for the Kingdome of Chriſt, can be ſo <hi>low</hi> within time, whoſe <hi>deſigns</hi> and <hi>hopes</hi> in the cloſe therof are ſo <hi>high</hi> in the matter of <hi>enjoyment;</hi> or take ſo litle to heart, that the whole <hi>day of the diſpenſation of the Goſpell,</hi> amidſt the moſt diſmal trials may fall in therewith, is a continued time wherein we are called <hi>to keep the feaſt,</hi> and from one age to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other celebrate the ſame, as a perpetuall <hi>Jubily of joy and exultation,</hi> ſince <hi>Chriſt our paſſover was ſacrificed for us;</hi> but oh how rare a thing ſeems this to be, and how litle of that flame and ferven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of <hi>love to our bleſſed Redeemer is now kindled on his altar,</hi> that might be expected on ſuch won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull incitments therto, and which once was in the Church.</p>
                  <p>CHARACT. III. Though a <hi>confirmed Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> muſt be ſpecially ſtated as ſuch, who <hi>knowes the internall part of religion, and ſealing work of the Holy Ghoſt</hi> on his own ſoul, which is not by <hi>words,</hi>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:205486:65"/>but <hi>things</hi> of the higheſt <hi>truth, ſubſtance,</hi> and <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity;</hi> yet is he herein not alone ſatisfyed to know this by <hi>ſpirituall ſence,</hi> untill he can ſee the ſame with the furtheſt <hi>evidence of light</hi> alſo to his mind; and have no leſſe a clear and <hi>judicious tryal</hi> of this great myſterie of <hi>experimentall religion,</hi> for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of his faith, then to be <hi>ſenſibly</hi> affected with the felt power therof. And in the <hi>firſt place</hi> why this is neceſſarly requiſite and called for, with reſpect to the <hi>confirmed ſtate</hi> of a Chriſtian, may be thus <hi>conſidered,</hi> on ſome <hi>few grounds.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the things of religion, which muſt be <hi>experienced</hi> within time, are ſuch ſublime, and <hi>wonderfull myſteries,</hi> as may be juſt matter of aſtoniſhment, and make men a wonder to themſelves, to think that theſe preſent <hi>pledges</hi> of ſo great a hope which is to come, are no <hi>shaddows,</hi> no appearences of things, but moſt ſure and undoubted <hi>realities;</hi> and that ſuch are this day in the earth who knowes ſo near a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with an <hi>inviſible God,</hi> and the <hi>ſupernaturall truths</hi> of his word, with the ſenſible fealing of that <hi>ineſtimable love of Chriſt,</hi> by this demonſtration of <hi>experience;</hi> yea who in ſuch diſmall times does aſſuredly know what the <hi>joy of his preſence,</hi> and an immediate fellowſhipe with their bleſſed head is, upon the greateſt certainty of tryall; ſince theſe are ſo high, and marvelous things, which exceed all <hi>naturall underſtanding,</hi> as the <hi>felt ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of their enjoyment ſhould not more deeply
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:205486:66"/>take men up, then to ſee the <hi>truth,</hi> and <hi>ſureneſſe of theſe principles,</hi> wheron they found herein.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe this teſtimony of the truth of <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentall religion,</hi> ſhould be underſtood not only as its of higheſt uſe for Chriſtians <hi>perſonall comfort</hi> and eſtabliſhment, but with reſpect to the <hi>publick intereſt</hi> of the Church, as a ſpecial truſt repoſed theron, to have the <hi>credit</hi> of this greateſt teſtimony and <hi>ſeal, demonſtrably cleared,</hi> with the furtheſt ſtrength of <hi>harmonious, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentive reaſon,</hi> for ſuch who look but at a diſtance yet theron, as may not only awake them to ſome deeper <hi>ſenſe</hi> and impreſſion here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but conſtrain them to ſee, how no <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſcience</hi> hath more clear, and firm <hi>demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations,</hi> then the <hi>experimentall part of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> (which is the very life and ſoul thereof,) may have to mens <hi>reaſon,</hi> and <hi>judgement,</hi> tho they never knew it within themſelves; yea for this end ſhould ſuch, as have experienced the <hi>truth,</hi> and <hi>vertue of the Goſpell,</hi> reckon themſelves as <hi>witneſſes</hi> who are <hi>judicially ſiſted</hi> to <hi>put their ſeal</hi> therunto; &amp; is now more called for in an age, when no particulare truth ſeems more ſtrongly impugn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then the <hi>reality of experimental godlineſſe</hi> is, and become as a <hi>publick theam of deriſion,</hi> tho men muſt either quite the whole revelation of the Scripture, or ſee this to be as <hi>eſſentiall to the conſtitution of a Chriſtian,</hi> as <hi>vitall principles</hi> are to a <hi>living man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:205486:66"/>3. Yea its ſure herein, that ſuch as take re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to heart, muſt needs look to be put to the <hi>greateſt tryal of its certainty,</hi> and ſhould moſt nearly concern them to know if they can <hi>abide as firmly by their ſpirituall ſenſe</hi> as by that which is <hi>naturall,</hi> and doe thus know as ſurely in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the <hi>operations and motions of a ſpirituall life,</hi> as that they have being by <hi>nature;</hi> and that here is no doubtfull or abſtract notions, but who have had ſuch deep <hi>tryall and reflexion</hi> on the ſame as theſe who dare venture their <hi>eternal ſtate</hi> on the known certainty theirof, as they could thence <hi>reaſon</hi> their ſoul to a ſtedfaſt adherence to the truth, if they were called to <hi>ſacrifice their lives</hi> therto, from what <hi>rare experiments,</hi> and <hi>proofs,</hi> they have oft had of the ſame in their own <hi>tryall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. It doth more ſpecially call for a demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrative clearing of the credit of this teſtimony, as one of the <hi>ſervices of religion,</hi> to promote the Kingdom of Chriſt amonghſt men, which ſeems leaſt <hi>improven</hi> of any with reſpect to the <hi>general ſtate</hi> of ſuch who are within the Church, who are ſo great ſtrangers to the ſame; yea ſhould be judged one of the <hi>great wants</hi> of this day, when Atheiſm is now at ſo aſtoniſhing a hight, that it is not more ſtudied to have the <hi>experimentall part of religion,</hi> (which in it ſelf lyes deep and hid, and is a ſecret betwixt God and the Chriſtians ſoul,) with ſuch <hi>clearneſſe,</hi> and by that <hi>manner of evidence</hi> demonſtrat to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:205486:67"/>the world, as might tend to beget ſome more <hi>awfull ſenſe</hi> and conviction hereof, (when ſuch clear and unanſwerable grounds might be impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for this end) on theſe who look thereon as ſome ſtrang and dark riddle, ſo as they could no more deny or withſtand the <hi>evidences</hi> hereof, then that they have a <hi>living ſoul which yet they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw,</hi> or could ever be the object of human ſenſe. And how ſad a proſpect ſhould this give of the greateſt part of the <hi>Chriſtian world,</hi> who not only know nothing of the <hi>true glory,</hi> and <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall powers of Chriſtianity,</hi> but have not the very <hi>notion,</hi> or any <hi>ſenſe</hi> of the reality of ſuch a thing.</p>
                  <p>But in the 2d <hi>place</hi> it is thus that each Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, for being ſolidly confirmed in the way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, may as <hi>clearly ſee,</hi> as he does <hi>ſenſibly feal,</hi> the truth of his own experience, and have his faith as fully eſtabliſhed by this <hi>inward</hi> and <hi>great demonſtration</hi> of the things of God, as his <hi>affections are quickned,</hi> upon ſuch ſtrong and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrative grounds</hi> of the <hi>certainty</hi> hereof, as theſe are.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. By <hi>conſidering,</hi> his <hi>preſent</hi> and <hi>former ſtate,</hi> that not in a dream, but in the moſt deep and ſerious compoſure of ſpirit, he knows how <hi>once he was blind</hi> and wholly eſtranged from this myſterie of <hi>Chriſtian experience,</hi> which now he does ſee; and once had the ſame <hi>ſentiment</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with ſuch who doe moſt deeply reflect on the ſame, but no ſooner did the truth, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:205486:67"/>
                     <hi>power of religion</hi> ſeaſe on his ſoul, then he found himſelf <hi>entered into a new world</hi> to know the dawnings of this <hi>marvelous light,</hi> and what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to theſe injoyments, and <hi>vital acts</hi> of Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianity, that hath not the leaſt dependence on any <hi>naturall cauſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. By conſidering that <hi>marvelous ſuperſtructure of experimentall religion,</hi> which from the <hi>inward obſervation of Chriſtians in all ages,</hi> is ſuch as the <hi>world could not</hi> almoſt <hi>contain the books, that might be write hereof,</hi> which yet is ſo intirely found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on one and the <hi>ſame foundation,</hi> and does in all the <hi>lines</hi> of this great <hi>circumference,</hi> ſtill meet in the <hi>ſame center;</hi> yea thus how intire and <hi>har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious</hi> a thing religion in all the parts therof is <hi>within</hi> upon the ſoul, as well as <hi>without,</hi> ſo as every <hi>ſtep in this way</hi> of the <hi>experience</hi> of the ſaints is no groping in the dark, but what is by <hi>line</hi> and <hi>rule,</hi> with as ſure and demonſtrable a connexion with the <hi>externall teſtimony of the word,</hi> as there is in <hi>nature</hi> betwixt the <hi>cauſe</hi> and the <hi>effect;</hi> which affords a more wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full aſſiſtance to his faith, then the greateſt <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall miracles</hi> could ever doe; and tho the ſpirit of God does ſometimes in an <hi>extraordinare man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> reveal himſelf to men (as <hi>acts of his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign prerogative</hi> which make no <hi>rule</hi>) yet with the eſtabliſhed <hi>conſtitutions of his word</hi> does the continued experience of the ſaints moſt harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly ever <hi>correſpond.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:205486:68"/>3. By conſidering thus alſo the <hi>being,</hi> &amp; <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality of grace,</hi> not in its <hi>effects</hi> only but in its <hi>proper cauſe and original,</hi> &amp; how the <hi>truth of holineſſe</hi> in the life of a Chriſtian is ſo expreſs a tranſcript of the Gospell, in its <hi>external reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> that the <hi>impreſſe</hi> doth not more clearly anſwer <hi>the ſeal on the wax</hi> then it doth beget the ſame <hi>forme and image of it ſelf</hi> in ſuch as <hi>believe;</hi> yea alſo that conformity it bears to the <hi>ever bleſsed Architype, as well</hi> as to the <hi>revealed ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le,</hi> and how bright a discovery is thus of ſo <hi>glorious a being, and nature,</hi> to which its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, who is the alone <hi>patern,</hi> and <hi>exemple of all truth and holineſſe;</hi> which is ſo great a discovery, as he is made to wonder, how men in this age are ſo much awakened to find out the <hi>true Phaenomena of nature,</hi> (though in its own room a moſt choiſe ſtudy, and ſpecialy deſirable,) and will be as in a <hi>tranſport,</hi> upon ſome rare <hi>natural experiment,</hi> as made one in that manner cry out <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; whilſt here is another kind of <hi>demonſtration,</hi> and of more transcendent intereſt then all theſe could ever amount to, on which the eyes of moſt are this day ſhutt.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. By conſidering that <hi>uncheangable congruity, which is betwixt the nature of theſe things, injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the whole inſtitutions of the Gospell,</hi> and <hi>mens being made happy therby,</hi> now in their <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate,</hi> and how great a temporal revenew
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:205486:68"/>of the fruits of religion, as inward <hi>confidence, peace,</hi> and <hi>ſerenity of mind,</hi> doth as natively fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the life and practice herof, as the <hi>fruit</hi> of <hi>a tree</hi> anſwers to its <hi>kind,</hi> and is ever found the alone <hi>true relief of mankind,</hi> againſt all the griefs and bitterneſſe of time; yea that its no <hi>diſtance of place,</hi> but of <hi>mens ſpirit</hi> by <hi>impurity,</hi> and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption that makes ſo ſad a diſtance betwixt God, and man here in the earth.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. He is thus further confirmed upon this great <hi>teſtimony of experimentall religion,</hi> by conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that its ſure ſuch as does bear this witneſſe are known; 1. to be ſuch who are of the moſt <hi>diſcerning and judicious</hi> in the things of <hi>reaſon,</hi> as any elſe. 2. Whoſe <hi>walke</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> uſe to have the greateſt authority over mens conſcience with whom they converſe. 3. who are found moſt intenſly taken up in the <hi>retired worke, and duties of religion,</hi> that can have no reſpect to the witneſſe and obſervation of others. 4. Who ſeeks no <hi>implicit credit</hi> from any herein, but does ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt men to <hi>come and ſee,</hi> and prove the ſame in their their own <hi>experience,</hi> with an <hi>appeal</hi> to the moſt exact inquiry, and <hi>rationall tryall</hi> of all mankind, if here be any <hi>caſuall thing,</hi> and if that teſtimony of the <hi>doctrinall,</hi> and <hi>experimentall part</hi> of religion be not ſtill one and the ſame. 5. Who alſo out of the moſt <hi>remott places</hi> of the earth, and otherwiſe ſtrangers amonghſt themſelves, does yet moſt harmoniouſly meet in the <hi>ſame wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse,</hi>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:205486:69"/>and are thus <hi>mutually diſcloſed to other,</hi> by a near and fealing intercourſe of their ſouls, from ſuch an <hi>onneſſe in a ſpirituall ſtate</hi> and theſe <hi>ſpecifick properties</hi> of a <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> and <hi>new nature,</hi> with as diſcernible evidence as if one <hi>man</hi> ſhould meet with ane other of the <hi>ſame kind,</hi> in ſuch a place of the earth which were only inhabited with <hi>beaſts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. By conſidering alſo, (with a deep and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious reflection hereon,) that ſure and known <hi>conjunction,</hi> which is betwixt the moſt <hi>rare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences</hi> of a Chriſtians life, and the moſt <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arching tryalls</hi> thereof, with that uniform con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, that hath in all ages of the Church been, in ſuch marvelous things, as theſe. 1 what <hi>ſolemne tokens and teſtimonies of the love of God,</hi> and his <hi>acceptance,</hi> are found uſually to meet his people in the <hi>entry</hi> of ſome great <hi>tryall,</hi> or <hi>ſervice</hi> for him, even in ſome unuſuall manner then, in <hi>the ſence whereof,</hi> as it was with <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah,</hi> they have been made to <hi>goe many days af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in a wilderneſse ſtate;</hi> yea how this does not reſpect <hi>perſons</hi> only, but <hi>Churches,</hi> that the word ſtill uſeth to goe before with ſome remarkable <hi>confirming worke</hi> to ſecure the heart, before the <hi>croſſe</hi> and ſome ſpecial tryal of <hi>perſecution</hi> comes 2. That as each day hath its <hi>proper burden,</hi> and worke, ſo hath it its <hi>proper allowance</hi> provided for the ſame, which ſhould be no leſſe ſought after by a Chriſtian, then his <hi>dayly bread,</hi> and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:205486:69"/>when the preſſure of ſuch a day grows to ſome more ſingulare hight, ſo alſo ſhould the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe hereof be in faith ſought for &amp; expected. 3. How the <hi>choiſeſt mercies</hi> are reſerved to the <hi>ſaddeſt times</hi> of a Chriſtians lot, and moſt uſually croſſe to their own <hi>choiſe,</hi> and thus hath had the greateſt ſtruglings with theſe <hi>methods of providence,</hi> which hath in the iſſue tended moſt to their upmaking. 4. Yea how the returnes of a <hi>long deferred hope</hi> after much humble on-waiting, have been to ſuch as a <hi>Pisgah,</hi> whence they have not only had a clear and comforting <hi>proſpect of their bypaſt tryals,</hi> but for being more fully confirmed of the <hi>time to come;</hi> and can bear now that teſtimony, <hi>that the Lord hath clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all bygones to them,</hi> and hath taken <hi>the vail off his worke,</hi> which for long had been as a dark and ſtrang riddle.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. This likeways gives a moſt clear, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming proſpect of that great <hi>ſeal of experience,</hi> when he can now ſee, both in his own caſe and of others, what the <hi>issue of believing in a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular exigence and tryal</hi> and upon ſome ſpecial act of <hi>truſt and adventure herein does at laſt come to;</hi> which the more deeply its conſidered he finds one of the moſt peculiare <hi>aſſiſtances to his faith,</hi> and one of the <hi>greateſt attainments of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentall religion</hi> within time, when he can thus ſee the ſame way of <hi>believing,</hi> (in ſome ſtrong and extraordinare aſſaults, which he hath had to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:205486:70"/>cruſh and break him herein,) which hath car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried ſo many thorow in their ſaddeſt tryals, bring him alſo in <hi>his turn,</hi> to be an <hi>inſtance in the ſame kind,</hi> to bear an honourable <hi>teſtimony</hi> to this <hi>ſure,</hi> and <hi>excellent way of believing before the world,</hi> and that none fear, <hi>after him,</hi> to <hi>hold by the promiſe of God</hi> and venture on that ſecurity, tho it then ſeem againſt hope, whoſe <hi>diſpenſations, did yet never, never give his word the lye.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>CHARACT. IV. Such is a truely <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed Chriſtian, who in a diſmall time, is not ſtaggered in his faith from the preſent ſigns and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearences therof,</hi> but hath his <hi>ſoul ballaſt with ſuch ſolid grounds of confirmation</hi> againſt the ſame, as theſe <hi>providences,</hi> wherat others doe moſt <hi>ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> tends to his further <hi>ſtrenthning in the way of the Lord,</hi> when he does now clealy <hi>ſee;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. How <hi>tribulation and the croſſe</hi> makes one of the moſt <hi>illuſtrious and beutifull parts</hi> of the <hi>whole frame of Providence about the Church,</hi> and in the lot of each Chriſtian, ſo as there can be no poſſible <hi>ſtumbling</hi> to any for want of light here, that ſore <hi>tryalls,</hi> and <hi>diſtreſſe</hi> ſhould moſt remarkably follow theſe in their <hi>journey,</hi> who have an <hi>eternall bleſſedneſſe</hi> before them in the <hi>clofe</hi> hereof, when ſo great a part of the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> is directed not only for <hi>comfort</hi> but for a clear <hi>conduct of the Chriſtians faith,</hi> through all the <hi>intrcacies</hi> and <hi>labyrinths</hi> of ſuch a diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and thus ſees how highly <hi>congruous</hi> it is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:205486:70"/>to the infinit wiſdom of God, that ſo <hi>ſtrait and narrow a way,</hi> in ſuch a <hi>ſtate of tryall</hi> as is here, ſhould goe before the ſtate of everlaſting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment; that there ſhould be ſuch a <hi>ſtage</hi> and <hi>theatre</hi> alſo, whereon the <hi>paſſive graces of the ſpirit,</hi> may not only be <hi>exerciſed,</hi> but <hi>diſplay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their true luſtre</hi> and <hi>glory before Angels and men;</hi> yea that thus the Redeemed of the Lord be firſt <hi>trained</hi> in ſo ſharp a <hi>warfare,</hi> as may not only put a <hi>due value</hi> and <hi>reſpect</hi> on the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that <hi>triumph</hi> and <hi>reward</hi> which is to come, but be matter of <hi>ineffable joy and exultation,</hi> that ever they were admitt thus to evidence their love and adherence to their <hi>bleſſed head</hi> and his <hi>truth</hi> here on the earth, and accounted <hi>worthy</hi> to be put on ſome <hi>hotter ſervice,</hi> and to peculiare <hi>tryals</hi> and <hi>conflicts</hi> this way beyond others, for ſome <hi>example</hi> and incouragement to the <hi>Church in their day;</hi> and here alſo he can now ſee how the greateſt <hi>injoyments of comfort</hi> are more owe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the moſt ſharp and <hi>afflicting tryals</hi> of their life, then to the greateſt <hi>externall calme;</hi> and that to <hi>endure</hi> patiently and <hi>ſuffer for the name Chriſt</hi> is ſuch a priviledge as the <hi>elect Angels</hi> have not been admitt to, yea that the Lords <hi>chaſtning worke,</hi> and ſoreſt <hi>ſmitting</hi> of his own, is <hi>an act alſo of ſaving;</hi> ſo that thus the more deeply he ſearcheth here, the more does he <hi>ſee, admire,</hi> and <hi>conſent</hi> to that <hi>glorious piece of the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of providence</hi> about the Church, and finds
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:205486:71"/>it to be one of the greateſt <hi>confirmations of his faith</hi> within time.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He does now clearly ſee how the <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>faithfulneſſe</hi> of <hi>God is commenſurate to his whole worke of Providence</hi> &amp; that all the <hi>lines</hi> hereof, as they doe lead from his revealed councell in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> which is the <hi>adequat ſigne</hi> of his <hi>eternall councell and decrees,</hi> ſo doe they returne thither again, to make this great <hi>demoſtration</hi> clear; that if a <hi>full Hiſtory were write of this world,</hi> and what hath been conspicuous thorow the whole ſeries of times paſt in all theſe conjunctions of <hi>inſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our cauſes,</hi> whether <hi>neceſſare, free, or contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent,</hi> and of ſuch events that ſeem moſt <hi>caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,</hi> it ſhould be nothing elſe but an exact transcript and <hi>hiſtory of the Bible,</hi> to bear this witneſſe, <hi>quod mundus nihil aliud eſt quam Deus explicatus ſecundum ſcripturam;</hi> but though a full diſcovery hereof be not attainable within time, yet is it a ſad and deplorable want, that the <hi>great acts of the Lord,</hi> in each <hi>age</hi> of the Church are not more ſearched <hi>and ſought out of all them that take pleaſure therin,</hi> that they may be <hi>ſeen, obſerved,</hi> and <hi>admired</hi> by that part of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Men,</hi> who are only in a capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to know the ſame; which is a ſervice for the Lord wherin his <hi>praiſe,</hi> and <hi>declavative glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> is ſo highly conceirned, as a Chriſtian ſhould account the meaneſt <hi>roome</hi> herein one of the moſt deſirable attainments within time; yea it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:205486:71"/>ſeems juſt matter of regret alſo that this comes not under a more <hi>publick care</hi> and nottice of <hi>particulare Churches and</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te,</hi> where religion hath any true regard, to have ſuch <hi>ſolemne providences</hi> as occurre in that <hi>time,</hi> and <hi>place,</hi> which may be called <hi>experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta lucifera to the Church,</hi> and of a further reach and extent then any private uſe, both <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch'd</hi> after and <hi>recorded</hi> as becomes ſo high a <hi>ſervice to the Chriſtian cauſe</hi> and one of the hig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heſt conceirns of the <hi>poſteritie,</hi> to have ſuch not only poſſeſſed of a pure <hi>religion,</hi> but of that <hi>ſeal</hi> alſo; which the Lord hath in the <hi>great acts</hi> of providence <hi>appended</hi> therto, and thus to have that <hi>increaſe,</hi> which each ſucceſſive age brings therwith to the <hi>publick ſtock of the Church,</hi> looked after, as a piece of the greateſt truſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed theron, ſo that the Children riſe not up and ſay, we have not <hi>heard nor have our fathers faithfully transmitt</hi> to us the <hi>wonderous works which the Lord hath wrought in their time.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. He is thus alſo tought to ſee the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <hi>demonſtrative cauſes</hi> of the moſt ſtrang judgments on the Church, to be as <hi>clear in the Scripture</hi> as they are in the <hi>event,</hi> and though the holy God in the day of his <hi>patience,</hi> and <hi>long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering</hi> is not alike quick in the execution of the <hi>ſentences</hi> of his word, yet does he ever eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabliſh the <hi>authority of his Laws</hi> by the <hi>works</hi> of <hi>his providence</hi> in the moſt opportune ſeaſon;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:205486:72"/>and as <hi>judgment deferred,</hi> is no <hi>acquittance,</hi> ſo does it more threaten its being the <hi>greater,</hi> when it comes, then a <hi>quick and preſent dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch;</hi> yea though this <hi>tempeſt</hi> which now blowes on the Chruches of Chriſt, come to a gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ater hight, and the darkneſſe be ſuch, as <hi>no Moon</hi> or <hi>Starres</hi> may for many dayes yet appear of any <hi>viſible ſigns of hope,</hi> yet is his ſoul thus at reſt whilſt he can ſee the <hi>credit of the truth clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> on which he hath more in <hi>dependence</hi> then any <hi>adventure</hi> within time, and does rejoyce, whatever miscarrying may be of inferiour <hi>ends,</hi> that this great and <hi>ultimate end</hi> of the works of God is ſecured herein, and the <hi>glory of his truth</hi> does ſhine forth in the moſt ſtrang and <hi>amazing acts of his providence,</hi> wherat many are ready to ſtagger, when they doe not <hi>wiſely</hi> conſider the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. He ſees now likewiſe, ſo <hi>high a value which the Lord puts on the tryall of his peoples faith,</hi> and that the great dispenſation wherby he deales with men is <hi>by truſt</hi> and on the <hi>credit of his word,</hi> as it addes further to his confirmation, to ſee all human and <hi>viſible refuges</hi> oft taken out of his Churches ſight, yea his <hi>greateſt works</hi> in the earth make the <hi>greateſt delay</hi> er they be brought forth, &amp; his Churches caſe put ſo far beyond help before a <hi>cure,</hi> as the firſt quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of her cruſhed and allmoſt <hi>dead hope,</hi> muſt be at the <hi>mouth of the grave;</hi> and he is thus here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:205486:72"/>more ſingularly ſtrenthned, that when the Lord ſpeaks the ſame in the <hi>way of providence,</hi> which he hath ſpoke in his word, <hi>not by might nor by power,</hi> that he doth with unspeakable advantage <hi>ſupply</hi> and <hi>fill the roome</hi> therof by the <hi>next word, but by my ſpirit ſaith the</hi> Lord, which in this day ſhould with a <hi>full aſſurance of faith</hi> be both ſought and looked after.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. It is in this rare <hi>ſtudy</hi> he attaines alſo the greateſt <hi>confirmation</hi> to his faith that could poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be deſired within time, to ſee now when its ſo near the <hi>cloſe</hi> therof and after all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions of times paſt, how the <hi>truth and faithfullneſſe of God,</hi> hath, as the ſun in its ſtrenth, ſtill keept its way ſtraight and fixt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt all theſe dark clouds which have been to darken the ſame and is now gone its courſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it draws near to the full and perfect day; yea thus to ſee how <hi>ſignally this preſent age is ſiſted upon that ſame appeal</hi> and ſolemne <hi>teſtimony</hi> which as <hi>Joſua</hi> gave, <hi>Josh.</hi> 23:14. <hi>that not one thing hath failed of all the good things which the Lord your God ſpake concerning yow, all are come to paſſe to yow, and not on thing hath failed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of;</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> did bear alſo at the <hi>dedication of the Temple,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8: <hi>v.</hi> 56. <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord that hath given reſt unto his people Iſrael, according to all that he promiſed, there hath not failed one word of all his good promiſe, which he promiſed by the hand of Moſes his ſervant;</hi> ſo is this now that great <hi>teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the latter dayes</hi> and the higheſt <hi>tribute</hi> of <hi>praiſe to the glory of God in his truth</hi> which can be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:205486:73"/>given by men, that this preſent generation ſtands accountable to make the ſame yea much greater appeal to the world, if they can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance one <hi>promiſe</hi> or <hi>prediction</hi> of that ſacred re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of the Scripture which hath ever failed or fallen to the ground, but may be <hi>this day read in the event,</hi> &amp; under theſe proper <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances</hi> wherin it was to take place in its proper ſeaſon, as evidently as it was <hi>fortold,</hi> and muſt ſtill bear the ſame witnes, <hi>Pſal,</hi> 18:30. <hi>that the way of the Lord is perfect,</hi> and <hi>his word tryed</hi> on all the <hi>adventures of faith,</hi> and <hi>tryals</hi> which to this moment of time have been made hereof, and of his being ſtill a <hi>buckler</hi> to ſuch as truſt in him, and are called to transmitt this glorious <hi>teſtimony</hi> to the ſucceeding <hi>ages,</hi> that it may never ceaſe to <hi>shine</hi> or want a publick witneſſe therto before <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>men,</hi> untill the <hi>whole myſtery of God in his word be finished</hi> in that magnificent cloſe which ſhall be therof at the <hi>ſecond coming of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>CHARACT. V. A <hi>confirmed Chriſtian</hi> in this day ſhould be thus alſo <hi>ſtated,</hi> as one who hath not only attained a <hi>ſolid reſt</hi> and <hi>ſettlment of mind,</hi> upon the <hi>certainty of the Chriſtian faith,</hi> but does know the <hi>pure genuine truth of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity</hi> amidſt ſuch high oppoſitions betwixt the <hi>Romish</hi> and <hi>Reformed Church</hi> herein.</p>
                  <p>And in the 1 place hath in this <hi>manner</hi> ſiſted himſelf upon ſuch a <hi>tryal;</hi> I as one who knows
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:205486:73"/>there is but one <hi>true</hi> and <hi>ſaving religion</hi> in the earth, to which God hath annexed the promiſe of <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life</hi> which can never be divided againſt it ſelf. 2. Who knows that within a litle his <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion will be tryed</hi> in the truth therof at the <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunall of Chriſt,</hi> where each muſt <hi>give account of himſelf unto God.</hi> 3. As ſuch who ſees there can be no poſſible <hi>indifference</hi> in the <hi>exterior pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</hi> of either way, but that ſo high a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of principles is in this <hi>oppoſition,</hi> that if the <hi>doctrine of Chriſt</hi> be on the one hand, it is ſure <hi>Antichriſtianisme</hi> muſt be on the other hand. 4. Yea who hath in that <hi>abſtract manner</hi> ſought to <hi>ſtate the caſe</hi> herein with his own ſoul as if he were come out of <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> to give a ſerious as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the <hi>divinity of the Scripture,</hi> and thus preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to joyn in with that profeſſion of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith,</hi> which is moſt exactly conforme to the ſame, in the <hi>genuine</hi> and <hi>perſpicuous ſence</hi> therof.</p>
                  <p>In the 2d <hi>place</hi> he hath ſought to know, how he could imbrace the <hi>Popish creed</hi> and adventure his eternall ſtate theron, or can extinguiſh his <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and <hi>conſcience</hi> ſo far as to believe that the <hi>holy God would ever impoſe ſuch a faith upon men,</hi> as <hi>this is;</hi> I where he muſt abandon theſe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>naturall reaſon</hi> in the moſt neceſſare uſe therof, which God hath himſelf <hi>planted</hi> in mans ſoul, ſo as not to <hi>truſt</hi> his <hi>own eyes</hi> but others in that great intereſt of his <hi>eternall ſtate,</hi> and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:205486:74"/>with his own conſent be ſhutt out from all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per knowledge of the <hi>rule</hi> of his religion, yea account a <hi>blind</hi> and <hi>unlimited obedience to men,</hi> amongſt the higheſt <hi>excellencies of ſaith.</hi> 2. Where he muſt at once believe the <hi>fullneſse,</hi> and <hi>perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Scripture,</hi> and to be not only fitted for that great end of <hi>bringing mankind to God,</hi> but for ſuch an <hi>univerſall uſe</hi> herein, as to make the <hi>ſimple wiſe,</hi> and that the <hi>poor may receive the Goſpell;</hi> and yet believe alſo that it is a <hi>maſſe of dead, and unſenſed characters,</hi> untill the <hi>Romish Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> put a juſt <hi>ſenſe</hi> theron, tho its <hi>ſenſe</hi> and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is the very <hi>ſoul</hi> thereof, yea thus paſſe from the whole <hi>letter</hi> of the ſame, or any certainty of its truth, from <hi>intrinſick evidences</hi> and theſe <hi>marks</hi> and <hi>characters of its divinity,</hi> wherby the <hi>Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian cauſe</hi> could be maintain'd againſt <hi>Pagans.</hi> 3. Where he muſt believe alſo that theſe are the words of Chriſt <hi>Joh.</hi> 7:17. <hi>if any man doe my will he shall know my doctrine whither it be of God or not,</hi> and that men <hi>errs through not knowing the Scripture Math.</hi> 22. and yet believe therewith, that theſe <hi>ſacred fountains of light</hi> should <hi>be shutt up, to keep men from going wrong,</hi> and that the ſole right of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding the ſame belongs to a <hi>few,</hi> but not to the <hi>multitude,</hi> who yet can pretend no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinare <hi>aſsiſtance or revelation</hi> herein, nor will themſelves come to theſe <hi>waters of Jealouſie to be tryed.</hi> 4. Where he muſt needs believe that the Scriptures are the <hi>oracles of God committ
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:205486:74"/>to the Church,</hi> to give anſwer in every darke caſe Rom. 3:2. the <hi>type and forme of ſound do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Rom.</hi> 6.17. unto whoſe <hi>ſentence</hi> in all matters both of <hi>faith and practiſe,</hi> we are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presſly referred, Is. 8.20. and yet <hi>believe</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that it hath no <hi>authority</hi> or <hi>deciſive voice,</hi> but what is <hi>precarious</hi> and dependant on the <hi>Romish Church,</hi> and thus conſent to have the whole <hi>Chriſtian faith viſibly unhinged</hi> of that <hi>foundation of the Scripture,</hi> and ſubjected to a <hi>ſupreme, viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> and <hi>infallible judge</hi> here in the earth, with ſuch a claime of <hi>dominion over the faith of the ſaints,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtles of Chriſt</hi> durſt never owne, but did fully diſclaime 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1:24. 5. Where he muſt believe that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> came for this end, to <hi>ſave loſt man,</hi> and by one <hi>offering hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified Heb.</hi> 10:18. and yet joyn in the ſame faith herewith a <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſatisfaction for ſin,</hi> ſo as men may both <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, mediate,</hi> and <hi>ſupererogate</hi> above what is needfull for themſelves, and be thus ſaved in the ſame <hi>way of life,</hi> which was by the <hi>covenant of works;</hi> aſcribing that only to <hi>Chriſt</hi> to give ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to their <hi>merits,</hi> which yet their own <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſick value,</hi> and <hi>condignity</hi> doth require as a <hi>debt.</hi> 6. He finds not how in the ſame <hi>creed</hi> he could poſſibly hold by <hi>one Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and man,</hi> where a <hi>plurality</hi> for this end is admitt; and by the reality of <hi>Chriſts hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man nature,</hi> and his having a true and <hi>finit bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:205486:75"/>which is ſubjected to have a <hi>new created being,</hi> each time in the <hi>Conſecrate Hoſtia;</hi> or believe the truth of his <hi>ſufferings</hi> as now fully accompliſhed, and to be <hi>repeated</hi> no more, when it is in that <hi>dayly ſacrifice of the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ſtill offered,</hi> as a <hi>propitiatory ſacrifice for the liveing and the dead;</hi> ſo as on the moſt ſevere and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial inquiry here, he cannot find how one holding by theſe <hi>principles</hi> ſhould goe a further lenth then <hi>Morality,</hi> or claim another ſtanding then by a <hi>covenant of works.</hi> 7. Nor knows he how to believe at once the truth of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> to be a <hi>doctrine of Holineſſe,</hi> and <hi>infinite purity,</hi> and yet joyne in the ſame <hi>faith</hi> herewith ſuch an <hi>immunity and indulgence</hi> for men to <hi>ſin,</hi> as <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> can ſtand for <hi>merit,</hi> and the <hi>rich</hi> have the moſt <hi>eaſy</hi> and <hi>large entrey</hi> to heaven and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it a <hi>priviledge to deſtroy themſelves;</hi> yea where ſome externall <hi>ſeverities</hi> and pennance to the fleſh, like to the <hi>lanching</hi> and <hi>gashing of Baals Prieſts,</hi> are reckoned enough to ſupply the roome of <hi>Chriſtian mortification.</hi> 8. Yea he finds it not poſible to <hi>believe,</hi> that <hi>ſin</hi> by the <hi>blood of Chriſt can only be expiate,</hi> and is his alone worke, who hath <hi>purged our ſin himſelf, Heb.</hi> 1:3. or that there are but <hi>two ways</hi> that lead to a <hi>twofold ſtate</hi> of men, a <hi>ſtrait</hi> way which leads to a <hi>life,</hi> and a <hi>broad</hi> unto <hi>deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Math.</hi> 7:14. and yet believe that there is a <hi>Purgatory</hi> after this life, where men muſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:205486:75"/>be <hi>tormented</hi> and ſuffer <hi>extream pains</hi> there, to expiate ſuch <hi>venial ſins,</hi> as their prayers and <hi>pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</hi> here could not doe; yea is here made to wonder how any that believes ſuch a thing, can ever have <hi>true peace, or comfort in the world,</hi> but doe either take it as a <hi>fiction,</hi> or forget themſelves when they are <hi>chearfull;</hi> where the fear of ſuch a <hi>place,</hi> the uncertainty of <hi>releaſe,</hi> and how long a <hi>term</hi> it may be er this <hi>purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worke be compleat,</hi> (when their own <hi>writers</hi> aſſigne no leſſe time, then 10000 <hi>Years</hi> as need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to <hi>ſatisfy</hi> for ſome <hi>ſins,</hi>) and leaſt it prove a <hi>reall hell,</hi> muſt ſtill be a preſent terrour; nor can he believe that ſuch poſſibly doe <hi>credit</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves herein, who aſſume this power to <hi>change the condition of the dead,</hi> ſince were it real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>believed,</hi> that the <hi>keyes</hi> of ſuch a <hi>priſon</hi> were here in mens hand, and could, by the largeſt <hi>dotations to the Romish Church,</hi> get a ſafe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate thence, it were not ſtrang, to ſee the <hi>temporall ſtate of Criſtendome</hi> in a ſhort time made o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to theſe, and ſhould Judge they were in a ſtrang manner indead priviledged by the whole reſidue of men, who by ſuch a <hi>power over the world to come</hi> can make ſo eaſy a <hi>purchaſe over this alſo which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</hi> 9. He finds &amp; is ſure he could never get his <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and <hi>conſcience</hi> brought to ſuch a <hi>faith,</hi> even tho he made a <hi>ſimulate</hi> profeſſion herein, of that <hi>pretended ſupremacy of Peter as Bishop of Rome,</hi> on which the whole <hi>frame</hi> and ſtructure of the <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy</hi>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:205486:76"/>leans, and the <hi>vertue of all the pardons and abſolutions</hi> founded theron, on which ſo many have adventured into an other world except he would thus <hi>build on the ſand</hi> only, but not on <hi>the rock.</hi> 10. He finds alſo how ſuch an <hi>erection</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell Church</hi> in her militant ſtate here, <hi>as</hi> the <hi>Papacy</hi> in its <hi>complexe frame</hi> is, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ite in ſuch an <hi>head,</hi> as the <hi>Pope,</hi> who as the <hi>ſole vicegerent of Chriſt</hi> in the earth, is at once inveſted with a <hi>civill Monarchy,</hi> and <hi>univerſall impire</hi> over the <hi>Church,</hi> to <hi>impoſe,</hi> and <hi>judge</hi> in the higheſt tranſactions that relate to the <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſtate</hi> and <hi>immortall ſouls</hi> of men, is a thing that as to <hi>matter of right</hi> is as <hi>forreign to the Scripture</hi> and incompatible therwith, as <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humitanisme</hi> can be, and as to <hi>matter of fact</hi> is a <hi>truſt</hi> that no <hi>created being</hi> could ever exerce. 11. he ſees &amp; is ſure that he muſt either loſe ſight both of the <hi>rule,</hi> and <hi>ſpirit of the Goſpell,</hi> or have a juſt abhorrence at that way, where he ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitably <hi>involved in a virtual conſent, and acceſſion</hi> to all that <hi>cruelty</hi> and <hi>blood</hi> which for ſo many ages hath been ſhed therin, when its ſo clear that this was no <hi>exorbitance</hi> only of <hi>practice,</hi> but a native reſult of their <hi>tenets,</hi> and <hi>principles,</hi> and not only <hi>diſpenſed</hi> with, but counted an highly <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious</hi> ſervice; yea when it is ſure that under no <hi>ſecular government</hi> of the moſt <hi>tyrannicall ſtate</hi> that ever was in the world, hath ſuch <hi>arbitrary vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> and <hi>oppreſſion</hi> been exerced, or ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:205486:76"/>
                     <hi>blood</hi> ſhed, as by this party. 12. And tho his judgment ſtood indetermined and in an <hi>equall ballance</hi> upon this great controverſie, he could not exerce reaſon, and not ſee upon what <hi>hand</hi> ſuch a <hi>deciſion</hi> is as was in <hi>Solomons time</hi> of the <hi>true mother of the child,</hi> and who does moſt <hi>ruthfully</hi> ſeek to intereſſe themſelves in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent <hi>hazard</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian faith,</hi> and under leaſt influence of any <hi>temporall motives</hi> does this day ſtand for the <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>ſubſtance of Chiſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> and plead that it be not deſtroyed in envy and hatred to them; or on what ſide it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways that this manner of <hi>conqueſt</hi> is moſt follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to gain men to the profeſſion of the truth by a <hi>prevailing evidence</hi> of their own <hi>light</hi> and jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gment herein, and to require their exacteſt <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall tryall,</hi> and <hi>inquiry</hi> about the ſame.</p>
                  <p>In the 3d place, tho he ſees there can be no pretence of <hi>doctrinall wavering</hi> about the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed</hi> religion, and finds it not eaſy to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend how in one and the ſame <hi>age,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>truth</hi> hath ſo brightly ſhined, this way of <hi>Popery,</hi> ſhould have <hi>prevalence,</hi> or gain ground any more by <hi>ſeduction</hi> from <hi>arguments to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> or <hi>conſcience of</hi> any; yet ſince it is an <hi>hower of temptation,</hi> and of <hi>fainting,</hi> above all that hath been hitherto known, and mens eyes <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſted</hi> with ſuch a <hi>proſpect</hi> of the time, as is like to <hi>ſtagger</hi> the <hi>faith</hi> of the moſt eſtabliſhed, he is thus preſſed, as one of the higheſt duties
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:205486:77"/>of this day, to know and ſearch out what may afford greateſt <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> to his <hi>faith,</hi> from the <hi>diſpenſations of providence</hi> therin, and to know the <hi>evidence</hi> and <hi>ſtrenth</hi> of ſuch <hi>reſlections</hi> as theſe are for this <hi>end.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. That its ſure, as the <hi>ſmalleſt things</hi> which the Lord does afford, to ſtrenthen and ſupport againſt ſuch a <hi>ſtorme,</hi> ſhould be ſeriouſly <hi>impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and taken to heart; ſo does it lay us in the way of that <hi>promiſe</hi> for having <hi>greater things</hi> given to our <hi>obſervation;</hi> yea that now is the time when ſuch as have been moſt comforted by the word of <hi>promiſe,</hi> may be put to the foreſt <hi>tryal</hi> in their <hi>faith</hi> of any, to keep off ſtumbling at the <hi>worke of providence,</hi> and be thus tryed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaſure of theſe <hi>confirmations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Tho the <hi>Churches declinings</hi> under greateſt meaſures of <hi>light</hi> may be too viſible, and that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion gains not by <hi>perſecution</hi> as formerly, with ſuch an amazing chang as is now in her external condition, yet ſees it to be no ſtrang thing, when moſt ſignal <hi>warnings</hi> have gone before of ſuch a try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al with too evident <hi>diſpoſitions</hi> towards the ſame and diſcovery of its approach in all the <hi>cauſes</hi> therof; yea might be forſeen by all, that the <hi>holy God</hi> would not ſtill bear with an <hi>impure,</hi> and <hi>uninlivned profeſſion</hi> of the <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous truth of Chriſtianity,</hi> which hath now long been one of the moſt ſad, and mortall <hi>ſigns</hi> in the <hi>publick ſtate</hi> of religion; nor can it be found
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:205486:77"/>that ever any <hi>Church</hi> did decline and fall from the <hi>purity</hi> of the truth and loſe ground herein by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall <hi>perſecution,</hi> where a judicial departure of its <hi>life</hi> and <hi>power</hi> did not remarkably goe before; ſo as it is not of late this hath been too clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>preſaged,</hi> that ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dark and unuſual meaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure of tryall from <hi>Amichriſt,</hi> and that <hi>ultima cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of</hi> the <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> was drawing near, which would be ſore er it had done its worke.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He ſees alſo, how this preſent <hi>hower</hi> is not more ſearching and <hi>dark,</hi> then it may be <hi>clear</hi> herewith, 1. that now after the <hi>iſſue</hi> of that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, which was betwixt the Chriſtian faith in the <hi>firſt entry</hi> of the Goſpell and that dying Apoſtate <hi>Church of the Jewes,</hi> and <hi>next</hi> with the <hi>Pagan Impire,</hi> after that new erection of the Goſpell Church among the <hi>Gentils,</hi> which is now over; ſo is the greateſt <hi>tryall</hi> of the <hi>latter</hi> dayes fixed on the <hi>deciſion</hi> of that long depending <hi>contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie betwixt Chriſt and Antichriſt.</hi> 2. That ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scripture we muſt believe that as <hi>after the manner of Egypt,</hi> that glorious <hi>triumph</hi> and <hi>delivery</hi> of the <hi>Church from Antichriſt</hi> will be ſurlie carryed on, ſo the more near it comes to the <hi>laſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault,</hi> and when this falls in to have its <hi>proper roome</hi> in the <hi>frame</hi> and adminiſtration of providence, the greater <hi>extremitie, terrour</hi> and <hi>darkneſſe</hi> may be expected alſo, as hath not been in any ſuch manner formerly, yea with that <hi>unite</hi> and <hi>formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable conjunction</hi> of ſtrenth and <hi>growing ſucceſſe</hi> of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:205486:78"/>this adverſary for a time, as the moſt eſtabliſhed Chriſtians may be in hazard to ſtagger. 3. That now is the day wherin the Lord will have men know what it is to have the <hi>Bible</hi> as the alone <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant religion,</hi> on which they muſt intirely reſt no leſſe then it is the <hi>ſole rule</hi> and <hi>ſtandard</hi> therof, which is a <hi>tryall</hi> worthy of all that expenſe of the <hi>pain, anguish,</hi> and <hi>wreſtlings,</hi> that can now poſſibly attend the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Whilſt the <hi>great ſtandard of Antichriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> is viſibly ſet up and brought to the <hi>open field,</hi> as its this day in the <hi>Church of France,</hi> and all human help taken out of ſight; yet does he ſee here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, 1 how this now is concluded, as the moſt <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible remedy</hi> to recover <hi>Popery,</hi> and that <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument,</hi> to which they truſt more then to <hi>Peters keyes</hi> to wit theſe <hi>ſanguinary lawes</hi> by <hi>the ſword,</hi> and <hi>rack,</hi> which they have again betaken themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves to, tho ſuch an <hi>argument</hi> the Scripture ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knew, which ſober <hi>heathens</hi> would abhorr, and gives up the <hi>credite</hi> of all religion to <hi>Atheiſm.</hi> 2. That there can be no more evidence of a <hi>deſperate and ſinking cauſe</hi> then is here, and how nothing elſe can ſupport it but theſe <hi>weapons</hi> which are not againſt the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> or by any ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of the 2d <hi>death,</hi> but of the <hi>firſt.</hi> 3. that this is ſuch an <hi>argument,</hi> (if they have not in a ſtrang manner forgot,) which hath within theſe 100 <hi>Years</hi> been ſo fully <hi>anſwered,</hi> and by ſuch an immediate appearence of God in the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:205486:78"/>of France,</hi> that according to theſe meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of cruelty againſt the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> there, ſo was it returned in a <hi>deludge of their own blood,</hi> yea thus both the publick ſtate of the Church and faith of the ſaints in the truth more deeply root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and tho we yet ſee not the end of <hi>theſe wond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> and the <hi>darke ſide</hi> only of the diſpenſations of ſuch a day, yet doe we know this <hi>ſore rod</hi> on the Church is but as the <hi>ſaw</hi> and <hi>axe in the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters hand,</hi> who ſhall never <hi>undoe</hi> that <hi>glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous worke</hi> which Chriſt hath done and is ſtill fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perfecting on the ruins of <hi>Antichriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. Tho ſome unuſuall <hi>deeps</hi> and <hi>methods of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty</hi> be now on foot alſo againſt the truth, yet he cannot but ſee how nothing could more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually tend to confirm the <hi>proteſtant cauſe</hi> and take the <hi>credite of popery</hi> off the conſcience of theſe in their <hi>own profeſſion</hi> who are conſiderate and in the leaſt ſerious herein; when the world muſt thus ſee, 1 how eaſy its for ſuch to take any <hi>meaſure and latitude</hi> in the <hi>doctrinals</hi> of their profeſſion, when this can moſt ſerve the jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of ſuch a time and <hi>highten</hi> or <hi>narrow</hi> the controverſy betwixt them and the Reformed Church at their pleaſure, ſo as to <hi>ſacrifice</hi> the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> unto the <hi>Court of Rome,</hi> if no leſſe can ſecure that end. 2. That the moſt horrid <hi>Turkish Slavery</hi> over mens bodies comes no ſuch lenth, as that ſtrang <hi>claime</hi> that theſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:205486:79"/>now make of an <hi>abſolute impire</hi> over mens <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> by the <hi>ſword,</hi> and to put them to ſuch a <hi>tribute</hi> of their obedience, and they ſhall then be ſecure, if they but come the lenth to ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their light, and adventure on ſo ſmall a thing as to goe to <hi>Hell and perish eternally,</hi> ſince its an externall and ſimulate profeſſion of ſuch a way they doe thus inforce from theſe, whom they ſee cannot in faith be perſwaded hereof. 3. Yea it hath been too viſible how much that <hi>maſter-plot,</hi> and <hi>ingine,</hi> hath in theſe times been working, to take men firſt off all <hi>ſenſe</hi> of religion, and deſtroy them in the <hi>morals of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,</hi> to make this <hi>conqueſt</hi> more eaſy, that ſuch may have no <hi>inward defence</hi> and ſupport a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the terrour of <hi>human violence,</hi> yea in this way, when they have ſought how to <hi>divide Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants among themſelves</hi> and betwixt <hi>Rulers</hi> and them, this ſeams the <hi>laſt</hi> and greateſt ingine of all, how to <hi>divide betwixt them and their God,</hi> and <hi>act the ſame plot,</hi> which was laid betwixt <hi>Balack</hi> and <hi>Balaam,</hi> as knowing that its no naked ſhew or profeſſion of the <hi>Reformed religion</hi> they nead fear, ſo much as that <hi>old proteſtant ſpirit</hi> in the <hi>power</hi> &amp; <hi>life</hi> therof, before which their intereſt could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſtand, and dreads nothing ſo much as the <hi>reviving</hi> hereof, which as the <hi>hand-writing</hi> upon the <hi>wall</hi> did ever more threaten the fatall ruine of that Kingdome, then any <hi>human power</hi> or ſtrenth.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:205486:79"/>6. Here alſo he finds juſt cauſe of aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, how <hi>Kings or great men</hi> in the earth ſhould give their <hi>power</hi> to ſupport the <hi>Romish inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt,</hi> that hath been ſo viſibly deſtructive to theirs, when its not poſſible to deny how its <hi>firſt</hi> advance and progreſſe to that <hi>ſupreme hight,</hi> which it once attained, and the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining</hi> of the <hi>civill impire,</hi> did by the ſame <hi>ſteps</hi> goe together, untill <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> was turned as unto a <hi>dead image and shaddow,</hi> except its being <hi>enlivened</hi> by their <hi>breath</hi> and authority, as it was during the whole <hi>hight</hi> of that Antichriſtian po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer; nor will it be denyed that in theſe <hi>late times</hi> the <hi>French Monarchy</hi> was never more near its diſſolution in its <hi>right line,</hi> then by the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick league</hi> there; and would ſeem not eaſy to be forgot, how <hi>Henry the</hi> 3d, who had moſt ſought to cruſh the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> there in purſuance of that <hi>league,</hi> was at laſt conſtrained to flee to ſuch for help, or by whom he was <hi>killed;</hi> and that <hi>Heroick Prince Henry the</hi> 4. was firſt <hi>ſtobbed</hi> in <hi>the mouth</hi> and then in the <hi>heart;</hi> yea that the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick <hi>records</hi> of that <hi>nation</hi> cannot poſſibly deny how the <hi>houſe of Burbon</hi> owes its <hi>power</hi> and <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation</hi> more to the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> (without whom it had been fully extinct,) then <hi>Ahaswe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> did to <hi>Mordecai</hi> the <hi>Jew</hi> for what he found written in the <hi>Chronicles of Perſia,</hi> when the <hi>decree</hi> was then paſt to deſtroy all the ſeed of the <hi>Jewes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:205486:80"/>7. As in no times paſt was ever a greater <hi>expectation</hi> then is now, which way the <hi>ſcale</hi> will turn, and what will be the end of theſe <hi>wonders,</hi> when the <hi>neareſt events</hi> of Providence are ſo darke and amazing; ſo does he find this, in ſome eztraordinare way called for, <hi>to be ſtill,</hi> and <hi>ſee what God will doe for his Church,</hi> and with hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble confidence look for ſome <hi>diſpenſation</hi> as hath not hitherto been in this extreme exigence, and tho he doe not appeare in that <hi>way</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> as in <hi>former times,</hi> that it ſhall be in a way more ſignally <hi>glorious,</hi> beyond what hath formerly been; yea does in <hi>faith</hi> thus judge, that then is the <hi>Churches day broke,</hi> and hath found the ſure way of <hi>her ſtrenth,</hi> and <hi>right lith of duty,</hi> when her <hi>hope</hi> and <hi>confidence</hi> is taken of all <hi>viſible refuges</hi> and intirely ſetled on her <hi>inviſible head,</hi> and his <hi>promiſe</hi> put to <hi>ſuite</hi> by <hi>prayer without fainting</hi> herein. It is ſure the <hi>truth &amp; faithfullneſſe of God</hi> ſtands ingadged for <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s fall,</hi> as well as for <hi>ſalvation by Chriſt,</hi> and ſince he hath <hi>ſaid</hi> this <hi>adverſary</hi> ſhall be <hi>broke</hi> and brought down, it muſt ſurely be, <hi>tho the duſt of the ground</hi> ſhould riſe for this end, and now is the <hi>faith</hi> of the ſaints called for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming the greatneſſe of ſuch an <hi>aſſurance,</hi> on which are the <hi>eyes of men,</hi> of their own <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> of the <hi>elect Angels,</hi> yea of the <hi>glorious God,</hi> to ſee who does indeed <hi>credit</hi> him in this day, when there is no ſenſible ſupport herein; and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:205486:80"/>tho it is now like to ſhake ſore the <hi>departure</hi> of many from the <hi>faith</hi> who had ſome viſible pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion therof, yet may it be hoped for, that the <hi>turn of the next tyde</hi> ſhall bring in <hi>moe,</hi> with a <hi>ſolid</hi> and <hi>true increaſe to the Church,</hi> then theſe ſad dayes doe now <hi>take off.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>CHARACT. VI. It is thus a <hi>confirmed Chriſtian</hi> ſhould be ſpecially conſidered, as one who is not only at <hi>reſt on the known certa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inty of his ſaith,</hi> but is <hi>ready to render ſome account</hi> of the <hi>ſolid rationall grounds</hi> and <hi>demonſtrations</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>unto all who ask</hi> after the ſame, and doth thus judge, 1 that theſe are the <hi>proper</hi> and <hi>appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed means</hi> which the Lord hath afforded for the greateſt <hi>confirmation</hi> of mens faith within time, yea preferable to any <hi>externall miracles,</hi> which are more extraordinare and remott <hi>aſſiſtances</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. 2. That theſe are given as ſo great an <hi>helper to his joy,</hi> and <hi>excitment</hi> of his affections to <hi>follow the Lord fully,</hi> as makes him wonder how the greatneſſe of theſe things, which men are called to believe, can come near their thoughts, and yet not more taken up about this <hi>confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming worke.</hi> 3. That the too viſible neglect her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, both with reſpect to the <hi>youth</hi> and <hi>commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of profeſſours</hi> in the Church, ſeems one of the ſad, and <hi>fundamentall defects</hi> of this day. The <hi>reaſons</hi> hereof, with ſome clear view of theſe <hi>means</hi> which might moſt anſwer ſuch an end, are <hi>briefly offered,</hi> in this <hi>preceding worke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:205486:81"/>
                  <p>CHARACT. VII. À truely <hi>confirmed Chriſtian</hi> may in the <hi>laſt place</hi> be herein alſo conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, as ſuch whoſe <hi>faith being oft tryed</hi> through all theſe <hi>ſtages of Chriſtianity</hi> he hath been taken; hath ſome <hi>proper record</hi> of the moſt <hi>choiſe,</hi> and <hi>ſignall confirmations of his life,</hi> to improve the ſame not only for his <hi>own ſupport</hi> in that <hi>laſt warfare of death,</hi> but for <hi>ſtrenthning the faith of others;</hi> wherin he does thus judge, 1 that there could be no true ſupport or relief from <hi>religion</hi> here in the earth, if it cannot bear out then, and that <hi>death</hi> is the great <hi>touchſtone</hi> and <hi>tryall,</hi> when the true <hi>value</hi> and difference betwixt things of an <hi>eternall truth</hi> and <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> and the things of this <hi>world,</hi> will be beſt ſeen. 2. He reckons each real Chriſtian, by his profeſſion then <hi>ſiſted</hi> and accountable, even by ſome <hi>explicit perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall teſtimony,</hi> to put to his <hi>ſeal that God is true,</hi> and bear the ſame witneſſe with his <hi>laſt</hi> and <hi>dying breath</hi> to the <hi>truth of Chriſtianity,</hi> which he gave in the whole courſe of his life; and of that <hi>joy, complacence</hi> and <hi>aſſurance of mind,</hi> which he hath found, and now hath in the way of truth, ſo as to preſſe the ſame on his <hi>deareſt relations</hi> as their alone true intereſt. 3. He ſees alſo, how <hi>honorable</hi> it is for the Lord, that ſuch whoſe faith hath been oft <hi>tryed,</hi> (and when thus with <hi>joy</hi> and <hi>admiration</hi> he can look back on the moſt preſſing and conſpicuous <hi>conflicts</hi> of time,) ſhould have it their laſt worke to pay
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:205486:81"/>in ſome <hi>tribute of praiſe,</hi> unto <hi>him</hi> whoſe <hi>word</hi> &amp; <hi>promiſe</hi> unto them did yet <hi>never fail.</hi> 4. He ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts the more <hi>weighty tryalls</hi> he hath been car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed thorow in his Chriſtian warfare, doth both give more acceſſe to this <hi>ſervice,</hi> and adds more to the <hi>value</hi> of ſuch a <hi>teſtimony.</hi> 5. He judgeth this one ſpecial way and advantage, wherby <hi>one generation might declare the truth and faithfullneſſe of God unto an other, in a family line and relation,</hi> to <hi>shew</hi> forth thus that the <hi>Lord is upright,</hi> that <hi>he is their rock,</hi> and <hi>with him is no unrighteouſneſſe;</hi> yea which ſhould be matter of unſpeakable joy, when now in his <hi>turn</hi> he can ſay that ſuch hath the Lord been to him, what was <hi>Davids</hi> dying words 1 <hi>Kings.</hi> 1:14. <hi>Who hath delivered my ſoul out of all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe,</hi> how that in no trouble or <hi>exigence</hi> of his life he was ever left without a <hi>door of outgate;</hi> and thus alſo with <hi>Caleb Josh.</hi> 14:10. to give in ſome ſuch <hi>wittneſſe for God</hi> I am now near the <hi>cloſe of time,</hi> and does <hi>teſtify,</hi> that the <hi>word of his truth, and promiſe</hi> he hath ſurely <hi>accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed,</hi> which hath brought <hi>me ſafe</hi> and <hi>honourably through,</hi> when ſuch as did dicredit the ſame by <hi>misbelief,</hi> and ſought after another <hi>refuge,</hi> found all <hi>their confidences fail.</hi> 6. And knowing like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways how great a <hi>ſuprizall death</hi> may be, and that ſuch as have <hi>shined</hi> in their day, may yet fet under a <hi>cloud</hi> and goe ſilent off the <hi>ſtage,</hi> he jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth it the more needfull to have ſuch a <hi>piece of his dying worke prepared,</hi> as one of the choiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:205486:82"/>
                     <hi>legacies</hi> he can bequath to his ſurviving friends, in a <hi>ſeaſon</hi> when it hath uſually the greateſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of <hi>weight</hi> and acceptance: it being ſtill qualified with <hi>Chriſtian prudence,</hi> and <hi>humble ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety,</hi> ſo as all may ſee its whole intent is to <hi>commend</hi> to mens conſcience the <hi>way of truth</hi> and <hi>godlineſſe</hi> and not themſelves, and thus only direct, for the <hi>proper uſe,</hi> and improvement of their neareſt relations. I know it may be ſtrang to ſome, what is ſpoke upon this head; but as its ſure the preſent day hath its <hi>duty,</hi> and each time of our life hath ſome <hi>proper worke,</hi> ſo I humbly judge, that this ſeems to fall in as the <hi>laſt ſervice of a dying Chriſtian</hi> to his generation, to <hi>deliver of his hand the truth</hi> which he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and hath oft <hi>proven,</hi> with his <hi>confirmato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſeal</hi> and <hi>teſtimony</hi> therto, and now in ſome more then ordinare way called for in this hower of great darkneſſe, when if that ſecurity of the <hi>abſolute promiſes</hi> ſtood not good to the Church, we might fear <hi>religion</hi> might quickly wear out, and <hi>truth</hi> periſh from the earth; and as ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn and weighty a thing ſhould be mannaged with much humble prudence, ſo it may be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that no ſerious and <hi>obſerving</hi> Chriſtian but hath ſome peculiare <hi>ingadgments</hi> under which they find themſelves ſiſted even beyond others, yea ſome ſuch <hi>ſingulare confirmations</hi> in the <hi>journall</hi> of their life, that ſhould be not eaſy to <hi>hide</hi> under the ground, where the <hi>ſtrenthning of others</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:205486:82"/>is conceirned, and that ſuch ſhould not then leave the <hi>croſſe of Jeſus Chriſt</hi> at a <hi>loſſe,</hi> or part therwith without their <hi>teſtimony,</hi> which hath left them at ſo great an <hi>advantage.</hi> And though this is not to offer particulare <hi>rules</hi> in ſuch a duty, but that <hi>Chriſtian wisdome</hi> muſt direct here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as the preſent <hi>caſe is circumſtantiate,</hi> yet might it be hoped, were this more taken to heart, it ſhould be a ſingulare <hi>mean,</hi> to put a more deep impreſſion of mens <hi>dying worke</hi> on their own ſpirit, even whilſt they are in <hi>health,</hi> to <hi>excite</hi> their ſurviving friends, and to keep <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> thus <hi>alive</hi> in a <hi>family ſtate,</hi> and <hi>relation,</hi> and gain a more venerable <hi>reſpect</hi> to the ſame on mens conſcience, yea to <hi>fix</hi> alſo ſtronger <hi>ingadg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> on the <hi>ſucceeding offſpring.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus is preſented here a ſhort <hi>Idea</hi> of the <hi>ſolid and judicious worke of Chriſtian confirmation in the truth,</hi> under theſe forgoing <hi>Characters,</hi> to ſhew how rare an atteanment of religion this is, yea to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent herein a ſpeciall <hi>ſeries</hi> and <hi>ſcale</hi> of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>ſteps in this confirmatory worke,</hi> by which it ſhould be followed, and where none of theſe may be parted from other, though ſome be of an higher and more abſolute uſe for ſuch an end. And if it ſhould be objected here, what needs any ſuch expenſe of <hi>time</hi> or <hi>pains</hi> in this caſe, when its ſure the eſſentiall truths of the Goſpell are not <hi>queſtioned,</hi> and that without <hi>internall evidence</hi> of the ſpirit, no externall means of this kind can
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:205486:83"/>be of uſe. I know that its the alone worke of the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> to beget a <hi>divine</hi> and <hi>ſupernaturall faith,</hi> without which the furtheſt <hi>light,</hi> and <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jective evidence,</hi> though backed with a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed diſpenſation of <hi>externall miracles,</hi> could never bear Chriſtians out, either as to <hi>duty</hi> or <hi>comfort,</hi> in their paſſage thorow time; yea nothing is in the leaſt here to ſubject the <hi>credite</hi> of our <hi>faith</hi> to mens <hi>rationall comprehenſion,</hi> but rather tends to enervate wholly the ſtrenth of any ſuch <hi>tenet</hi> and take off all pretence for the ſame: But its ſure alſo, I muſt quite all <hi>ſolid ſecurity</hi> in the way of religion, and any clear founding in the <hi>light and certainty of the Scripture,</hi> or admitt theſe things as undenyable, 1 that ſupernaturall <hi>faith</hi> is the moſt <hi>highly rationall light</hi> thats within time, and that none who profeſſe the name of Chriſt can be of ſo low a <hi>ſize,</hi> as ſhould not be preſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and <hi>excited</hi> to be much about this <hi>ground worke</hi> of knowing the <hi>truth,</hi> and <hi>principles</hi> of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion upon its <hi>own evidence;</hi> yea are thus called <hi>as new born babes to drink in the ſincere milk of the word,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. Which, as its clearly in the <hi>originall,</hi> is the <hi>rationall milk of the word,</hi> to be thus received no leſſe on <hi>conviction</hi> and <hi>certainty</hi> of the judgment, then with the out going of their <hi>affections.</hi> 2. That as its not conceivable how a <hi>true</hi> and <hi>firme aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> can be to <hi>divine truth,</hi> but on its <hi>known cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty,</hi> ſo here is no <hi>reſolving</hi> of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans faith on the ſtrongeſt <hi>rationall evidences</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:205486:83"/>yet muſt it ſtill be <hi>reſolved</hi> on the <hi>teſtimony of God,</hi> made clear &amp; <hi>evident to them</hi> to be ſuch. 3. It is ſure alſo, the Lord hath not given ſo large a meaſure of theſe <hi>grounds</hi> and <hi>demonſtrations</hi> of his truth with ſuch <hi>redoubled arguments</hi> of that kind, to be of ſo ſmall regard, as is with moſt, but for ſome <hi>great,</hi> and <hi>univerſall uſe</hi> hereof to the wholl Church, and knew how needfull ſuch <hi>aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances</hi> to the faith of his people would be, whilſt they are on the earth. 4. That theſe <hi>means,</hi> which tend moſt convincingly to found a <hi>ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall aſsurence</hi> in the judgment, are the proper <hi>vehicle of the Spirit of God,</hi> by which his <hi>ſealing worke,</hi> ſhould be both ſought and expected; nor can I judge how the credite and uſe hereof ſhould be ſo ſmall, and not on the ſame ground quite any <hi>externall ordinance</hi> of the Goſpell, which without the Spirit of the Lord can never profite, nor how we ſhould expect and ſuite his <hi>confirming worke</hi> on the ſoul, when theſe greateſt confirming means, which he hath given to the Church, have no juſt weight; but o how wonderfull a teacher is the holy Ghoſt, when ſuch ordinare means fail, and are <hi>inac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſable,</hi> by furniſhing his people then with theſe ſtrongeſt <hi>arguments of love and power,</hi> who hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing had but ſmall <hi>meaſures of light,</hi> yet were not unfaithfull to improve the ſmalleſt degree of ſuch a talent. 5. Yea ſo great a thing is it, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a ſolid <hi>faith of things</hi> wholly <hi>remott from our
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:205486:84"/>ſenſe,</hi> and ſo far <hi>above</hi> the reach and <hi>apprehenſion of nature,</hi> or to have an abſolute relyance on an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible refuge,</hi> for our preſent and eternall ſtate, as no common aſſent can anſwer, when the very <hi>reſt and quiet of the ſoul</hi> muſt needs ly in the ſure and firme perſuaſion hereof. 6. It is too viſible alſo how little the <hi>practicall uſe of ſuch a mean</hi> hath yet been <hi>eſſayed in the Church,</hi> that all who are mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers therof might no leſſe know the <hi>ſtrenth and firmneſſe of the foundation of their faith</hi> by its <hi>own evidence,</hi> then the <hi>generall articles</hi> of religion, but whilſt the moſt uſuall inſtructing worke lyes almoſt wholly about the <hi>noetick part of Divinity,</hi> there ſeems not that ſerious regard to preſſe the <hi>dianoetick</hi> part hereof on mens conſcience, as if this were to be reſtricted to a few who are more know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, learned, and of an inquiſitive ſpirit about the <hi>rationall certainty</hi> of the truth, and for whom theſe choiſe and abundant helps of this kind, which are in this age, ſeem more peculiarly directed. Its ſure, that the Chriſtian faith in the <hi>firſt times</hi> did remarkably then ſpread and prevail, by theſe clear <hi>evidences</hi> hereof to the judgment, made effectuall by <hi>the ſpirit of God,</hi> more then by <hi>extraordinare mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles,</hi> nor knew they otherwiſe what it was to be <hi>Chriſtians</hi> but by imbracing the truth with a full <hi>aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of underſtanding,</hi> no leſſe then of <hi>delight</hi> and <hi>affection.</hi> But if it be objected, it is not the ſame caſe now, where religion is <hi>planted in a nation,</hi> and hath an uncontrollable <hi>publick profeſſion</hi> under the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:205486:84"/>ſupport of <hi>humane lawes;</hi> I know no weight this can have, except that should be admitt therwith, <hi>quod nunc naſcuntur Chriſtiani, ſed non fiunt.</hi> 7. Yea is it not ſure, (tho it ſeems little underſtood,) that the <hi>primary grounds</hi> and <hi>evidences</hi> of our faith are not only as to their <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd demonſtrative</hi> of the truth and divinity of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but are upon the <hi>matter</hi> ſuch <hi>demonſtrations</hi> alſo which moſt natively reſult from the ſame by infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>conſequence,</hi> and are thus to be accounted not as <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> but <hi>divine arguments,</hi> given us by the ſpirit of God. 8. I shall but further add, how ſuch as doe ſeriouſly <hi>ponder things,</hi> will find this <hi>demonſtration</hi> to be not more important then clear, that to be a <hi>confirmed Chriſtian</hi> and a <hi>confirmed Proteſtant</hi> are <hi>convertible terms;</hi> and that if theſe as are under that deplorable bondage and <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of popery</hi> were but once <hi>awaked</hi> to ſee the <hi>truth</hi> &amp; certainty of the Chriſtian faith, by its <hi>intrinſick</hi> and <hi>objective evidence,</hi> and taken off that brutish creduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and dependance on the alone credite of others here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, it might be ſaid the <hi>ſtrongeſt ingine</hi> to hold up that profeſſion were then broke, and should ſee the <hi>doctrine</hi> and <hi>rule of faith</hi> to be of ſuch <hi>full</hi> and <hi>perſpicuous evidence</hi> from the Scripture, as without <hi>blaſphemy</hi> they could not ſeek from the Lord to give them a <hi>plainer rule,</hi> then what he hath there given.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <head>READER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ITs like you may think ſtrang, how theſe</hi> few sheets <hi>in the</hi> cloſe <hi>fall in here, after the</hi> forgoing part <hi>was fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed; but tho they meet in one deſigne and intereſt, yet was not this then intended untill the former was done, and if it might tend to a ſolid uſe and fruit unto any, I shall forbear a further Apology herein, I may trulie ſay, the weight of the</hi> ſubject <hi>hath carryed it ſome further lenth then was deſigned, when I ſo much ſought to be short, as
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:205486:85"/>I aim at in any thing of this kind, that through my deſir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to avoide any unneceſſare multiplying of thords, I sar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> leaſt it may make ſome things ſeem a litle dark at the firſt looke, tho I hope not upon any ſerious peruſall of the ſame.</hi> Two <hi>things I muſt further crave leave to add;</hi> 1 <hi>that when ſome</hi> ſuccinct view <hi>of the great aſſiſtances and confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our faith is here offered, which theſe of the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt capacity of the Church, might with that advantage improve, as in a few howers, by reading it ſome times over, may be ſo far impreſſed on their mind and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that they could give ſome clear and judicious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thereof; it may be by ſuch but ſeriouſly weighed &amp; taken to heart of what conceirn the uſe hereof is:</hi> 2. <hi>That I would humbly judge alſo, it were a moſt ſpeciall ſervice for the truth in this day, to have ſome short</hi> Directory <hi>and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancer of the</hi> great acts of the Lord <hi>and</hi> monuments of his Providence <hi>now under the New Teſtament, in that maner held forth as might moſt tend to ſome</hi> univerſall uſe <hi>of all within the Church. I confeſſe my deſire preſſed me to ſome ſmal eſſay herein, with intent to have joyned it to this worke, but haveing with much conviction laid this wholly aſide, as to any further appearence that way, ſo is it with an earneſt deſire, that ſome more qualifyed, might take to heart and under their hand ſo great a ſervice both for their generation and poſterity. It is ſure the Lord hath deſigned his people to be tought the greatneſſe of his workes as well as the precepts of his word, and as no duty is more preſſed then this under the Old Teſtament both as to Publick and Family inſtruction, ſo are we no leſſe accountable i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> theſe laſt times for this improvement of ſuch as are of known, publick, and uncontrollable evidence, and should be th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> care of each age to have that ſolemne remembrance kept up hereof, ſo as not a few, but the very multitude within th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Church might be as a publick Library and Repoſitory of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
